Is that working now? Can anyone hear me?
Now it's on.
Is it on now? Yep.
Good morning, everybody.
Welcome to the
session on restricted access species or sensitive
species data.
I'll be the convener for the morning. My name's Cameron Slater.
I'm from the Atlas of Living Australia.
If you were really unfortunate, you heard me talk yesterday.
So we've got a great lineup of presenters for you this
morning, and the way the session will work is we've
tried to arrange it so that
presenters will take you through the range of issues
around restricted access species, leading up
to
Tanya's presentation at the end, which will talk a bit about the new potential
Darwin Core
extension on sensitive species. And then,
Martin down the front, he will be
your resident
timekeeper and evil person. If you go seriously
over time, because we do need to keep on time this morning, I'm going to
start singing really bad Australian '80s rock
music and talk over the top of you. So I'd suggest you keep
to time so that we can keep the session running.
So our first speaker is
Dimitri Broessens, who is a biodiversity informatics researcher
at the
Research Institute for Nature and Forest, INBO,
in Brussels, specializing in open science, data management,
and ecological mobilization.
I'm not going to read out the full bio because it's in Whova, but
Dimitri, please join us.
Yes. Okay. Good morning. I'm very curious for the
Australian rock music.
Let's see.
Good morning. I'm Dimitri. Thank you for the introduction, and I'm very happy that
I'm allowed to speak here. I'm going to talk to you about--
This is very small, so I don't see the
slides. So maybe I can go a little bit up here.
I'm going to talk to you about the Flemish Living Atlas, the
Flemish version of the Living Atlas, which we adapted and tweaked from the
Living Atlas of Australia and managed to have it operational
in Flanders. Very small, tiny-- No, it's half of Belgium.
And in the beginning, there was the idea of, okay, we need to
manage the sensitive data. Actually, the question was different.
We need to manage different datasets.
Because there was an organization, and they wanted to have their data
not to the public, but only graded.
So we're thinking, okay, we need two versions of data.
And from this question, which is a little bit different than managing sensitive
data, we started to think and try to adapt our Living
Atlas to
something that will work for our community.
And that's mostly
policy-related people, but also scientists, et cetera.
The people who actually normally use these kind of atlases, we
all know. We have this operational.
We got like 38 million occurrences now, information about the 27,000
species we have in the Atlas and are
visible sometimes in Flanders. About
320 dataset with occurrences already.
A lot of
species list, about 100. And the thing is working.
It's been used in the community, and we are still in the phase of getting it really
launched. We have a lot of positive
feedback. The
only thing, it's not an easy suite. It's not an easy thing to work with.
What I will show you is the difference between the version
of the people who has the access. We have the idea
to have
RBAC, role-based access to the portal, and
people who are just logging in with authentication from the government
or people who are not logging in. One
important thing is that it starts with how you are logged into
the system. In Flanders, we have this authentication
way, access, LCEM, we call it, access management, the central
gateway for your web application.
It's something from the Flemish government, and they organize all the
access to
things, to applications, et cetera, from the government.
So we are not putting the management of who gets the access
in our team. Actually, this is Stefan. That is the rest of my team.
It's only two people. So if we have to take that all in the team,
that would be a little bit difficult.
So it is the organizations, the institutions who have
this access, who manages actually the access for their people, for their
employees, for the people who are working with the Atlas.
We log in with our eID or with its me, it's a token or whatever,
and then in-- This is with the light.
This here, you have to choose, are you an entity of the Flemish government?
Are you a person or whatever? And those entities, they manage the access-
To the portal. This is what a part of our portal looks like
in Flanders. And I have here two sides on my screen.
This is two times the same person,
but I am here
a normal citizen without access to the sensitive data.
And here I am the editor, the admin, the user.
But important here is I have data high res, means that I can see the
data in high resolution. Portals,
we'll go through it and you'll see what the difference is between the
admin Dimmy or the high resolution Dimmy and the normal citizen Dimmy,
which I am
in the weekends.
If you go the top data set INBO collaborator occurrence of fern recorded in
observations.org, that's a translation, Belgium, you see a number.
And that's actually the number of occurrences you will see on the atlas without
logging in. And we have this statement in dynamic properties
where we actually tell the system this person
does have access to the high-resolution data or doesn't.
And the other side, the Dimmy with all the rights, you see that there is no number
on this same data set. But on the data set below that, that's the
high-resolution data. It's on the end, you see "hoge resolutie" means high
resolution. It's not that difficult to translate. There you see the number.
Normally, these numbers should be completely the same, but I come
back to that a little bit later. And also we have this in the dynamic
properties, RBAC. Role-based access is true.
RBAC allowed is high resolution.
So this is what you see when you're just a normal user
and you see one data set, it's gridded data.
These are all one-kilometer squares where the data is blurred
or a little bit more vague than the one on the other side.
You see here the squares, the grids, and on the other side, you see actually the
exact locations in the atlas. So depending
on who you are, how you work, what your role is, you will see a different version
of the atlas.
Going to the species page, also, this is the same observation.
And we know already what the difference between the two sides is.
It looks quite-
Was
a very clear question from-
Finnish Environment Research Institute, Parks and Wildlife, people like
that. And they guide decision-making around how data is
shared by and among Finnish government and authorities.
They're the body that's responsible for
creating and maintaining the list of species that we want to restrict and
what data restrictions we actually apply.
So
that list was itself, again, first published in 2015 and
just updated last year in 2025.
To come up with it, the government authorities working group
made a wide consultation with
various stakeholders and experts.
And we take a conservative approach and apply
the restrictions they come up with to all the data that we mediate, not just the
data that's originally coming from government sources.
There are now a
bit more than 150 species on the list.
I think you can see some of the same taxonomic biases that we see in the
biodiversity data itself.
Half the species are birds, and make up, I don't know,
about
Third of the breeding birds that are actually in Finland.
I think that's pretty much every single bat we have, but then just a few more
mammals.
A few reptiles and amphibians, but that's about half that we get in Finland.
A few butterflies and a moth, couple more invertebrates, and then
a bunch of vascular plants, I think a lot of which are orchids.
So what you might expect.
So there are sort of restrictions we're applying.
So in some cases, we conceal the location of the records
completely.
But for most species, we're doing some sort of
location generalization,
so aggregating data to grids of one, five, 10,
25, 50, 100-kilometer grid squares.
And these restrictions might apply to the whole of Finland and the adjacent
region when we're getting data,
or sometimes it might be limited to
a particular area of Finland, like the north, or a particular time of year,
like records that occur during the breeding season or during wintering periods.
And sometimes it might even apply to very specific locations, such as known
breeding sites or nesting sites, stuff like that.
We will often and do
conceal other information that might inadvertently reveal the location of a
species, like field notes for field records.
And we also make an effort to unlink records that are
part of multi-record events, such that you can't infer
the location of a restricted species when you're looking at the
location of an unrestricted species that was seen at the same time.
So once those restrictions have been applied, the data is then available
on our public data portal, which is a interface to our public data warehouse where
all the Finnish biodiversity data has been harmonized.
And you can access this via a rich web interface with filtering and analytics and
all the sort of bells and whistles you might expect.
And then it's available via our web API and some API clients, and with a
free user account, you can do a bulk data download
via a request service that produces referenceable
material with
persistent identifiers. Running in parallel, though, is a government authorities
data portal,
where you can get unrestricted access to data.
But this requires
a user account which has been limited to authorized employees of Finnish
governments at all levels, national, regional, and municipal levels.
And access to this data portal is logged so that we know who's accessing the
data and when.
But if you're a user that doesn't work for a Finnish government
but needs access to this unrestricted data, you can use our data request service
that allows you to
make a
request which might be fulfilled at the discretion of the data providers or their
proxies.
Requests can be made via the public data portal, but you need to provide a
reason for
needing the restricted data, such as you're doing a research project or something
like that. And the system we have mediates these requests from users
and the approvals of the providers.
So you can make a single request for
a bulk data download that will go out to multiple providers simultaneously
and may or may not be fulfilled.
So
the majority of the data that we mediate in FinBIF is then
published as Darwin Core Archives and indexed by GBIF.
And these data have the data restrictions applied.
So
we use some of the Darwin Core standard to try and indicate something about what
information we're withholding. So for occurrence class records, we
use Darwin Core property information withheld,
and the value of this will consist of a short statement that indicates what
information is missing and by implication, what might be available on request.
Then we'll use the property Darwin Core data generalizations
to indicate the level of location aggregation
we're using for records.
But a lot of the information that we actually have about what restrictions we're
doing and what a user might be able to
ask for is not
currently provided to us with any sort of data standard.
We have a rarity species checklist, but it's not in any
standard format. It's available online as an Excel
spreadsheet.
We also have information about the entities that are acquiring or applying the
restrictions that was not shared via a standard.
We have information on
where and how unrestricted data can be accessed, and we have
more detailed information on what has been withheld.
So these are the sort of things we'd like,
hopefully in the future, to be able to share via our Darwin Core Archives or
Darwin Core data packages.
And hopefully, I think we'll hear some more about the work that the task group has
been
working on to expand the Darwin Core standard such that this sort of
information might be available in the future.
But I think that's
about it for me. So
thank you all for listening, and
let's hear the dulcet tones of Cam with "Power and the Passion" by Midnight Oil.
Will, we are slightly ahead of-- Well, no, we're about on time now, but I might-
Save it for the end?
... defer questions to the end again-
Sounds good
... if that's all right.
Thanks very much.
And while I'm just setting up the next presenter, I'd like to
apologize to the people online that have had a very
incomplete
listening experience so far, but I understand that that's now been sorted,
and hopefully you can
hear us more effectively than you were for the first speaker.
And apologies to Dmitri for his presentation not coming through
online.
So our next speaker is
Johan Wiljegård, who's from the Swedish
Species Information Centre and is going to talk about
sensitive species data from a Swedish perspective, and look forward
to hearing about it.
Thank you.
So let's jump right into it.
Back in 2000, when our first citizen
observatory was
kind of officially launched,
first only birds, but then we had a simple table
with roles, what you could access.
One account, one authorized role.
So you had to log out and log in to get another role.
Kind of simple.
And then we also had, up until 2008,
observation database, which was not even online, but just
local with sensitive data, which was stored there
and gone through to actually
soon or later be entered into
online access.
And then in 2014, we launched the user
admin system along with Artportalen 2,
where we have a different system for the roles.
So you didn't have to log in and log out.
You could just choose your role for what you were authorized to
access.
And also in 2021, we launched the federation
system that harvests data from different
Swedish datasets,
through APIs and made them available.
It's not just our Artportalen system, but others as well.
And then a few years ago, we had a new version of this user admin
authorization and role handling system.
So total available together with Artportalen and the other sources,
we have about 158 million records,
and 1.5 million of those are protected,
and those belong to 111 species. And we have
also an Excel spreadsheet available on our website where you can see
which ones those are.
And we
divide those into a few classes,
open, of course, and then we have one obsolete we removed,
and then it's
squares of 5, 25 or 50 kilometers.
We also have manually then a user can hide their
observation if they choose until a
date in the future, and we treat those as class
three.
And we can also manually hide the observation database.
For example, we can
enter that
and just hide everything.
But the user can also privately diffuse
their own observation, just not hide them, but diffuse them
in those three classes there you can see.
And this system is revised every five years more or
less.
Usually we actually remove or make
species more accessible because if you hide things,
you can't really protect them that well if people are not aware of
observations.
So that's the trend we see.
We restrict less and less, actually.
So, there's different ways of getting access to the data.
You can actually, of course, ask authorized staff.
You can use something called signal search if you're authorized to access
that role
or you can
have a contract you sign, and you can have restricted
access to some level of these classes than
four or five.
And usually it's for a specific region of
the country as well
and a taxonomic, maybe just plants or something like
that.
And you can access these through
three different systems, Artsök, which is the country administrative
board's system.
It means species seek. And Navet, the hub at the Swedish
Forest Agency, and our own system,
Findata or sighting data, basically.
So we have several ways of accessing, but
the authorities, they have their own justice, I think,
the Finnish, was it you that said that?
That the
county administrative board, they organize their own-- They have
authority to give out roles to their different employees.
So we don't have to do it centrally at the Swedish Species
Information Centre.
And we actually log searches. So if data
leak and only one person search for it, well, they
should know that it's possible to sort of pinpoint that.
But usually it's not our system or people that are leaking it,
it's Facebook groups or research papers which actually tell
these species were found here.
So this signal search,
it's a way of asking the question, is there anything here
which I have access to which is sensitive?
And it says yes or no.
So it needs to be a little bit more specific.
So,
you have a geographic area usually,
maybe tied to
one of those country administrative boards
And also,
needs to be a special list. So is it red list species
or,
what
do you call them, the
protected species?
So you have a
more or less extensive list, so you can't pinpoint what species it is you're
getting a signal for.
So if there is no, well, it's fine, it's a go, you can do
what you need to do. But if it's a yes, you have to ask
someone.
And you might have access to level four and it
still says yes, so you know it's in category five that it's
hidden.
We have some problems with this because,
say, eagle,
when they have nestings,
they have quite a wide area of diffusion.
So it's more or less the whole of southern Sweden is
saying yes. So we're trying to fine-tune this so it
will not say yes all the time.
Yeah, without going into too much detail here.
Yeah, I think I
covered that. You need to have your search from today
and at least one year back, so it's not too precise
when it comes to dates as well.
And we have a GitHub repository where you can see this
quite detailed in
how it works, the system.
And then we have a point, a bit different, because since we're
harvesting data from other systems,
we're getting data from iNaturalist
once every half year,
which we put into our systems, and we're planning on harvesting
observation.org
sensitive data.
Then we need APIs with authorization to do that,
which we don't have yet really.
And we also need a way to, if we get species into our
system, we need to verify them,
or we might want to, and then send that data back
to
the original dataset.
So
it seems that both these things need to be more standardized than
they are currently, especially the second thing, what
kind of verification categories to use.
And I think that's actually it. Johan Nilsson is
he who
started Artportalen, and Oskar Tjernvall is the one who started User
Admin system. So
a big thanks to those guys.
And thank you for listening.
So I'm saving you a minute, maybe.
Thanks very much.
And no songs.
Again, we might hold questions to the end, if that's okay.
Thank you.
I know there's an Australian band called Portal, otherwise I can request maybe.
I'm sorry. IT
changes.
So our next speaker is Clara Baringo.
She's from the Brazilian Biodiversity Bio Information--
Sorry, Brazilian Biodiversity Information System.
And she'll be speaking on one of the most important aspects of
RAS D that deservedly now gets the
attention, well, is starting to get the attention that it should, and
talking about
the importance of picking up
restricted access information in relation to
First Nations people and traditional knowledge.
Okay. Thank you.
Good morning. So I'm going to talk about
sensitive
species
more focused in traditional species and traditional knowledge.
First of all,
I want to explain a bit about the
SBIF
National System. We have lots of species.
These are the native ones. We have publishers, collections, datasets,
and occurrences. We are growing really fast.
We realize that all our data is outside of Brazil.
We are trying to repatriate all the data.
People, when publish
data, send the
files outside to other repositories, and then we are trying to
go back or
show the people the importance of having the data as the most biodiversity
country in our country.
We are not dealing with sensitive data at all.
We just use data generalizations, information withheld.
We divide it in two datasets, one private, one public.
That's the only thing that we do. We are really happy with our
colleagues here and also this project.
So
we identify a few
topics that we will need to implement some solutions.
So endangered species, ongoing research, and socio-biodiversity data.
Different topics, different risks, different decisions, different
access rules.
So for example, endangered species, hunting, trafficking, who
can decide which level of
sensitiveness and
some rules to limitate the access.
We have ongoing research, people that they don't want to publish because they're
still studying it. We always say keep it private.
And
And for example here, the most important is the socio-biodiversity
data and traditional knowledge
misappropriation via piracy. Communities
have to decide, and they need
systems to track what's going on with
their data.
So although we have international laws, it's
not enough. We need
systems that carry these kind of conditions.
Yeah, so we need to
implement as a data level, data in the
system and also at a
legal framework.
So traditional territories are essential to conservation, but they're really
underrepresented in repositories.
But at the same time, it's like if we don't have mechanisms to
restrict this kind of data, what is the point to
put more information? And also we want to
bring fair and care principles to the systems.
But so things we need to take
into account, the appropriated metadata,
sometimes just metadata should be public.
We need systems for
the community to authorize what kind of data sets are public
or can
we share or no. We need semi-restricted access.
For example, for socio-biodiversity data, it's really important, for
example, that some data is not allowed for the public,
but to the patents office
to control or to access. If this species has some
traditional knowledge, maybe it won't be possible to develop
a product into a patent
with that. Yeah. And we need traceability, of course.
So for that,
I
come up with three important use cases for traditional
knowledge. One is with the religious or sacred use.
Normally, communities, they don't want to share any of this
information. It's just to keep the knowledge, to
preserve the traditional knowledge, and this you
can put it in somewhere, but nobody can have access.
It's just for them to preserve this knowledge.
For species use, normally it's not the species itself, but
it's the
attributes or the use of the species that must be
restricted. And also we have this,
in Brazil,
communities are allowed to hunt,
but there's
some of these indigenous
territories are in protected areas, and sometimes the managers of the protected
areas, they want to control if this is sustainable hunting or not.
So this
is controversial in Brazil. So
different kind of access, too.
And yeah, the most important thing that
normally it's not the species, as I said, it's the
attributes. So in taxonomy,
sometimes
it's the scientific name or the local name.
Could be partial restricted. The control has to be always the
community.
We need to
be able to control or say what is
sensitive or not. So, for example, the type of use or method
of preparation, and sometimes time and
space, location, and
yeah, we need this
way, tools to control and the access.
So that's it. Thank you.
Thanks, Clara.
So I'm actually the next speaker, so just bear with me a moment
while I sort myself out.
We had a check in the gang, a lot of belt out a few tunes.
Oh, yeah. Okay.
That's an interesting question. We could always bring the first
few speakers up if people wanted to ask questions, but do we actually have a
roving mic? I presume we do. We do? Awesome.
I'm just checking how much time we've got.
We've got about 15 minutes?
15 minutes ahead, yeah.
Yeah, sorry about that. That was me getting stressed out by all
our online people not being able to hear.
So look, in order that anyone who,
for some reason, wants to come in and hear my talk in 15 minutes,
if I could get the
first four speakers to come up, and what we might do is just a bit of an
impromptu question session for anyone that has
questions on the first four speakers.
Thanks, Will, for pointing out how disorganized I am.
Mics
there.
Does anyone want to ask a question then?
Yep, we've got a few questions come up.
We need a mic.
Yeah, I'll rep-
Thank you. Sensitive species and handling them, it's a fantastic topic,
and thanks for the
session.
In GBIF
Global, we don't have sensitive species.
It's all controlled by the publisher agreement.
If it's sensitive, people don't publish, it's not in GBIF.
For the national system, as you presented, it's a very important
topic and imposed by governments, by own law, by regulations.
But then there are global systems, for instance, Barcode of Life, and I once asked
Sajivan Ratnasingham about this and how
resource thirsty is the whole business, and he said that his dream
was to never handle any sensitivities.
Like to have everything restricted or everything open, but not both.
So I would like to ask you, the speakers of this morning,
how much person, years, euro figures, whatever
... you actually spend on handling sensitivities?
How expensive is this business in any units you want?
I think it's a question to all speakers.
I'll get the microphone up here, and then you'll be able to answer.
Thank you.
Who'd like to kick off?
I could maybe.
Yep.
We have
three people working with
contracts and delivering to
whoever in Sweden wants to gain access.
So, it's pretty expensive, I would say.
Three full-time, more or less. They do a bit some other things, too,
but
yeah.
So that's my short answer. Do you have anything similar?
Yeah, sure. I think it
can and is incredibly resource intensive to
do this. So in theory, we have a system that should
mediate
how requests for access to restricted data
works, and then how those
requests are fulfilled. And ideally,
the middle part of that process should be
automated, but in practice, it relies on humans at both ends, and so
there needs to be humans in the middle
doing a lot of work. So there's the initial technical
infrastructure of actually
having the system to do it and maintaining that system, and then there's the actual
administering that system. So
I wouldn't want to put a figure on it, but there
is a hidden cost,
and that's an opportunity cost which could be used for doing something else
that might benefit these protected species, which I don't think is
really taken to account
by the sort of precautionary principle that people are applying.
Which personally, I
sometimes think is overdone.
We sourced it out. So we are laying this in the hands of
the institutes, where we give the institutes the
mandate
to choose for their employees to have this access
or not.
So that's,
in theory,
very easy. It's not always
that easy. We are still in the beginning of our
bringing this very broad, so we will see how it will
evolve in the future. But for the moment, the only
thing what
I see is that a lot of people
think they have
high-resolution access,
and they don't.
But we will see how it will evolve.
Just to say on this that we are trying
to get the most high... And we talk about high, low resolution.
So we don't have these lists in the institute like you have.
This is something that I should not decide, so they have to bring me the list, and
then we can accommodate. But for this moment, it is high resolution or low
resolution, depending on the datasets.
Voilà.
Clara, you?
Yeah. We are not implementing this.
Our
cost is like we have lots of private datasets.
And I'd add from the Atlas of Living Australia's perspective, it's
expensive.
We keep our RASD lists updated every month.
There's a lot of effort going into checking what data's made publicly
available or not.
On the flip side, I'd note that there's probably about a million
records that have come into the ALA since we've ratcheted
up our RASD that wouldn't have been made publicly
available at a lower resolution if we didn't have that system
available. And I think one of the later speakers will be talking
about this, but I'd also reference the opportunity cost
of us making this data
publicly available and causing the extinction
and/or increased rarity of species by giving
full resolution to species that are
sensitive for one reason or another.
André.
Maybe I could just add that we made this signal search because of
this, because all these 21 county administrative boards, they
get these questions, and they have access.
So it's not just we as a central organization, so it's
probably really costly.
Yep.
Oh, thanks very much. André Zerger from Cam and Tanya's team.
Great presentations. Focus being very much on the technology and the
implementation. Have you had any experiences, kind of like the
ALA, your roles are very different whether you're a national system or a research
infrastructure, but are there examples of where you've had breaches, data
breaches, and are the processes for escalating that and dealing with
that equally mature?
I'm not sure I heard the question.
No, actually try to...
No.
We are not aware of any breaches.
I think there's a difference also in Flanders, a very small part of the world.
We have a lot of
sensitive species, but it's very few.
And people, like it was said before, they get their information from
Facebook or from groups or whatever.
So we know that most of the people actually know where these things
occur. So
we have the idea with, there is another system, I will not talk about it,
that this private data, there is an agreement.
It's out of the Atlas, out of GBIF. So we're trying to change this
into there, that our scientists, our researchers, or the people who have
this data are really not sharing the raw data.
That's what we believe.
As far as I'm aware, no. We haven't had a breach.
Couldn't put my hand on my heart and say that we would be able to know if we did.
We're a small team and
we're based at a university, so
I don't know.
I think in general,
we take
restricted access species data too seriously sometimes and not
seriously enough at others.
I think more often than not, the threat to species is not
that people know where they are. The number one threat to species is
habitat loss, and people bowl over habitat without knowing where stuff is
all the time. That's what happens.
So
security by obscurity is a really poor conservation tool, and
sometimes it's necessary, but if that's the only weapon you got, then we may as
well give up.
Yeah, I don't think we've had any breaches either.
People are still hesitant to enter some
large
birds of prey into our database. But even me working as a
manager of our systems, I don't have access, and our
developers, they have to sign agreements as well.
Is it Dmitri or Mura? I don't
know.
I
think you were first. I don't remember.
That's fine.
Hi, I am Udiliyu from Royal Botanic Gardens,
Kew.
So in addition to Taxon itself,
we encounter issue with the Data Protection
Act for people, ourselves. So
anything which identify with person,
we couldn't put into. So like collector
number and the name and the place
would say where the person is moving.
So how you are dealing with that? Because it is a
big issue to Kew, ourselves, we are facing how we are
going to track that and not to disclose
those information. So it is about not the Taxon,
just like the collector itself.
Well, you agreed to have that information disclosed when you
create an account with us,
but we still only show the name of the person.
So we need to be accountable to
not enter fake information.
So that's why you have to be contactable through at least
email as a reporter. So I think
if you don't want your information out there, don't report,
basically. But I know especially women have their
favorite place in nature.
It's obvious they go there every
weekend or anything. So it's a problem, I guess, but you
can hide your observation in our system, although
you're not supposed to for just that kind of reason.
But it's possible, and if you have authorization, you can still view it.
For us, we actually go to GBIF
and fill our portal with data which we first publish on GBIF.
So the persons who publish the data have this responsibility in a way
to blur or whatever. We have datasets where we just say the fishing
team from IMBO,
and then we know it's
that- To wrap up ... and now I'm going to sing an Australian rock song.
So that's in another way for the privacy.
People sometimes don't want it, and we have this whole thing in the institute
running. So for all the data, what has been published, we say we leave it like
that. If there are complaints, we try to accommodate, and we try to give less
names than we did in the beginning, but with a reference to the institute or
to something official.
That was a good song, hey? Oh.
Thanks, everybody.
Look, we'll continue the discussion after the next five speakers.
I'm not going to introduce myself because I already have.
I'm the next speaker.
And for any millennials in the audience,
that's "The Edge" from U2, so
sorry for the dad joke.
So,
as I did yesterday, I'd like to acknowledge the traditional owners
of the lands that Tanya, Simon, and I work on, the Ngunnawal people
and the Wurrung / Woiwurrung people
of the Kulin Nation. They're not from the lands that I work on, which is why I
have problems pronouncing it.
It always was Aboriginal land and always will be.
We wish to acknowledge their elders, past and present, and to extend that
acknowledgment to any First Nations people joining us today.
So,
the first few talks are actually a really good introduction to
my talk, which
is really about the complex edge cases that
arise from implementing
restricted access species solutions
based on our experience in the ALA.
So it's not necessarily
a talk about solutions. It's a talk about some of the
problems that we've come across in implementing.
So as a refresher, and as you've probably gleaned from some of the earlier
talks, there are a diverse range of reasons why species data
can be considered restricted species data.
This can range from more traditional issues like data sensitivity
around publishing and withholding for conservation reasons,
to more unusual reasons such as discouraging people from entering
bombing ranges or the need to restrict access to biosecurity
incursion eradications to avoid risks to
agricultural trade.
The ALA applies a variety of fuscations to over
184 million records. We do everything from withholding
records and images to generalizing records and even
modifying fields.
We use lists.
The
core of our system is basically lists.
They're provided by government authorities at state, territory, or
commonwealth level in Australia, and we use those to implement our
solutions.
We do also try to respect
the
variety of reasons that individual data providers give for applying
treatments to their data.
So our interest
in this talk is really about how the intention of
applying a RASD treatment to a data set can
result in
greater complexity in the solution than perhaps you intended by the
simple
issue of, for example, generalizing a record to 10 kilometers.
So our principal take-home message that
underpins all of these issues that we're going to raise is basically making sure
you plan your approach. It's critical that when you consider
treatments
that you're going to be applying, you need to give attention to what's actually
being restricted, what are the flow-on effects of the treatment,
and what are the risks. And so I'm going to go through a few
examples where taxonomy, data errors, associated
data, and associated records all
unexpectedly
complicated our approach.
Anyone who deals with data knows how challenging taxonomy is.
And it is an absolute nightmare if you're dealing with RASD
and you're trying to implement solutions based on
a species concept. Most organizations implementing
RASD use a list of species at some point that they regarded as restricted.
As I've already said, we use lists given to us by various governments in
Australia. But one of the biggest problems is
not all RASD species in Australia are formally
described. That gives you uncertainty around the name, both in
terms of the list that you're trying to apply, but also the data that you're
trying to match against that list.
To complicate that matter, there's also the issue that not all
states and territories agree on what species are at the actual
current correct name,
and that some data
providers are contributing data at subspecific
level
but the
sensitivity is being applied at species level or vice
versa. So
it's quite common in Australia to have an issue where a government
authority that's telling us that a subspecies is sensitive
is actually only supplying their data at species level.
So there's literally no way for us,
unless we intervene, to actually
make that work.
So
what we're working towards is basically a situation
where we try to account for
that taxonomic variability by applying a precautionary
principle.
So our general rule of thumb is if we've got to apply a species, we
can't resolve the taxonomic resolution, we tend to go up a
taxonomic level, so we're protecting everything by default.
It's pretty clumsy, but
it's kind of really interesting because it's not necessarily something you pick up
in the data unless you're looking for it.
So
I've just given three pretty common issues that we've
encountered. So in the first example, the species we've been asked to
generalize is not in the ALA's taxonomic backbone.
This causes two issues. Firstly, there's no species to generalize
because the ALA's entire system works off a taxonomic
backbone. If the species isn't there, what are you going to attach your
treatment to?
In the second one, the data that needs to be generalized
is
likely to be matched at the next highest--
sorry. The data that needs to be matched, i.e., the data that's coming
into the system, because we don't have the species in the system, the data will
attach at the next highest taxonomic level.
So because it's not in the system as a species, it will attach to
the genus.
Therefore, our approach has to be generalizing any
data that has come into the genus but has attached at
genus level, not at species level, if that makes sense, I hope, because it's not
very clear. In the second example,
a subspecies needs to be generalized.
However, as I've already said, some data sets are only supplied at
species level. One possible
approach is to approach the data providers and get them to
supply data at subspecific level, which we've done in some
instances.
But generally, we've found that even if you go back to source, the
data provider themselves doesn't actually have the data at a finer
taxonomic level.
So
the solution is similar to the next example that I've
got, the third example, where a non-taxonomic unit such as a
population is identified. So what you've basically
got to do is come up with a bespoke solution, either generalizing the
species instead of the subspecies, even though the subspecies is the thing of
concern. In the case of a population, the ALA
has no way of delineating a population, so we just generalize the
entire species
rather than the population.
We've also encountered problems with RASD where there are errors in the
incoming data. These increasingly
are a problem because AI makes these very easy to mine
and return information that you thought was hidden or altered.
For example, if you're applying treatments automatically to a polygon,
such as a country or state boundary, what happens if a record has an
incorrect latitude or longitude?
So for example, if the rule set that you've got
is
you say any records inside this polygon
need to be treated for RASD, and you've got an erroneous latitude and
longitude that falls outside the polygon, what you end up with
is a piece of RASD that is fully
exposed because it's not actually hitting the preconditions that you've set for
your data set, which is, again, really challenging.
If you were applying RASD treatments based on a species list, what happens
if the incoming data has a scientific name in the incorrect field?
This is something we encounter all the time with eDNA data sets because
a lot of eDNA data sets will have the bin number or something else
coming in in the specific field, and it's been attached to the record
in another field. So unless we're
consistently dealing with those things, we can quite often end up exposing
RASD inadvertently.
Another common issue is where supplementary information has been
included in the wrong field. We came across one the other day where we had a
restricted access species.
The incoming data set had simply recorded the
locality information in the wrong field.
And
we had an experimental AI thing that was mining
iNaturalist data for this particular species.
Yep, and I'm going to start singing bad Australian rock now.
And effectively what was happening was our own system
was basically exposing the data purely because
the locational field was in the wrong field.
I do have some other examples. I'm going to leave it there because I'm being a good
citizen. And thank you.
So our next speaker,
is there? Good,
is
Charlotte Lassaline, and I am just
trying to get her presentation up.
She is going to be speaking on
the really fascinating issue of...
Sorry, I'm just trying to get your presentation to appear.
Bloop. Apologies.
Charlotte's going to be speaking on the fascinating issue of
wildlife trade species,
and the work that she's been doing in Australia, which has been absolutely
fascinating. And I seem to be having a problem with-
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you, Charlotte.
Thank you. A lot of suspense there.
Hi, my name's Charlotte. I am a PhD researcher at Adelaide
University, and I research illegal wildlife trade in Australia,
particularly the trade of invertebrates.
So wildlife trade is a global conservation issue, and its scale is quite
substantial. Currently, it is predicted to affect one in every five
species worldwide.
At the same time, we're living in an era of unprecedented biodiversity data
availability.
Open access biodiversity platforms and scientific literature have made
species information more accessible now than ever before,
which is incredibly valuable for conservation, for research, and for
public engagement, but it also creates conservation risks.
Poachers have been known to use public occurrence data to locate and
target species for collection. And so this raises the important
question of how we can balance the principles of open and accessible
biodiversity data with the need to protect species that are vulnerable to
this level of exploitation.
In this talk, I'll explore how wildlife trade data can
be used to inform this balance, and I'll be looking at it from the Australian
context, where I'm researching.
Okay.
So how do we decide what species should be included in these
RASD frameworks?
And how do we decide what species have their locality data restricted?
So RASD lists or sensitive species lists are managed in a
wide range of different ways right around the world, as we're hearing today.
But largely, they're informed by species that have had their
conservation formally assessed.
And so, for example, this could be through IUCN Red Lists, as we've heard about,
through CITES appendices as well, and through government species
protection lists.
But doing these formal conservation assessments can be resource-intensive,
time-consuming, and most often they require quite a bit
of knowledge and data on a species.
So this creates a limitation where species that are poorly studied or have limited
available data on them are less likely to receive this level of
formal recognition, even when they may be vulnerable to exploitation
through wildlife trade.
So as a result, existing conservation assessments and consequently approaches
to selecting species to be considered for RASD frameworks can be
biased towards taxa for which we have more information on them, and this is
particularly towards vertebrates.
And these biases become quite clear when you look at the taxonomic coverage of
IUCN's Red List of Threatened Species.
So this is the animals that are covered by IUCN's Red List as of this
year.
So for vertebrates, as you can see, the vast majority of them have had their
conservation status evaluated, whereas only
1.4% of the insects and just over 1% of the arachnids
have had their conservation status evaluated.
And this disparity is particularly striking when you look at
the huge number of species that are represented by these bottom two groups here.
And so if we're relying primarily on these existing conservation
frameworks or existing conservation assessments to identify species
for these frameworks, we risk overlooking a very large proportion of
species.
Not necessarily because they're less vulnerable, but simply because we don't have
the same level of formal assessment available for them.
And so this raises the question, can we identify species that may warrant this
kind of data protection before they have undergone these lengthy formal assessment
processes? And this is particularly important when we consider
invertebrates.
Invertebrates,
a lot of them are newly described, they're largely range-restricted,
many of them are poorly known in general, they're data deficient, and as
we've just seen, they are poorly represented across conservation frameworks and
assessments right around the world.
At the same time, we're seeing an increasing interest in invertebrates in wildlife
trade.
This leads to a situation where some of the species that are the most poorly
understood in terms of research and conservation are also
becoming increasingly sought after by collectors.
And this creates another important problem for RASD,
where for many of these species, the publicly available occurrence data provides
some of the only accessible information we have about where they're occurring.
So the very data that is essential for understanding and conserving these species
can also potentially make them easier to locate and exploit for poachers.
So this raises the question of whether we can use information that we have
available on a species' trade and demand in wildlife trade to
identify these risks before a species has the opportunity to undergo
these formal conservation assessments and to be formally recognized as threatened.
So this brings me to the broader governance problem, where these formal
conservation assessments usually happen quite slowly.
And even once they've happened, translating that into legal protection can take
even longer.
But wildlife trade doesn't wait for these processes to catch up, and a species
can become desirable in trade and exploitation can begin long before a
species is even recognized as vulnerable.
And this creates a potential window of vulnerability where a
species is exposed to exploitation, but there are very
few mechanisms in place to protect the species.
So what happens in the period before a species becomes officially recognized as
vulnerable? And can we use information that's already available to us to
identify species that warrant data protection during that period?
So rather than only asking, is a species recognized as being
threatened, I propose we also ask a different question: Is a species
showing early signs of exploitation through wildlife trade?
Wildlife trade data is something that is available right around the world across
different regions and taxonomic groups, and is largely within the scientific
literature.
And it can provide some useful indicators of this.
It can tell us about consumer demand, emerging and shifting
market trends, as this is always changing across wildlife trade, and also
particular species' traits and characteristics that are appearing
to be desirable to collectors.
Also, trade data can quite often provide solid evidence that species are being
sourced right from the wild.
So importantly, this means the trade pressure can be considered as an early
indicator of exploitation risk. It doesn't necessarily tell us that a
species is vulnerable, but it tells us that a species is being exposed to a
pressure that may lead to it being threatened in the very near future.
And this is a concept I want to introduce today, using wildlife trade
data as a conservation early warning system.
So a good example of this and of how these RASD frameworks are working in
Australia is with the
Kangaroo Island pygmy trapdoor spider.
This is a spider that is highly range-restricted, has a small population,
and it lives on Kangaroo Island right at the bottom of South Australia.
Following recent bushfires, it was nationally declared as
endangered and,
despite its conservation significance, its occurrence data was
publicly available still.
Early this year, a poaching incident was reported by researchers that had
gone out to their known locations where they had observed their burrows being dug
up, and it was
quite easy to tell that this was a human disturbance.
And so using images of this human disturbance and this poaching
incident, we were able to report it to ALA, and very quickly,
they helped us further that report to relevant state government.
Very quickly, their data was made restricted online.
This happened within a span of, I reckon it was less than two weeks, so it was a
very effective and quick approach. Data restricted.
And can we identify species that are highly likely to be vulnerable to this
type of exploitation before the exploitation is actually caught in the act?
So the key difference in this approach is the timing.
A reactive approach, as I just talked about, it responds once a threat is
confirmed or the exploitation has already occurred.
A proactive approach looks for an early warning signal, such as emerging trade
pressure or collected interest, before significant exploitation actually
occurs.
So the goal is to move from reacting to observed threats, towards
identifying potential risks early enough to prevent damage to these already
small and sometimes fragile populations.
So how can we actually use this wildlife trade data to identify
vulnerable species that haven't been formally assessed yet?
So the approach we've developed, what we're calling a wildlife trade
species sensitivity framework.
It starts with wildlife trade data, and this most often will include some
type of measure of trade demand. So this could be the number of advertisements, the
number of individuals that are being traded.
It could be the market value as well, and it combines this data
with biological sensitivity factors.
This could be anything from a species distribution, its population size,
reproductive output, dispersal ability.
I could go on for a long time.
These biological sensitivity factors, they're all individually weighted,
and what this framework spits out is a vulnerability index for each
species.
This allows us to identify species that
should be a high priority for further investigation and data protection.
We can then ask, are these species already formally assessed or
protected within Australia, for example?
If they are, then they should be considered for
restricted access species listings.
And if not, they should definitely be a candidate for further
investigation.
So in this way, trade data can act as an early warning mechanism to support
proactive RASD decision-making rather than waiting for this
exploitation and poaching to occur first.
So importantly, this isn't just about closing off access to
biodiversity data, but it's about finding the balance between
accessibility and also erring on the side of caution for
species protection, particularly in the absence of so much
data and knowledge on these species.
For vulnerable species, sensitive locality data would ideally be
obscured, not removed, while retaining access by request
and allowing for the restrictions to be renewed and reviewed as
more research comes out about these species.
Because for some species, particularly for the range-restricted invertebrates that
I've talked about today, the removal of even a few individuals from their
population could have significant consequences on them.
So the goal is therefore to use whatever data we have available
to identify potential risks early enough to protect these vulnerable species,
rather than waiting until the damage and the poaching has already been done.
Thanks.
Thanks, Charlotte.
So, I guess that's it.
Yep.
So, thanks. Our next speaker is Tanya Latey
from the
Atlas of Living Australia.
And
Tanya's presentation will be a nice round-out to the talks today and focused on the
activities of the
restricted access species/sensitive
species
working group, and I will hand over to you.
Thank you.
Okay.
So, as Cam has said, I'll be talking
about the work of... Oh,
the
what was it?
If you follow.
Cool.
I'll be talking about the work of the
TADWIG
Sensitive Species Extension
Task Group. And we're up to,
and I think a number of you already have seen a lot of these slides
already, so apologies for that.
We've been convening, the
ALA,
mostly Cam, I, and Simon Sharon, who I think is
online,
have been
convening the task group internationally, and we've had quite a number of
meetings so far.
But I'd also like to thank GBIF,
who also co-convene, and we've had a lot of involvement from,
and on convening as well from GAIA Resources,
which is a company in Australia.
So as I said, we're convening this task group to develop a
new standard to provide more visibility to users of data on the
reasons why a species may be considered sensitive, and also
the treatments which have been applied to generalize the data in some way.
The task group arose out of a workshop at the 2023
TADWIG meeting in Hobart, where we decided to develop a new
Darwin Core extension based on
Arthur Chapman's work and make amendments to it to
fit use cases.
And we also wanted to define a set of sensitive fields similar to the
pick list for data sensitive reason, which is defined in Chapman
as well.
So as
I said, conveners are from ALA, GAIA Resources, and GBIF,
and membership includes representatives from government,
university data providers, and data aggregators across
several countries, and some of who also are here today.
We first met in September 24, and we've had several meetings since.
We've developed a proposed set of vocabularies for RASD
reasons and treatments. We've also collated a set of use
cases from the task group from real-world examples.
We're now in the process of preparing the draft
documentation for the TADWIG maintenance group
for review and ratification. So we hope to get that submitted by the
end of this year.
Can I get it to move?
It's all right. Got it.
So as you've-- This is probably just rehashing what everybody else has said, but
sensitive species data are basically data about species that have features
that mean there are reasons for withholding the data from public view or modifying
the data before it is made public.
And we're tending to use the terminology of restricted access
species data within the task group now because of the word
"sensitive" tends to cause people to feel reticent about sharing their data
rather than about making it open, but in a way that protects
the sensitivities of the data.
And most of what the task group has been talking about is how we can go about
protecting the importance of this kind of sensitive data,
but still allow the data to be accessible in some form to
people who need to see it.
That includes people like researchers or decision-makers.
So
the image on this page,
as you've seen similar examples from other
speakers today, it provides a practical example of
what
this looks like in practice. So on
the bottom left-hand side
are records for a species that is
sensitive
in South Australia, which is on the right-hand side, and the left-hand side is not
considered sensitive, which is in the state of Victoria in Australia.
So you can see we basically do a similar
treatment to others where we generalize the data or
we
basically snap it to
either a one- or 10-degree grid.
So another feature of restricted access species data that it tends to
vary on the data custodian that we're talking to or
the administration that you're dealing with.
So
as you can see there as an example.
So the RASD reasons that we've come up with
to form the vocabulary.
So they're things like personal information and privacy,
which may either be a lack of consent or
someone's asked for request for privacy for their information.
Sensitive species location, so this might be where a
species is highly restricted, there's a threatened
population, there's exposure via survey
information.
Don't know why it went--
Or a potential harm to people or property, or there might be
a lack of information about the species.
Biosecurity risk, so there might be trade species or invasive
species.
Species attributes might
be something that might need to be restricted.
So other people have talked about
things like roosting sites or nesting
occurrences. So that sort of information might be something that might be
restricted within a record, not the whole record itself.
And there may be usage restrictions on the data.
So there might be a legal contract or other reasons
for withholding the data or
generalizing the data in some way.
And last but not least, First Nations cultural significance.
So there might be culturally significant species or
significant information,
or it might be a particularly
sensitive or significant location, such as a sacred site.
Treatments we've come up with.
We've done a hierarchical
vocabulary.
And hopefully we've captured most things, so obfuscation of coordinates,
and that might be truncating standardization to a grid, snapping to
a centroid of a polygon or
randomizing
the data points. Generalizing attributes can be generalizing
taxon level. So if you're going from, as Cam's example had,
was
generalizing to higher taxonomy
rather than keeping the
subspecies name or the species name that's sensitive or
generalizing the locality information.
So that's a textural locality information.
Generalization of dates, so generalizing date to month, to year, to
decade
or withholding data. So that might be just withholding records, withholding
particular attributes, embargoing a data set
for a specific period, or a record for a
specific period or attributes, or withholding the data set entirely.
So the vocabularies can be applied in a one-to-many relationship with a Darwin
Core record or data set similar to the measurement or fact Darwin Core
extension.
A RASD treatment needs a RASD reason associated with it.
A RASD reason may require more than one treatment being applied.
A record may also have more than one RASD reason and therefore
treatment applied.
So the purpose of having the subcategories are so that data custodians can
comply with the basic fair principles as they apply to
restricted access records, and the extension can handle the
breadth of restricted access species data management actions across
multiple
data custodians.
So now we want to move a bit more into the technical
implementation of how to use the extension within the two Darwin Core
data models.
So firstly, Darwin Core Native, or the Darwin Core Archive, or what we're
calling Darwin Core Native in the task group, which is basically the Darwin Core
archive. So this model has a star schema,
as you can see on
the right-hand side,
with a core in the middle, and then the other higher class nodes that point towards
a core. The treatment would be in a similar vein to one of those outer
edges of the star that are pointing to the core.
So that would be where we'd put treatments.
Secondly, the Darwin Core data package.
This would be similar in vein in that the treatment is its own kind of
class and would be joined to other classes using join tables such as the event
treatment table shown here.
When implementing the RASD treatments and reasons into the Darwin Core data
package, the treatment is applied to a core entity via a join table.
So you can see in the diagram that we've now got the event treatment
table. This join table includes the two identifiers of what you're
treating, i.e. the event ID, occurrence ID, and the treatment
itself. And then, of course, with the treatment, you'll have external
links to the treatment reason and treatment type vocabularies.
So this is just a brief flash. Don't try and read it.
We have draft schema in code to describe all the fields.
This includes vocabularies as code and one that's
implementable potentially with all the other GB
vocabularies that are heavily used in Darwin Core.
I'll show you on the next slide what this looks like in detail.
I'm not going to show you all the fields, but these
show you what might be in a Darwin Core data package.
But it also includes a lot of the Erian links to the vocabularies
as a whole concept schema.
So we have a treatment field. This is the target field to which the
treatment applies. So
it might be things like decimal latitude or longitude if
you're obfuscating a location, or it might be the locality field as another
example of an attribute field. When a record is being
withheld, then this treatment field will be blank because there's more
than one field that's being targeted.
Treatment reason. This is where we would be using the terms for the
vocabulary, as would the treatment type.
So this is where the vocabularies are used to show the implementation of the
treatment. Treatment description.
This is a free text field, which you can put more information about
the treatment that's been applied.
You can put more detail about the descriptions of what you've actually done to
treat the record. And the treatment start and end date can be things where
it might be an incident where someone's asked to embargo a
record for a particular period and then release it publicly.
So this will capture that information.
Treatment organization is who actually asked to apply the
treatment. And then treatment in effect is a bit contentious, but
I'm not sure this will still be in there at the end
when we go to publish the
publishers standard.
But this is just to allow a differentiation
between whether the treatment is the one that is currently being applied to the
data or whether there is another treatment that has taken precedence on the same
data.
So that might also need to be taken into consideration when
considering provision of access to the raw data.
I'm just going to take you through one case study
with a few different
examples within it.
So
this is an example of where we've got a troglobitic
spider in a cave,
and
there's also fossils discovered there and records of fossils,
and there's also these new mites that we've discovered, or that have been
discovered.
So there's three groups of taxa which are considered RASD in this
case, the troglobitic spider, the new species of
mites, and the fossil
records. So although the spider itself is not sensitive, the reason
why the data about it is restricted is that there is
information in the record which describes it as a troglobitic or cave-dwelling
spider, and this in turn could alert cavers to the fact that there are
caves in the area which could lead to destruction or damaging
of their habitat.
Similarly, the presence of fossils also alerts users to the
locality of caves, together with potential illegal fossil
collection. And the mites are sensitive because they have not yet been
described, and the taxonomist wants to keep the information on their localities
withheld until his description has been published.
So as you can see, there's three class tables: event, occurrence, treatment,
and two join tables. So the event treatment and the occurrence
treatment.
For ease of demonstration, the treatment tables are shown as separate, but they are
actually illustrating three different entries to the same treatment table.
With the Darwin Core data package, the location of records or species is attached
to the event as opposed to the occurrence, which you're more likely to see with
Darwin Core Native. So we'll start with the troglobitic spider and how we might
deal with this. There's information in the occurrence remarks field which
identifies the spider as troglofauna.
This indicates to the user that the species dwells in caves,
so there must be a cave in that locality.
There's a risk that cavers might enter the site and cause damage to habitat.
fossils or the cave itself.
In this case, we've applied two types of treatments to the record.
We've applied obfuscations to the decimal latitude and decimal
longitude and withheld the occurrence remarks field.
The first join table takes the event to two treatments.
These have been split up because it's two different fields that are applying a
treatment to. One is the decimal latitude and one is the decimal
longitude. Then we've got
a link to the vocabulary, the treatment type, coordinates truncated.
The description gives you more information about how the coordinates have been
truncated. In this instance, they've been generalized to 10 kilometers.
It also includes organization, which in this case is the State
Department of Environment. The treatment in effect is true because this treatment
has been applied and the value has been truncated.
Then to further reduce the potential of cavers finding out that
there is a cave at the location, we withhold the occurrence remarks attribute.
The treatment type in this case is attributes withheld, and the treatment
description tells the user which attributes have been withheld.
The second issue in this use case I'll go through
is
that we have a new species of mite, which also would have their
coordinates obfuscated as they are in the same location as a cave.
The particular issue we're trying to address here is the mites are new species, and
the authors of the paper describing them want to embargo the data before it's
published.
The RASD reason in this case is categorized as non-legal reason, and the
treatment type is an embargoed record.
And the embargo period is one year.
We can use the start date and the end date columns on these records to capture this
information.
The organization in this case is different to the spider, but both of the
treatments are in effect, but affecting different parts of the data.
That's it that I have to say. And I'd like to
acknowledge all the members of the TADWIG task group that have been
helping us
pull this information together, and particularly Mica Strong and
Simon Shewan for working out the technical details, and Cam for convening the
group and keeping us moving forward.
Thank you.
Do you want question time now?
Yeah, you may as well stay up.
Well.
If I could get all the speakers to come up again and
indulge in some ritual humiliation on stage.
What I thought we'd do now is a
Q&A session.
You've now had a chance to have a look at
the
proposed extension and heard some of the range
of issues.
I do have a couple of questions online, and-
There was two
... we'll try to go through some of those first.
Sorry?
There was one from last time that we didn't get to. We'll start with that.
Okay. Yeah.
Okay.
I am Morten Aronson, also Sweden, a colleague of Johan.
So it was more of a comment on what was
discussed the last
question session on
just between what is public, what is
hidden. It's always a balance between,
and very much trust from the reporters
because
there are rather many that just report it.
They know that the
reports will not get public, but will be
used of the county boards and agency,
those who should protect
birds' nests or so, whatever. But this is also something that
changing over time. So, and new generation
of biologists thinking in another way and
are, or the criminality
around
especially
birds and some orchids and, yeah,
some butterflies and so on. It's also changing over time.
So it's
sometimes the most gets, should say, better on the,
should say, the public way, but there are also
some
things that get more problematic.
Sometimes someone
just--
some restaurant
get very famous on
serving something with some quite rare
plant in the recipes, and suddenly everybody should
pick it, and even in nature reserves and whatever,
they are just totally
freaked out. So it's always a way
of
being, should say, on
our toes when we work
with that. And that was also interesting to see
from our, from Sweden, how you see on that,
how much on the, should say, on the
edge
you need to be to just really protect what should be protected.
Who would like to, uh...
I'm stumped with the first question.
Oh.
Well, start with Morten.
I can probably kick off.
One of the interesting things about
RASD is that it does have currency, and it does change
over time. As you know, you do get
changes in what can
Is considered
as RASD.
I
doubt whether there would be
many organizations in the biodiversity sector, rightly or
wrongly, that were even thinking about, for example,
cultural sensitivity if you go back 15 years.
Whereas now it's an important thing, and it's an important thing because we've
evolved our understanding.
I take what you say about the idea of
a
plant briefly becoming
a part of a culinary trend and consequently
becoming RASD, and that does indeed happen.
I think all that we can do is have
an infrastructure that can respond to those changes quickly.
And I think some of the things that Charlotte
pointed out,
trying
to be as cutting-edge as we can be in the
identification of a growing trend,
deal with that growing trend
as adroitly as possible is about all we can really do.
I don't know if that really answers your question, but yeah.
I think it suits a little bit in the whole discussion,
but aren't we a little too late
for all this?
Because I was just looking for the place where I could find the
Kangaroo Island pigmy spider, and Gemini gave me
actually
the hostels where I could stay and what place and where I should look.
And another thing is that the occurrences are online, but I don't think
that's the reason anymore, because all of what we did already is already indexed
and is in the AI. And then I checked for an
orchid, which we have
not so many of these pieces, but one in Flanders, the Groenendaal orchid.
I don't know the Latin name or
the English name. And I said, "Where can I find?" "Oh, yeah, but it's protected,
and you can find it in this and there and there."
But the data is, and that's what the AI told me, the data is in a
grid, but if you look good, you can find
where it is. That's my response on the AI.
So maybe are we just a little bit too late because everything that we did before,
it's already in all the systems.
Yeah. In actual fact, the spider that
Charlotte was talking about, just before this session, I tried
asking ChatGPT, "Where can I find a spider?" And it told me,
because the data had already been mined a number of years ago.
On the other hand, when I tried looking up a species that's been,
in Australia, treated as restricted access species for five years,
ChatGPT said, "I'm sorry, the data on this is restricted, and it's
inappropriate that you asked where it is." So
But I don't know. I'm still not sure it's only the data because there's-
No
... a lot of other information which will really guide you.
And as we have this discussion, a lot of people with bad intentions will keep
on having bad intentions. Even if we open the data, a lot of the
data is open, they will find their ways, even if it's without our
infrastructure. Unfortunately,
it is the case.
I'm going to ask one of the questions online, which rather vexingly I
can't seem to find on my own copy of WHOVA, which is not very handy.
But via the circuitous route of Australia,
the question is: It seems restrictions are mostly
based on sensitivity of species, but it is also common to do
location obfuscations on request from data collectors,
as in some might be more eager to collect data if they know the data is
obfuscated for the public. Now, I know I can comment on this, but would someone
else like to talk about it?
Yep.
So, yes.
Species are general--
RASD is often based on the sensitivity of
species.
We've got data sets in the ALA where the
condition of sharing data with the ALA was
generalization of all of the data in the data set.
So, a classic example was
a
vertebrate pest data set in Australia.
Deer and pigs are commonly hunted for recreation.
It doesn't have, I suppose, the je ne sais quoi that it has
in Europe as an activity.
There's a lot of illegal hunting. It's not very highly
regarded in Australia, and hunters will actually
use systems like the ALA to
trespass onto people's property to shoot things.
And so quite often, that kind of data set will be
obscured in its entirety as
a precondition of sharing. Another one would be indigenous data sets.
We've had several recent indigenous data sets where the condition
of sharing them has been generalization of the entire data
set. Don't know if anyone else had any
thoughts
or not.
Apparently not. Then the next question online
is: Why would bats be restricted?
Mm-hmm.
Bats.
I think that was
for you.
I don't know. You'd have to ask the bat people.
They need habitat restriction.
They're in habitat restriction, yeah.
But specifically in Finland, I think
their
attributes of particularly roosting sites are prone to-
Sensitive to disturbances from people, and it's a
precautionary approach to not reveal the actual specific roosting
locations so that
threatened species aren't--
I don't know.
I think for us it depends on the certain species.
Some are really, really rare, so they have the whole group, because people cannot
recognize one from another.
On the other hand, we have a data set published which is a very precise location of
their roosting places because we do it for--
That's a difficult one in English.
Maybe, Niels, you can help me. So care for old buildings.
So if they want to renovate old monumental buildings, they want to
know if there are,
bats in
the attic or whatever. So we went there getting some
DNA from all the droppings, et cetera.
So they really want to know where it is.
So it's one with another, I guess.
It's not always one list for species because there are several reasons to do it
differently.
There might be one good example of it's not just about the species themselves,
it's more about the people. So-
There's one more
... it's quite likely that they ended up on the list just because an
individual or a group of individuals really cared about it.
And like I said in my talk, you can see a lot of the taxonomic biases that we see
in biodiversity data. There's a reason why we have a lot of bird data,
because people love birds, and
it's also the same reason they're on the restricted access species list.
There's probably a lot of species that are under threat, but no one cares, so they
don't get on there.
And yet people care about birds for some reason.
Thanks, Cameron. My name's Arthur Chapman.
The question is probably to you, Cameron.
I'm wondering what the consequences are of
upscaling to some extent. And I think of the example
you used of, I think it was Eucalyptus studii.
Yep.
If you're then saying you go to the genus and you restrict
all Eucalyptus
distributions in Australia, where there's
900 something species or something like that, does that mean you
restrict all that information and therefore you lose a whole lot
of valuable information for other purposes if you do that for
general?
Thanks, Arthur. Good question. Yeah, I probably wasn't terribly clear.
So
we don't restrict access to all eucalypts.
What we do is restrict access to records that are only attached at
genus level.
So,
it's still precautionary. It still means we're probably generalizing a lot of
unnecessary records.
But
we're not generalizing
all the species in the genus, just the records that are only attaching at genus
level. And that's really been our
general approach, is to try to shrink wrap things as much as possible.
Because I suppose the cautionary tale
is
there was an example in Australia where,
as most people know, iNaturalist records, you've got
geo-obfuscation of records, which is basically based on
their
threat status. In Australia, it's a bit more complicated than that.
But you can also do
generalized records based
for privacy reasons. Now, in Australia, the
geo-obfuscated data is shared with government, the privacy
data, for obvious reasons, is not.
Now, in Australia, there was an instance where somebody had-- And the privacy
restricted records are not well understood in Australia by
iNaturalist users. This particular user had some very
important
records of a restricted access and
highly endangered species in Australia.
They'd marked them as privacy
restricted, and consequently, were not shared in government, and then that
particular area was annihilated because government was
completely unaware that the things occurred there because the data was not
able to be shared. And so I think there's always a tension with
RaaS-D that it's important to shrink wrap it as much as
possible to make the data available for research and
conservation purposes.
Thank you so much. I'm Ruben Pera from GBIF Spain.
My question is related to what happens when the
actual species name, it's the one that reveals the sensitive
information.
I was thinking of the case that Tanya has exposed about the spider, and then I
checked the spider name, and it already says that it lives in a cave, the Latin
name.
Anyone want to take a punt? I'm happy to.
You know why they call it Eucalyptus studii, right?
Because it grows in Studley Park, which you can look up on Google Maps.
Which is the
classic example of a problem.
Yeah, I don't know if there's a good answer to that other than not naming things
after where they are located.
So we've allowed for it in
the new
extension.
I think
our proposal would be what you would be able to do is
remove the taxon name from the record.
So you're still sharing the record, but
you're generalizing the taxon name field.
So you're making clear that there is a record available,
so the data is discoverable, but the taxonomy is withheld
for reasons such as studii.
Yeah. So
in Australia it's a common issue with orchids because we've got
gazillions of them,
and they're really problematic taxonomically and
so localized that they're very easy to
find, and they're frequently named after locations.
Oh.
Any...
No?
I've got questions everywhere.
Hey. Dmitri Dmitriev, University of Illinois.
I'm amazed that when you hide locality, do you also
hide collector? Do you also hide date?
Do you also hide identifier?
Because, same date, same collector,
identifier is sequential, so if you have the same person going to the
same place, probably it just doesn't go for the
single species, it goes to the variety of things,
and multiple things collected at the same time,
same place. Even if you hide for one, it's not necessarily
hidden for the next one.
I think it comes back to what
Dmitri says. How much effort do you want to
have to put it all obscured? Maybe we can
remove everything. It's easy.
We don't have any portals left. But it doesn't cost us any money.
So we try to... And for our situation, it's a little bit on a
dataset based, and our question why we had this
organized like it was, was not coming from the sensitive
species. It was about the records and the locations, how to hide this.
But we know we can adapt. So it depends a little bit on how much
effort you want to... You can keep on trying.
Maybe it's a new research
direction, how to
mystify or what they say, obscure data until we just
cannot really find the locality again.
And like I said before, people who really want to know where something is
with bad intentions, they will find it.
So I think at a certain moment you need a trade-off. "Okay, we stop here.
This is good enough. We have done our best." And then maybe other things
come up, and maybe we should adapt or whatever.
But it depends a little both on every situation and how much effort you can and
will put into that.
Yeah. I'm not sure if I understood the question, but the restrictions
must be
identified
at the level when you publish the first dataset,
maybe in the IPT or whatever. You need to have all the restrictions and all
the things already expressed there, and then all these
treatments and all this information must be...
You need to
be able to
follow.
So where the
dataset is going, all the restrictions has to be
carry with all-
Go with
... Yeah, go with all the dataset. So you publish your dataset once, and then
you replicate.
I just, thinking of something about in my former life when I did a lot of
data publishing where I had to obscure data.
It took me 90% more time to make the data which was in the database on an exact
location to make it obscure. Because then we had this species list coming
from Observa from Waarnemingen.be.
Then we had species in military area, so the grid was different.
So that took a lot of efforts to obscure the data.
The
mapping was not difficult. Then we started with the Atlas, and I did
to make the high-resolution dataset and de-obscure the data, which took me
also
some extra effort. So it's a little bit a trade-off, I think, on how much you can
and will invest in
this.
Just another annotation on that. I think that the ongoing challenge
is
really understanding the use case of what you're trying to
generalize, as I said in my talk. One that I became aware of
a couple of weeks ago. So we've got a lot of bird species in Australia that are
generalized because of their localized breeding habitats.
Now, we
got that down pat. We generalize everything.
But Tanya and I were in a workshop a couple of months ago, and someone
asked us a question about egg collections.
You have this thing where although
the records were all being generalized because the egg
collections were being photographed by museums,
we'd already gone through a process, as Shelley knows, with
images for restricted access species, for herbarium
specimens. It had never occurred to us to look at egg collections, and a lot of
these things, like
owls or parrots, who are return breeders to a
point, if you've got an egg defining where a nest is, it becomes
straightforward to actually find something online. Anyway, sorry.
Hello, I'm Niels Graas from Naturalis.
So I was wondering, especially to avoid poaching, and you mentioned this
wildlife trade database. So as an ecologist, I have never accessed a
database like that, but I think that's seemingly quite relevant information.
So where do we get access to that kind of data?
I would say this is something that is quite
broken and scattered around the world.
There isn't one database for it. What country are you
from?
Netherlands.
Europe at large.
Yeah. So I'm not entirely sure of a
Europe database. A lot of the stuff that is coming out is
in the scientific literature. People are publishing these big data sets of
species and the volume of trade that they're
observing, and a lot of these are over years.
So there's quite good research coming out, and I think it's within the literature
that we need to be keeping an eye out for these.
The US has really good
trade databases. Their LEMIS trade database is really good.
Yeah, within Australia, it's mainly through the scientific literature, but we've
got a lot across all different taxa.
And yeah, so there isn't one go-to place for it.
You kind of have to bring together these things in a sense.
Yeah. Harvesting a lot of data from different places.
I might ask a question of Tanya.
Will the extension include an element of term to check
if a signed agreement restricts data publication?
And do you think that might be easy to track on GBIF?
I guess we do have a treatment reason, which is legal
agreement.
And the treatment description, you can put into more information about
what that agreement is and between who.
You can put as much information as you can on that. So I guess, yes, it does.
I think we had a couple more questions.
Thank you. Franziska Schuster from Museum für Naturkunde in Berlin.
We heard a lot about recent occurrence data, and
because we are publishing historical occurrence data, and I just wonder
if there's any recommendation from any of you how far back in the
past we should apply the RASD rules.
I'll give a viewpoint from the ALA.
So
now that we've kind of got our taxonomic backbone a lot better than it used to be.
So roughly
30% of the species in the ALA, the most recent record is
50 years old.
Which is interesting because in Australia, the official definition for a thing
to be extinct is not have an observation of it in the past 50 years, which
is kind of interesting. So my view would be,
there is no
date. If there's a record,
it's RASD. I just think there's no
reasonable way of
setting,
if you like, a copyright date before which you should release the data.
But I don't know if other speakers have a thought.
Well, some bird nestings,
they change location, so a few years later, it doesn't
matter.
Yeah.
And we have restrictions on bird nestings, but not in wintertime, the same
species, they're open because they're not nesting anymore.
So it depends on organism, if they're
permanent or
moving around a lot.
Yep.
Question out-
There was
one.
Hi, Laura Russell from GBIF.
Really practical question, and I'm thinking back more to my
life when I worked at VertNet and was really helping people publish data.
For those of you that are obs...
I can't even say that word.
Obs...
I can't say it. You know what I mean.
It's all right. My wife plays-
Generalizing. Yes, generalizing the data
... my wife plays obfuscation bingo with me every time I say it in a telecom.
I've had six years' practice.
Yeah.
Sorry.
Can't do it.
So if you're generalizing the data, are you
completing the Darwin Core field for information withheld
to allow people that are wanting the data for
good to know that that data is available if they were to
contact the data holder?
Atlas certainly does. Yep.
Yes.
We mostly put it in the metadata, also in the abstract where you should with an
email, et cetera, and we try to have some information in
those fields, too.
I'd note that what worries me about using the field, what
worries me about the new extension is,
I do a lot of
training sessions with some of my colleagues for
industry and government users, and it is terrifying the number of
users of both the Atlas of Living Australia and GBIF who have no
idea that there is generalized data in the system.
People just
have difficulty interpreting Darwin Core,
and we need to come up with better systems of representing generalized
data.
Sorry.
Hi. I'm Sylvia Orli from the Smithsonian.
And I have a question for you. We deal with global collections,
all disciplines and
dating anywhere from 1840 to present.
And we have a fairly small and getting smaller
staff.
How would you suggest that we mark, we
have 11 million specimen records, how do we mark these
with such limited s- ... staff and with such a global collection,
such depth and breadth.
When I think about it, the last time we went through the IUCN Red List
was, I think it was 1994 for botanical
collections. So it's been a very long time.
So, the task of trying to figure out
what to restrict is daunting at the least.
So what would be your suggestions for an institution
like ours?
Well, yeah.
So part of that is going to be something that I
think the task group is hoping to address, is having a
standard in which we can actually share information
between organizations, even at a transnational level,
about what we consider
in our localities should be restricted species, so that people are publishing
data about us,
could also restrict it. But that idea actually
terrifies me as well.
The idea that then every single
organization around the world then wants us to apply their
own particular restrictions to all the data that we might, because we're a natural
history museum, so we have data all across the world,
how that works in practice, if it was possible.
Yeah.
Tough one.
Maybe I'm seeing this a little bit wrong.
Maybe, probably, but this thing
mostly goes to what we get in most recently.
So his collections and very old, not that old, but
a lot of the data is already herbaria specimens.
I don't think that they should
have a restriction on,
in certain cases, yes, but most of them.
And you can go and visit if you want, go and get-
Because plant populations are pretty stable over relatively long periods of time.
Oh, sorry. Plant populations are quite stable over
relatively long periods of time.
Yeah.
Many of them.
Yeah, but I never had the idea to go back and have this
implemented for everything again to do, okay, we need to check every data set
again for restriction. If you, as the publisher, made the
decision on how to do it, and these are handles and guidelines on how you can
document
the restrictions you put on your data if you want to.
I think that's the most important thing of
what the change is.
I mean, it-
That's my idea.
Yeah. Certainly in Australia,
and we do have... Oh, Shelley, did you want to comment on this as a collections
person from Australia?
Sorry.
It's more of a follow-on for Sylvia in, and I
always raise this as sort of the elephant in the room, of
how can we change culture so that we don't actually have
to redact data? Because all we're doing is
creating downstream issues for all of our conservation
people, all of our land managers, by redacting and
obfuscating data.
I have in my collection so many
sensitive taxa
that, to go collection item by collection item and make a
decision as to whether we
keep showing data, delivering data or not, and putting
terms associated with that. I have researchers coming to me saying,
"You can't share any of this data, but you can put it in your collection." And I
just go, "Well, that's a bit of a problem for our
management."
So,
do you have any ideas about culture shifts?
What can we actually do to stop making these things
sexy to people?
By hiding all this information, and we're saying, they're really important, so
people want to go and find them. Is there an educational tool
that we can use? Can we start
teaching kids just, "Look, don't touch, don't
take." That sort of thing. I'm just wondering if anyone has any
ideas.
Shelley, before I
provide an answer to that, I'm just going to respond to the question over here and
say, I think
the
challenge is
raised by a couple of panel members.
I don't think it's feasible for individual collections to go through and
annotate every single record. The
Smithsonian being the archetypal example, it's just not feasible.
It's just not doable resource-wise.
It's really about how the data's exposed publicly.
In Australia,
collections tend to rely on the ALA to generalize their
data for them.
And so it's really that
centralized exposure role
that makes that relatively straightforward.
GBIF obviously doesn't at the moment, but it's been playing with
how to do sensitive species, and has been actively
involved in the development of the
Darwin Core extension. So I don't think there is an
easy solution, but I think the
solution cannot be the annotation of individual records.
It has to be,
and this does then relate to what Shelley was talking about, it has to be
thinking more about how we deal with this stuff perfectly.
To flick onto
Shelley's question. I don't know, Shelley.
The thing that really worries me about RASD is that 80%
of species are being restricted, not because they're under any pressure.
It's because a
expert somewhere is precious about their
taxa. Australia has 2,000 orchid
species identified as sensitive.
I doubt whether a single one has ever been poached.
Whereas the
taxa that Charlotte's worried about are actively being poached, and
no one's doing anything except on the
ones that she herself has actually raised.
And I think
we need to become better at
doing formal processes, identifying why things should be restricted,
and we need to try institutionally to move away from
things that sort of say,
"Our precautionary approach
is that we redact everything and then decide what we make public." Which I've
heard institutions in Australia actively propose as a
solution.
We should probably wrap up.
Look, if you could just all join me in thanking the
presenters today. Sorry for the slightly shaky
start because of my fault. Thank you very much.
Oh, yeah.
You just never know.
It'd be better if everyone was tall, because then the light wouldn't shine on our
faces.
It's too big now.
Yeah, it's
quite big.
Thanks.
Thank you to the
audience.
... stations this afternoon from 4:00 to 5:00, when we have an open
discussion on
this topic.
And we have encouraged you to come to the Unconference
and contribute there and continue to find out who's also interested
in this topic.
So,
with that, I think we're going to get started.
We say thank you to all our sponsors for making all of this possible,
and
please keep everything respectful.
And if you have a question or an issue, come find one of the organizers, let us
know.
And with that,
I'd like to get started.
So, let's see here.
Oh, there you go.
Hi, everybody. Do you-
Oh, is it my-- Yeah.
Me.
Yep. Please.
I get to go first.
Oh, yeah. Of course.
Hi, everybody. My name is Debbie Paul.
I'm very happy to have this mic, which means I'm not glued to that thing.
I am very happy to be here talking about open digital curation.
And for those of you who don't know me, I do have a background
in both education and biology. And so
communicating the kind of things that we need to do to empower people in our
community is very near and dear to my heart, and so this is something I
have strong feelings about.
I have a background coming from, some of you might know the iDigBio project, where
I worked on workforce and capacity development.
And on the project I'm at now, I'll tell you a little bit about that.
Putting this talk together
was very fitting in sense of the kind of work that we do,
and figuring out on our project how we can empower our
community.
We have three software products we focus on.
It's not the only things that we do. How many of you know Global Names?
So if you need to clean, parse, verify names, these are cool tools.
We work on the Catalog of Life together. It's a distributed team.
About 25% of the names you find in the Catalog of Life
that end up in the GBIF backbone
come from work done in TaxonWorks workbenches.
So these are the three pillar projects that we
work together on. And we are a distributed team across Argentina,
the US at the University of Illinois, and New York.
So as fast as I could put this talk together, the ground is shifted
and around this topic. I'm going to focus on openness,
and there's an asterisk there for a reason.
Surprisingly, I won't talk too much about interoperability because interestingly,
most of the pieces to do what we want are there now.
And provenance, which we also have, but now we find we have
questions. What else do we need to be tracking in the light of things like AI?
All of the above are dependent on identifiers, all of them,
and the standards that the work of the Biodiversity Information Standards TADWIG
Group has been actively developing now for years, and you start
to see pieces coming together.
So
Bionomia. Some of us were just in the talk that David gave.
And
I put up here again, I think Sabino
walked into the system and created this profile so we could
see Henry's work. So this makes the point that it's a living,
breathing system, and it also helps us enable those are no longer
with us. And it helps not only that individual's expertise to live on,
they know where to find things on the planet, they know how to identify them,
but it also helps institutions understand their
remit in a longer fashion. Right? Because even though this person
is no longer working at Miza, this person will continue to contribute to
the intellectual expertise that Miza has supported bringing into the world.
So open digital curation
does a lot of things, and this is a way to make it very
inclusive. And round-tripping, this notion of getting
this data out the door. For example, you can create a researcher
profile. Jennifer Jeron here
is an early career researcher. Her data set now via Zenodo that's
regularly updated from Bionomia through an API has already
been downloaded over 1,000 times.
So
what about, for example, iNaturalist?
So you're an iNaturalist and a name comes up for Orthoptera.
You're looking at a grasshopper and you say, "Oh, there's a missing name," or
"There's a name misspelled." What to do?
GBIF gets lots of these emails, but GBIF can't fix them
in that space. Right? So here the nice thing is this is a
human-mediated machine round-tripping combination.
Typophyllum is a person.
He is also active in iNaturalist, and he sees somebody
post an Orthoptera issue for a name.
He then goes directly into the Orthoptera species file, the GitHub
repo, posts a ticket, and can get into the database to fix it.
So it shortens the time between something's wrong on the internet and giving you
agency to actually get it where it needs to go to get responsiveness.
Which, by the way, programmers find very motivating.
When they look at your GitHub repo, they can see what kind of community you are.
They can see if they want to get involved with you.
They can see how responsive you are.
So open digital curation supports round-tripping.
I
I propose here it is extremely useful, and it empowers many
more of us to be part of the network of
curating data and helping raise the profile of
the work that we do.
So who and what gets left out if we don't? A lot.
Intellectual expertise
over time, including the fact that when people can no longer speak for
themselves.
So another example you're going to hear more about in this session comes from
Disco. Many years ago, many of us were in the room talking about
annotations. How are we going to do them? Ooh, it's really hard.
And we didn't have necessarily the things in place to do it.
And now we're going to look at the system that's distributed across at the
institutional level, community able to engage in this world,
and a layered system to deal with what those issues are that could just be
automatically fixed versus those that have to be vetted.
So in TaxonWorks, I want to qualify
open. Open in the sense of in a network that you typically
wouldn't have been able to touch each other's data.
So if you create a controlled vocabulary, you went
to work to do that in a way to empower your data being
used and discovered,
I guess, in a more strategic way, I would say, more understandable way.
So in our system, not only can you create that term and the
definition for that term, but if it makes sense to do so, we empower you to
link it to existing ontologies. So that I will use the example
again, some of you will smile, you know it already, petiole. That's the word.
How many of you heard plant in your head when I said petiole? Raise your hand.
Aha. In the chat, you can put up plant if you want.
How many of you heard insect when I said petiole?
Ah.
That tells me who's in the room. All right, so you need an ontological
URI for that term if you want to search a giant pile of data
and images in case you are
interested in insects or plants.
So again,
when we do this in TaxonWorks, you can search across the
controlled vocabularies
that other people have created for things like
keywords or the added terms in the database, and you can
see what terms they are using, and you can clone
those into your project. So it's open in the sense that
in the past you would not have been able to look at somebody else's
data in those fields.
So,
and very quickly, what this does in my mind, the Paloeo Data Working Group,
anybody here from there? Yep, there we go.
So one of the things that does is help communities
understand what other people are doing.
And why is that important? You get emails.
"Deb, can you explain to me what other botanists, what do they use in
this field?" And I'm like, "We'll go to GBIF and look at millions of records?"
Right? This is a way to help the community mature these processes.
So I was very excited to see agent as a
concept in the Darwin Core data package. It's very cool.
And note that an agent here can also be an
LLM.
Very interesting.
So
also an agent then, much like in Bionomia, right, the agent needs
an identifier, and we need to know what that agent was
doing, what role were they playing.
And this is really nice because I don't know if you guys have played with it yet,
but John built this really cool tool where you can actually visualize the
terms you've picked, which is what I'm trying to show you here.
And in TaxonWorks, a person, which is different than a user,
a person in TaxonWorks can have or has a role
or roles, depending on whether they are responsible for naming a
taxon, or they're responsible for identifying something, or they
are the author of a source or paper, for example.
So our model aligns very nicely with this.
And this allows us, again, with credit and attribution in a way, to spin
up this notion of what activities has this person contributed
and in what way.
So thinking about provenance, it's important to
remember this process and role. So
one example would be, this is from the different journals of Pensoft
and the kind of things that they talk about.
So it's not just that you say, "I used AI." "Who are you?"
"I'm an author." "What did you do with it?" They are purporting here that that goes
in the materials and methods section.
And then what if you're the editor or the reviewer?
It is not etiquette to take someone's unpublished
manuscript and put it through AI and get some
information back. This is a no. So again, us learning about when
it's appropriate to use and what it's for,
and making sure our community's behaving responsibly
with respect to this.
So what about the user interface? And I suspect many of us are
still working on this.
And that would be, in this example, something that
we're further developing. This
is an early instance of global names.
Imagine you have a 900-page PDF, I'm not kidding,
of some
monograph that someone has published.
And in it are many names, new species, maybe species that
have been
synonymized, et cetera. And you would like to know, are all the names
in this paper, which ones are already in my database, which ones are
not?
How long is it going to take you to do it?
So this is a cool tool because you can apply global names to this paper and it'll
come back, and it'll look through the paper, find all the names, and then look in
your database and say, "Yes, it's there.
No, it's not."
And now you can imagine us expanding on this, adding sort of LLM type things
that you could do and ask on top of this.
But we've got to figure out a way for humans to be able to look at the output and
say, "Yes, that's right, add that to my database. No, that's not.
And this is where it came from, what page, in what journal,
et cetera."
So, a few thoughts on openness.
The pod bay doors, I would argue, are largely open.
How open they're going to stay is a question.
I
want to know, I'm asking you,
how does change in openness impact interoperability?
I know I don't know the answer there.
That discussion we just had with Matt Blissett about API
keys or not, that kind of thing.
I have seen some moves of people moving from CC0 back to CC
BY on very large projects.
And I'm wondering about logging in, because people are
now implementing that, and it's both a benefit and not for
some. But it's a real benefit for projects, knowing who's actually
touching their data and getting information about how they're using it.
So at TaxonWorks, the pod bay doors are open largely.
Most of our projects have their API open,
and an example would be the data that I exposed to you in the beginning, going
to Catalog of Life. And through that, again, I was
explaining that this shortens the distance to the time between
something is amiss or missing or needs
adding, and the way to actually manage to get that done.
And this helps GBIF too, then, in return.
So inside TaxonWorks, as in some other
collection management software, you can get your data directly to GBIF.
Inside our software, the nice part is we try to manage having more
than one person know how to do this in your project.
And so you can control how often the data is
grabbed by GBIF, and how often you create a new dataset,
as well as things like what extensions do you want to use,
and you can customize all of that and keep up with your metadata.
I talk fast. All right. So
do we
have missing data standards now for sharing all these
open digital curation processes?
What if you're using a cloud or local network? Do we know that?
Do we need to know if you're using ChatGPT constrained by an institution
or just the regular ChatGPT? Do we need
prompts?
And are there other things that we aren't tracking that we're discovering we need
to? What do we need to keep? What could be tossed?
Last thought, what if AI didn't hallucinate?
What would that change about the way we are thinking about all of this?
So this was a blog post from @typesafe.ai.
It's about five days old now.
But they are purporting this model that they put out that can't
hallucinate. And I was promptly told by a couple of developers, "Oh, let me poke
at it. I can make it happen." We'll see.
And then the last thought I think is interesting to ponder as well,
they have taken a system that can go through more
tokens faster, so they've shortened the time that the analysis
takes. And then
because of that, it's expanded the sort of magnitude of the use
cases they can think of to apply.
So this is something to think about as well when it talks about energy use and
sustainability, but also dreaming big.
So that's very quick. I want to say, I think we are in the age of open
digital curation. People are recognizing the value, and it is emerging
in the midst of AI,
LLMs, and machine learning evolution.
It offers us transparency and agency, it reduces latency,
and it builds trust.
Thank you.
And I don't believe there's any time for questions. Am I right?
Questions at the end of the session.
Questions at the end of the session. Thank you very much.
And me tracking the mouse across the-- There we go. I found you.
All right.
I'm looking forward to your questions very much. Here we go.
Our next speaker.
Nathan?
Yeah. Ah, shoot.
Ah.
I'm ready now. I was a bit eager earlier.
You are? No. Eager's good.
Yeah. It's a very exciting topic.
There we go.
Thank you, Deb. So
good morning. My name is Nathan Vandekreeft.
I represent the Missouri Botanical Garden, and my talk will be more
about Darwin Data Core package, specifically how we're
excited about this as sort of a foundational element for how we think
about our data at Missouri, as well as the potential
to use this as a method for communication with other
institutions. So what we've done is, as we started to
think about how we might use this internally, we realized that Darwin Core Data
Package is really an expansive standard that applies
broadly across lots of communities, and we needed a version of it that was a bit
more tailored to our needs in the botanical data
space. So what I'll show you today is our first step towards that.
If you take one thing away from this talk, I would encourage you to take away that
this is a draft, and I would love it if you would reach
out, and let's continue to discuss how to improve this and
make it something that's more firm as perhaps a standard for the botanical
community.
All right. So why should you be excited about Darwin Core Data Package?
And I'm not on their payroll or anything, I actually just really do
like this. So,
the first potential, obviously, is data exchange, which is the same value that you
might get from Darwin Core Archive.
There is kind of a cool extra thing you can do when your
basis is a semantic graph, and I wanted to explain that here.
So I'll show you the larger version later, but this is kind of a subset of the
larger graph that I'll get into for botanical data.
And this is our area where we're talking about specimen collection.
So if you'll notice, every one of these boxes has two
labels on it. There's a lower label that's bolded, and that's the official Darwin
Core Data Package class name. So you'll see at the bottom here you've got specimen
material.
There's a pointer, but I don't know how to use it. So the bottom box.
And then specimen there is just a sort of a convenience label that I've applied to
show how that material class relates to the structure, in
this particular part of the graph.
So you'll see that coming out more just to sort of explain how things are laying
out. Right?
Now, the point I'm trying to make is that we have specimens, and at the top
level, you'll see collection events, which is an event, and that's where the
specimens are typically collected.
Now, Tropicos, which is our collection management system at Missouri Botanical
Garden,
we have a third layer that sits in the middle that not all specimen collection
systems have. And we call that very confusingly, collection.
And it refers to sort of a collection of specimens.
So if you think about a number of specimens being collected from an individual
plant or from a related population in the field.
So you think about this as a collection of duplicates, effectively, of
specimens.
Now, not all collection management systems have this, and what's cool is if you're
looking at this as a graph and you're running a graph query language on this,
you can ask a question regardless of whether or not the two
implementations are exactly the same.
So I could say, "How many specimens were collected during this collection
event?"
And I'll get the right answer regardless of whether or not I have
that middle layer. So this is kind of something that's really interesting about the
graph version of this.
The other thing that really excites me specifically for Missouri is we
have a number of very sizable
collections. Now I'm using that word in the broad sense.
Living collections and
herbarium specimens and all these things.
And they were all developed independently.
And we're at a point where we need to think about how to integrate them together.
And rather than go through and redesign all of our
data foundations, what we can do is we can use this as
sort of an integration layer, which is going to allow us to show how all the
concepts connect and map the constituent databases up
through that structure and show how they relate, and then you can build something
on top of it that looks more like a data warehouse with more of a relational feel
to it. So this is the approach that we're taking, and I think, again, Darwin Core
Data Package can really provide that middle
layer that we need in order to stitch this together, as well as connecting with
sort of external concepts that are outside of things that we manage directly.
I was entirely too ambitious with the content that I have, so I'm going to skip a
few points. This is one of them. It's super cool.
You can use, when you have a knowledge graph, which you can build out with a
model like this,
you can use this as a way to get much higher quality when you're
doing LLM queries on large structured databases.
If you're interested, let's talk about that after.
I don't have time, unfortunately.
This is the full eye chart for our integrated collection map.
You can see this. Hopefully, the quality is good in the slides that you'll have
access to after the talk, and I'm going to go through it sort of section by
section.
So we'll start on the left, which is sort of our living collection area.
And so to sort of orient you, if you look all the way to the right,
in the middle, you'll see plant observation occurrence.
And again, this is my way of saying this is the occurrence table, the occurrence
records, and this case, the plant observations. So you can see how I'm labeling it.
If you go up from there, you'll see the organism, which is the plant that this
observation's referring to.
If you go down from there, you'll see a row full of material
classes, and these represent material that I might take from the living plant,
whether that's a propagule or a seed or tissue culture or other things like that.
And if you move to the left and up, you'll see
information on traits and on media, so
photographs that I might take of the plant.
Now, there's a lot more to say about media.
There's kind of a duplicate section here, media for specimens.
So I'll talk more about that when we get to that section.
The other thing I wanted to point out is that the semantics in this graph
express most of what you need to sort of capture what you need to store from a
data modeling perspective. There are a few things that need to be kept
consistent that are external to the model, and I wanted to call out a couple of
them as we go through. One of them is the idea of an accession number.
So it's very important to have
an accession number defined within the record.
So like the seed, for instance, has to have an accession number.
That's sort of a
genetic
identifier, if you will, for that seed, but it needs to be the
same as the identifier on the organism.
So that's really important for the people that work with that data, but that needs
to be enforced externally to the structure, if that makes sense.
All right.
So now let's move to the next section.
If I go over, this is sort of the part that deals with our
herbarium.
And again, to orient you, if you look on the left, now you've got the occurrence,
and if you move your eye all the way to the right and slightly down, you'll see a
box that I've highlighted over here called specimen material.
That's sort of the focal point for this part of the
graph.
If you go up, you'll see the specimen collection part that we looked at a minute
ago.
Next to the specimen, you'll see other kinds of material, figures and descriptions
that could be part of how you make an identification.
And if you look at identification here, this is based on
materials, so physical evidence that you have, as well as media.
And it's an important distinction to make that those are the things that you have.
So you can say within the graph that this specimen,
this DNA sequence, and this photograph were the things that I used to make an
identification. You can't go deeper than that, and I'll come back to that point in
a minute.
But that's how it's laid out. The other thing to make is, there's another one of
these sort of external
constraints or things that we need to enforce here,
which is on accepted identifications.
So within that box,
you can only have one accepted identification that's
true, and there's a field that you can set to true.
So that needs to be enforced across all the identifications you might make
on that particular occurrence.
Okay. Now, if you look at specimen and you start to go
down, that will get to the last section of the large graph here that I'm
calling specimen traits.
And so now you can see specimen at the very top.
And we're going to move down. And we have a large emphasis
on traits because even though we don't have a lot of data yet on
traits, this is an area I think is very important as we move forward, especially as
we think about automated workflows that are going to analyze these
digital artifacts that we're creating on our specimens.
So that's why we've paid a lot of attention to building out this part
specifically.
And so to walk through this real quickly, in the middle, you'll see a box that
says, "Trait," which is a material assertion. It's an assertion about the specimen.
These are always made by human agents because they are made on a
physical specimen. And as you move down, you get more into the digital
representation. So there's a row of classes in the middle that are
hyperspectral related. I won't talk about that, but if you're interested in
hyperspectral imagery, as it pertains to
specimen data, please go see the talk by my colleague Matt Austin at 3:00 PM
in South C.
When you go down to the lower section here, you'll see
the portion pertaining to photographs.
So there's two classes in the Darwin Core Data Package spec that deal with
photographic media,
or media in general. One is the properties of the
digital file itself, so resolution, things like that.
The other is content of the media file.
And then from there, you can do a bunch of different things.
You can take a region of interest, you can transform the image or do a mask or all
kinds of whatever transformations that you want to do.
And then you can assert traits onto that.
And, I also have a box for features, which is meant in the machine
learning context. So as we think about automating workflows, the distinction
I'm trying to make here is traits are
independently interesting for the community. Features may or may not be.
They may just be interesting for modeling workflows that you have.
And then you can see we have both human and AI agents called out there.
One of the big areas that
I won't have time to get into, but it's, I think very valuable for alignment within
the community, is actually the level below what we do here.
And there's a lot of unique identifiers and
controlled vocabularies that need to be defined on the fields in these classes.
So even though I don't have time to go through all of that, this is an area where I
think picking the right ontologies and picking the right identifiers for the
community has a tremendous amount of value for what we do next.
And so that's, again, an area where I'd really invite
conversation after.
And I'll leave you with this point, which is
calling back to what I had mentioned earlier about identifications being mapped
through from materials. So
at first when we encountered that, we thought, "Oh, maybe this is a limitation in
the Darwin Core Data Package standard that's going to hold us back
from capturing information that we might want to capture about which
traits are actually informing
decisions." But as we thought about this more, it's
a very difficult problem, and it's not something that's going to be easily
capturable in a simplified format anyway.
Because if you think, there's two sorts of workflows you can have.
If you think as a data scientist, you are looking at these automated
workflows and you have a black box, but sometimes in that black box, you have
explainable models where you can easily back out maybe
weights on specific traits that made your decision, and sometimes you
don't. You may have a very complex structure there where it's hard to understand.
That's highly nonlinear in the decisions that you make.
And that's pretty analogous to a taxonomist, in the black box, right?
Where sometimes you have information there, and they'll
do their best to write out why they made a decision in their notes.
Sometimes they don't.
And so I think in both cases, it's an independently interesting problem
around how we simplify and capture which traits were important to
making a decision. But I do think that's external, the more I've thought about it,
to what we need to capture in this format, and that needs to be something that's
going to kept separately from the data package itself.
So,
that's all I have time for, I think today.
I wanted to end with a thank you to my collaborators at
Missouri, as well as special thanks to
two really critical thought partners here, John and also Cam Webb.
And I'll leave on the point again, that I've said a few times, that if this is
interesting to you,
I would love to continue the conversation and figure out how we can
develop this better as a community. So, thank you very much.
Yeah. Oh, you're already micd. Yay.
Cool.
Come on up
Are you ready?
You want that? Next up,
Anna Koivunen.
Hello, everybody.
You can hear me, yes?
It's nice to be here today to tell you a little bit our work, what we're
doing in the
Finnish Museum of Natural History.
I'm the head of digitization in our museum, and
been about seven years, and we have
proceeded with digitization about 10 years, this mass
digitization. And we have had
many obstacles to
tackle. And now we are in this phase that we
are trying to make these
images-- Oh.
It doesn't show very nicely, the slide.
But anyway,
how to
extract information from the label images
and make it structured data. And this is the
showcase I will tell you a little
bit about. So this is a practical approach, how we have
solved this
or are trying to solve in our museum.
Little bit about the background.
So our museum, we like to call it Luomus because we like these
short names in Finnish. All our words are quite short.
So I will be
saying Luomus from now on. It's a part of
University of Helsinki,
and we have about 14 million specimens in
our collections,
and it's a nationally significant collection.
Actually, it's the largest collection in Finland.
I just wanted to be a little bit humble in this slide, but
couldn't
pull it off.
And, in the
row below, we can see how the collections are divided
into these sub-collections. So
invertebrates, which means mostly insects, are the main
collection, about 10 million. So most of our collections
are insects.
And then vascular plants and fungi and lichens are the next
big collections.
And till now, it has been a little bit pain in
the a*s that the insects are the most common collection,
because the digitizing of the pinned insect is really
difficult.
But
the positive side is that their labels are
very simple compared to vascular plants and lichens
and mosses and stuff like that. So when we get the images from
the pinned insects,
the transcription with AI is much easier than for the
fungi and vascular plants. So there is a
side to this
problem.
And this is the big problem that I'm facing, and
everybody else in this digitization world, I think,
that we have quite a big backlog of the
digitization status in our museum.
We are not the biggest in the industry, but quite
big anyway. We have this 14 million, and we have done
this
mass digitization already 10 years or something like that, and we
have digitized four million till now.
So we have
still 10 million to go, and it's quite a lot.
And we have a brand new
digitization strategy drawn, and we have made
our goal that we have been digitized all our collections till year
2045. So in 20 years, we want to
tackle the backlog.
And we have to increase our current digitizing pace
about 30%.
But I think this is a little bit positive because
size of our staff has gone down because of the funding has
decreased.
But this is our goal, and
for this,
we need help.
And we are calling AI to the rescue, as
it is the common
thing to do nowadays,
and a scalable process also, it has to be.
And here is a little words about what we mean about the scalability.
It's not just
volume, it's also the variety within in the
collections.
So we have a lot of specimens, but they are also from
different taxonomic groups. And it means that these labels
are quite different, varying from the collection to collection.
As I mentioned, insect labels are quite
simple and easy to transcribe, but
others are not.
And then there are different label types.
There are handwritten, typewritten, and then multilingual.
In Finland, we have a lot of
Finnish and Swedish in the labels, and some
Russian also.
And then there are many corrections and stuff like that, annotations
written in on the labels. And also we have
different collection traditions.
So
people, in different collections think that what is
complete and
digitized, and it's a
cultural thing
We usually like to
follow the principle KISS,
keep it simple. We are extracting the stupid part of it because
it's a little demeaning.
But this is our simple pipeline, how we are now processing
our images.
We load the
images, we have used Gemini 2.5 till
now,
to the
AI, and it transcribes the verbatim,
and then it comes back. It takes some
one hour to four to five hours to process, and then
postponing its post-process, it's just like going through if
there are some duplicates or something like that.
And then it's fed
again to the Gemini,
and then with the prompt and a schema.
So the prompting is
very important and the schema, we have found out that it's
perhaps the most important thing to
add to the prompts and
when the
verbatim
text will be
input to the
Gemini.
After that, when it's structured, it will be saved to
our
collection management system, Kotka.
And also with it, we store the metadata, and I will
talk a little bit more about this in a minute.
Then we have this little more
specialized work flow for the
more,
not so simple, more complicated
labels like these
vascular plants and moss labels. We have been,
added after the first verbatim input,
this intent.
We ask the AI to
think what the collector or who has written
the
label has thought that this information means.
So it makes this intent
and
corrects the output. And we have
found out that it's really good. It
comes back
almost 100% correct if you give it this intent,
if there are messy labels.
And then the rest is the same that in this
simple
pipeline.
This is an example of these messy
labels. These we have found that they are quite difficult
for the AI still.
If we wouldn't have these corrections, this would be really easy for the
AI, as probably everybody knows.
And it can
transcribe if there is just this
typed text and handwritten text. It's very easy.
The handwritten text is very easy for the AI at the moment, but when
there are these corrections, it gets confused and it's
not very good. But with
adding the intent, it makes it easier
for the AI to transcribe these labels.
But it's not 100% accurate.
And this is the output that comes from the
simple
pipeline.
It's really good
reading the text, even though it has been struck
over and there are these markings.
It reads
the text behind it, but
as you see, it doesn't
interpret it correctly, really.
Let's move on.
And this is the structured data.
We have included
fields that are included in the collections,
the most common
fields, and
the same fields are mainly according to
Darwin Core, but our Mikko, who has made this,
used a little bit intuition and
made some of these names,
just made up these
names because the Darwin Core names didn't
really work that well. So he invented
these names that they
gave better results.
And these are
the
data that we are
saving for the collection management system, this
verbatim transcribed text stored in dedicated fields.
So we have one field there that contains all the information,
what the OCR
has
helped produced,
and then the structured data will go to these specific fields.
But it never overrides the human transcribed
fields. So the
human transcribed is
the,
how do you say?
Yeah, preferred.
And then there is a flag that it's AI generated
And for the
AI part, at the moment, we are saving all the
information, these transcription runs, LM model versions,
prompts, and stuff like that
to play it safe.
And we have done this for the
30,000 specimens. This is just a
study case, and 600 we have reviewed.
It's 2% of the sample size, and we think that
maybe in the future it's only 1% because it takes
so much time to do this checking, and we can
perhaps concentrate only for the
most difficult labels to check.
And then I want to say this also before my time comes out,
that I think this has been perhaps the most
difficult part of this whole process, because the AI part is
nowadays quite easy, and the AI is really good at doing these things.
But to get the acceptance from the collection
people to rely on this method has been a
long way, and I have been working on it
these 10 years or seven years to get them
accept that the AI will
be trustworthy, and we don't have to
manually write everything down. And I think
nowadays, because they have seen it by
themselves that it's quite accurate and
trustworthy, they are now quite happy to rely on that
and stop writing everything manually down.
And then there is all these little bit takeaways that
we thought would be the
key things
from our perspective.
And
perhaps our
main point is that this is not an advertisement,
but just do it is our line of thought,
that people should just do things and by
trial and error to modify the process.
And
for the end, I will
thank our DigiTeam
and some other people
for the hard work, what they have been doing.
And if you want to know more, please contact Mikko Heikkinen if you
want to know about this technical thing and get some
sensible answers. And if you just want to
chat about digitization, then contact me.
Thank you.
Thanks very much.
All right.
Next up.
And thank you, Shovan and Spina, my
co-organizers here, keeping us going.
All right.
Wouter Addink. Thank you.
Hello, everybody.
My name is Wouter Addink.
I'm based at Naturalis Biodiversity Center in Leiden, the Netherlands,
which houses one of the largest collections in the world.
And I'm also representing DiSSCo here
as the technical director. And I'm going to tell you a little bit
about the plans for an annotation validation framework.
But before I do that, I would like to know who of you is
a curator of a natural history collection?
I see a few hands.
Most of you are not, but
assume for a minute that you are a curator. Yeah.
And that you are a curator of a typical collection, a
pretty large collection, a couple of million specimens,
and only about 10% of that is digitized.
And that digitized information is often of pretty low
quality. It's not georeferenced yet.
It is not having
identifiers for the collectors, for Binomia.
It contains
errors in the names, spelling errors, and things like that.
And you have a director of your museum, who is
a visionary director, and he is
informed about all the developments of AI, and he thinks, "Well, we can speed
up the digitization and improve the quality of your data
with use of AI." So that director
decides to give the technical team, the
developers of the museum,
to develop a annotation service with the help of
AI
that starts annotating the data, uses the
images from the collection to
transcribe the label information.
And, well, there is a pretty good software team at
the museum, so they succeed with that.
And the
machine annotation service they create
creates hundreds, maybe thousands, or maybe even millions of
annotations.
So pretty successful. So what is the result of that?
Well,
this is probably how the curator looks like now.
Like this.
A lot of stress because-
There are now thousands of annotations,
and what to do with that?
How to validate these annotations?
Do I trust these annotations? Do
I
maybe
accept that the annotation service automatically
puts the
data in
the collection management system?
If the
service does that and overrides the
records in the system, you lose the control over that, right?
So you lose the sovereignty.
But you also lose the provenance. So you lose the history of the changes in
the data. Of course, these things can
be fixed. We have seen that in the previous presentation.
These things can be fixed, but it's hard to do.
So it costs you a lot of effort at the museum to do that, and it also costs a
lot of effort to create this
AI-driven annotation system.
And this is exactly what the annotation validation
framework that we
want to implement in DISCO tries to solve.
With this, we want to enable
the running of machine annotation service, not at the museum, but
in the DISCO infrastructure.
And that means that
everybody can benefit from that
service. So if once you have created that service and you run it in the
infrastructure, you can run it not only on your collection, but you can
run it on all the collections that are in the DISCO infrastructure.
And
anybody can make an annotation in
the DISCO infrastructure, anybody with an ORCID and all the machine
annotation services can make annotations.
So you don't need to worry about that anymore in your
local collection management system.
And what we want to do, we don't want to have a system in
place where we say, "Well,
we accept this annotation. We don't accept that annotation."
That's not what we want to do. We want to have all the annotations
living happily together.
Right?
So we start, we create data layers, layers
of trust, where we want to place these annotations.
Because at the end, the annotations that we trust enough, we would like
to merge back into the digital specimen object,
so to have a single point of truth. So that is
the ultimate goal. That's the top layer here, the curated
consensus layer,
where we have the latest version of the
digital specimen object.
But we start with the institutional base layer.
So this, the data that we get from institutions, we are not going to
touch that. So,
the institution is in full control of that layer, and you can still use that layer.
But on top of that, we have that
community enrichment layer, where all the unvetted
annotations live. So everybody who makes an annotation,
all these annotations end up here, not validated.
And some of these annotations are just small error corrections, things like that.
And we can automatically
approve them, promote them to the curated consensus layer.
So we say, "Okay, we trust that these annotations are correct."
We promote them to the consensus layer.
But some of these annotations are things like
a suggestion for a new identification to change the scientific name,
or a suggestion to change the catalog number.
And these annotations have a high scientific impact, so these really
need a managed review. They need to be reviewed by experts.
And these experts can be humans, human experts, taxonomists,
but can also be machines. So once we have machines
that we can consider to be an expert, that we trust enough, we
can also automate part of that managed review process.
So the goal is to have a balanced
system where we want to automatically promote the
annotations as much as possible and only have to look at the
annotations that need further review.
So this is how the validation flow looks like.
You start
with the submission of a new annotation.
So that can be
an agent with an ORCID,
but that agent can also, that human can also
run a machine annotation service on
records.
And then, the annotation is created.
It gets a persistent
identifier and an ID of the agent, so we keep track of the
full provenance, the creation date, and things like that.
And then,
the step is followed by technical validation of that annotation.
So is the syntax correct? Does it follow the schema?
Does it follow the DISCO content policies?
For instance, does it not contain malicious content?
Does it not
provide an exact location of a
protected species?
Things like that.
This is a completely automated step, and once
it passes that technical validation, it enters the next
step, the automated routing of- ...
the annotation to one of these layers that I presented.
So it can be put in the open community
enrichment layer, the layer where all the unvetted
annotations live. It can be immediately promoted to the
consensus layer, or it can end up in the managed review layer, so
further review is needed.
And it ends with the promotion, the integration
into the digital object,
which creates a new version of the digital specimen.
And we store all the different versions over time,
so you can always go back to a previous version, and
this makes also the system very resilient, because if there
are some errors at some point in this automated
process, then we can always refer back.
This is the flow, how that works.
So
after the passing of the technical validation, we start
with the evaluation. What type of annotation is it?
Is it just a comment that is added, or is it
assessing data, so a quality flag?
So like this field needs to be checked, or that field is probably outdated.
Then we say, "Well, that's low impact." We put that in the community
enrichment layer,
because this is information that we cannot merge into the
digital object. It can also be
a proposal to delete the object,
because
it
may be a duplicate, it may be a digital specimen that already exists.
And this needs managed review by an administrator.
So this ends in the managed review layer.
The interesting part is where the annotation tries to add new data
or to edit existing data, or
to propose deleting of some of the data
within the digital specimen. Then it looks
like the impact. So it looks at the content of the annotation itself,
and it tries to assess the impact. And if it's
high impact, so it tries to correct an error in the type status,
or it
tries to create a new identification, then it is
considered high impact and it ends in the managed review.
If not, then it's maybe low impact.
So we use some algorithms to detect whether it's like an error
correction.
It's low impact, then we automatically promote that to the consensus view.
If not, if it's medium impact, then we say we need to
have a two-agent condition met. So two agents, for
instance, two machine annotation services, need to create the same
annotation, or an agent needs to
validate
the annotation of another agent.
Once that
condition is met, or the annotation is created by
an agent that has a good track record over time, that is a trusted agent,
then it is also promoted to that consensus layer.
These are two examples. So here you see a
low impact
example where you have an error correction.
So you want to correct this location
text,
and improve that and standardize that.
Other examples are measurements that are added.
We can just add them. So,
we have some automated checks for these kinds of annotations,
and we can automatically promote them to the consensus layer.
And this is an example of a high impact
annotation,
where a machine annotation service suggests a new scientific name.
I also mentioned the catalog number alteration, and this
needs a mandatory human peer review
by domain experts. And again, these experts can also be machines.
We are running a consultation on this because this is
just a plan at the moment.
We started that at the end of last month, so we aim to run this
consultation for
a month, until end of this month.
But I will give you a little bit more time if you want to look at this.
So, let's say to extend this public
consultation to the 16th of October, so with two
weeks.
I did not create a QR code for this because
the documents are very easy to find.
You can just go to the disco.eu website, and you
will find them on the homepage.
You can also look at the chat of this session, and you will find the link there
also. There are three documents in this plan,
and you should start with the general concept, because otherwise you will not
understand the other two documents.
We have also a document with the technical specifications, so all the nitty-gritty
details of the plan,
and a document with the conceptual governance model and the policy framework
behind that.
So this is what I had to tell. I invite you all to
look at this, because I think this is a very important development.
This is core to what we want to achieve with Disco.
So,
I ask for a call to action to all review these documents.
Send your comments via a form. I created a form for that.
On the 22nd of October, we have
an online meeting, and everybody is
welcome to join that meeting, where we are going to discuss the results, the
outcome of this consultation.
And after that discussion, we aim to finalize these documents
by the end of this year and then start implementation.
Thank you.
Are we done? Okay.
Thank you, Walter.
Is it on?
Yes,
but I have to find the mouse first. There we go.
Here we are.
Okay.
Next up, Nikki Nicholson.
Voila.
Thanks, Deb.
Welcome.
Yeah. Thank you everyone for the invitation to talk today.
So this is some work that I did with a couple of colleagues at Kew,
Ashley and Stephen.
They're both available online if you want to have a chat to any of us about this.
So we called this project Geonomia, and that's to
recognize the work that Bionomia has done in looking at the data that's been
mobilized through GBIF and disambiguating the people.
And for us, it's important also to disambiguate the geographic names that are
associated with our data.
And the reason we need to do this is because at Kew, we've digitized our
specimens, so we've got 6.3 million specimens now.
That's a bit of an old slide.
Yeah, and we've mobilized them into GBIF, and we have this lovely map.
But if you look-- Well, okay.
Yeah, look at that bit of the page, right?
So that map only being 13% of our data
because
we digitized the specimens by photographing them and then entering the metadata
from the specimen sheet,
and lots of our records, they don't have
any coordinates on them. They've just got descriptions of places because they
predate handheld GPS.
The other thing that we like about sharing the data through GBIF is that we know
how people use it. So we've got all these citations of the data where
did it from GBIF and used it in their place.
We took apart the
metadata about how downloads were generated through GBIF.
So for all of those citations, then I pulled down the
way that those downloads have been delimited and looked at the predicates that
people use to form the queries
to get that data, and two-thirds of them use spatial predicates.
So two-thirds of them throw away most of our data.
So yeah, we think that's a real problem.
That two-thirds figure, that's just done on
Kew data that's shared through GBIF.
But if you're sat in the audience and you want to make the same argument
to your managers or your curators, all that data is available
to do the same kind of analysis for any other dataset that's shared through
GBIF. So you can see how
people are querying it and
what bits of the specimen record you should prioritize for
management.
So we know that we need to
turn those descriptions of places into things that are computable because that's
the way that people want to get at our data.
And we've got some data that will help us get at that.
So
this is our specimen sheet, and I'd argue that it's
nicer than a pinned insect because there's loads of data on it.
But
there are a couple of pieces of data on it that help us disambiguate
from where this specimen was collected, even though we only have a description of
the place.
So yes. We have
a date,
and we have a number that the collector puts on their collecting events as
they
collect them.
And
collectors are great people, and some of my best friends are
botanical collectors, but they are bound by the laws of the universe.
They can only move forward through time, right?
And they can only move through space.
And as they do that,
they're putting numbers on the things that they pick up,
and they're ascending, right? You've got time on the bottom and number on the--
time on the bottom axis,
record number on the
y-axis, and they're ticking up through time as they do that.
So we should be able to use an algorithm to crawl along that trace and find all
those records that fit together from one person's work.
And someone else's work
might be within the same timeframe, but because they're allocating a different
set of numbers, we should be able to disambiguate them.
And with that, those adjacent collecting events should be spatially
adjacent, right? They're not hopping between different continents.
They should be close together, so they're easier to georeference because we know
that they're close by.
It's really tiny on there, I can't read it.
Okay, so we
ran this density-based clustering using those two numeric pieces of data that I
showed you,
the collector number that the collector has put onto the specimen,
and the date that they were working, and that means that we get adjacent localities
close by. So,
I've been working on a project with colleagues in Malaysia, so a lot of my
examples are from there. But here we've got different ways that
different collecting localities have been written down, and they
all end up clustered nicely together so that we can do them together.
And we can also see
sometimes the number gets written wrong, people transcribe digits wrong, or we
get the wrong year, and we can nicely find outliers by
looking at the data this way.
So we've got nice context for a georeferencing workflow if it's a
human-oriented workflow.
But we've also
got a more precise way that we can use AI.
So rather than throwing in every record as a completely
atomic entry into an AI process,
we can bundle them all up together and say, "We've got context for these, like
Tell us about them as
a logical batch of work.
I'm
getting old, and I can't read tiny writing on there, so I have to read it with you.
We picked up everything that was in
vascular plants because that's our interest for the organization that pays my
wages.
We're looking at everything that is a species, and we're looking at everything from
a particular country. So we're not just looking at key records because we know
in botany we collect duplicates, and they get spread around to
many different herbaria, so this georeferencing task is something that we should
share as a community.
And
I'm really grateful to GBIF for the work that they did on the SQL downloads because
that made us be able to get only the columns we needed and also to push a
lot of preprocessing onto the GBIF side, so I didn't have to do it locally.
You probably want to read this in the slides rather than me go through it just now.
But I could do a lot of
processing within this SQL query
to look at whether we've got useful dates, say, whether we've got
useful computable collector numbers
that we can do interesting things with, and also on recorded by.
Is it trying to do a name, or is it
all these different ways that you can say that we don't know what collector it was,
like collector not known, all that kind of thing?
So yeah, I think as a community, sharing even the different ways that we say
that could be a useful thing that we could share.
I used a HPC facility that was kindly provided by my colleagues
at the Crop Diversity Institute in the UK, so that's something that we share
amongst six different institutes.
They were really, really helpful about the way we set it up.
And we split up the work into three different jobs, the big clustering job.
Once we've got the clusters, then, as I said, we can pass them into AI
in quite a tight context. So then we did things like,
well, we've got all these localities,
and we know that often we get habitat descriptions alongside localities.
So with all of those together, can you summarize the habitat that someone visited
on a trip?
My project that I'm working on in Malaysia is particularly interested in peat
swamps. We want to find the trips that visited peat swamps and look at
associated species there.
Also for georeferencing, it's really important to know the visitation pattern.
So
a team might have
traversed an area,
gone through a long linear process,
or they might have set up a hub-and-spoke model where they set up a base camp and
then radiated out every day. And differentiating the two can help
you when you're doing your georeferencing, either as a human or a machine.
And then we package up all the data at the end, and we use this interesting tool
called Dataset, which was met
the previous session I was in, also talked about.
So it's just a nice way that you can
mobilize a web app built over a SQLite database.
So a little bit like if anyone was in the earlier session about resilience,
where David Shorthouse was talking about
the technical choices that he made to
give resilience to Bionomia, then we tried to
write as little code as possible and to use existing and generic tools where we
could. So Dataset is one that
I would promote for that reason, too.
And this is a
screenshot of the--
So this is Dataset.
This is its web interface.
All the data that we generated was in a SQLite database.
But we've got this nice templating page for the results of
a clustering run and the collecting trip that we found in
it. So,
I guess, yeah. Okay. So this is not an unusual name,
but we've got this collector
active in this year, in 1964, gathered almost 2,000
specimens,
and we've been able to
take all the localities that were associated with that trip
and say to an LLM, "Summarize me
where they went, the habitats,
what looks to be the itinerary, pull out all the place names,
predict the regional unit that they all fall within."
So we got quite nice
higher-level general data about the specimens as a logical unit.
We've got some stats here. So of all of those, we've pulled them together, only
about a third are georeferenced.
But we could do those as a batch, as a community,
and we can pull those data out and handle them in
different georeferencing tools.
Or if you're happy that they were all collected by this collector called Chu, then
you can download a file that can be pushed into Geonomia, and
all those can be attributed together.
But just to prove that this is really
something that needs to be a community effort, these are all the datasets that
contributed to that trip.
So
it makes no sense in a world of not many resources that
we individually do georeferencing or automated approaches
in all of these different organizations, like
the place that we all should be working together.
So yeah, we've got a tool then and a process that recognizes
collecting trips, and I would argue that sits in quite a
nice space between
the work that GBIF have done recently to
recognize related records. If you can think about that, that sits at the
collecting event level
So,
in Herbaria, duplicate records all sit on the same collecting event.
And then quite at the other end of the scale, you've got things where
Bionomia are generating
the entire products of someone's collecting
career.
We're sat in the middle. We know that people work in bursts of activity,
and we're finding the collecting trips that share a context, and that's
something where
we can think that that's probably a useful entity for us to
recognize, and
it's where we can
target some of our curation effort in a better way.
But then stepping back a bit and also thinking about the conversations we're having
this week about BHL is,
we can form up after digitization our specimens
into logical groups.
So we can think about how they were collected,
like finding itineraries like I've just shown.
But then the other way that we form logical groups for specimens is
how they were used.
And there's this thing called the hypodigm, this idea that you should be able to
pull together all the specimens that are taxonomist-cited when they did their
work.
And if we can do both of those things, then we can more properly represent the
spatial or morphological extent of species.
And that's important when we're doing automated approaches.
Again, we don't want to treat specimens as atomic units.
We want to make meaningful batches and then use those with AI.
So
I'm here for the rest of the week. I'm also an organizer on
the Unconference, so if there are any of these kinds of aspects that you would like
to talk about there, then I'd be happy to do so.
But that's it. Thank you.
Thanks very much.
Right.
We're on time?
We do.
Next?
Great. Thanks very much.
So I take this off?
Yeah.
Or we-
Oh, yeah, you can go that way.
Give it.
You can give it to them. They'll take it.
He's already got his, so you're good.
Yeah.
And at the end of the next talk, Dave Bloom will be jumping up to give
us a quick announcement, and I'd like to jump in right now to say there will
be a table at lunch that will be open digital curation.
So if you have questions for us and you want to come hang out at our table and
continue the conversations that are starting in your brain based on what you're
hearing,
that's the place to be. So,
next up.
Please introduce yourself.
Yes.
Hi, I'm Pranav Jha.
We are from Climatra Carbon from India, and we map
invasive species across India and also in the APAC region,
which is Asia and Pacific. So, we are presenting our work
on how satellite imaging can be used
for biodiversity observability,
and we are mapping a particular species, which is Prosopis
juliflora.
So just deep diving into how we are mapping this invasive species, I'd
like to put some light on Prosopis juliflora, which is also known
as Neltuma juliflora. It's one of the alien
species classified as top 10 invasive species by IUCN,
and it has spread across all APAC regions,
especially in sub-Saharan Africa and
India, Pakistan, Bangladesh, Nepal.
And
we are trying to restore this in a particular region in India, which is
Kutch in Gujarat,
and we are mapping it using satellite data and our own
geofoundation models.
So, deep diving to grasslands of Kutch, it has
covered around 1.1 million hectares, and it is
destroying the native species, and also the pastoral
communities. And over the years, the
infestation has moved to other parts of India, which includes
the 20 plus agroclimatic zones across India.
So we are trying to map these to understand how
adaptive this invasive species is to our climate.
So why we need satellite data and satellite mapping to
understand how this invasive species is moving.
Why not just do the ground truths, understand how
the species characteristics?
So first, to understand the
invasion, you have to understand that at scale level,
how it's performing at different agroclimatic zones.
Second, how it changes over time. So multi-date imagery
tells us that how
the plant has grown from a
starting point till at canopy height is till four
meters,
and where to look next. So we know that in one
climatic zone, the invasion is high.
Where to predict at which climatic zones the
invasion will occur, and we can do the
restoration or other predictive measures at that point.
What it displaces. So, to understand that what kind of
natural habitat it can displace.
So it's like a predictive modeling, which we are doing, and we are creating
the datasets around it.
So yeah.
This is one of the maps, the satellite classifier
maps which we created
using our geofoundation models. You can see the infestation of Prosopis
juliflora
In Kutch, Gujarat, which is around 1.1 million
hectares. So this is one of the snapshots from our model.
And here you can see that over the years, we
just show the indicative numbers.
It's a patch of land, how the dense Prosopis juliflora has
become over the next eight years. That's from
2016 to 2023. It's a snapshot from Google
Earth.
So with classification of Prosopis juliflora, we are
also mapping how density is varying with
the different ecological areas and regions.
So, we are deep diving at 10-meter resolution,
so you can see how density is varying
with different ecological zone at
just a particular 50-hectare plot of land.
And it helps the ground team to understand the hotspots and
clusters, where the density is high, where it's sparse, and
where they should go and collect data.
So how this-- Yeah, just a second. Yeah.
So how this works. So, it starts with satellite data.
We ingest multiple satellite datas, like from Sentinels,
from
HSI datas, from HyperFlies, FireFlies, and AVIRIS,
the synthetic aperture radar data from NASA
ISRO dataset NISAR,
and we do our own ground truthing. So our ground team is there to
validate and to find the clusters which we have identified.
Then we have geo-based AI models.
If anyone have heard about AlphaEarth,
it's one of the geo foundation models which is used to understand the
spectral signatures of plants or any other things.
And we are using this geo foundation model to
understand the spectral signatures of juliflora and to
map it.
After this, we do the provenance layer, where we understand that over the
years, how it's performing and how the plant
species had adapted to the region and how, if you see
that in two different ecological zones, let's say,
one part of India in north and one part in south,
the
plant is behaving completely differently, and
the water retention rates is also very different.
So we are trying to study that and how the plant is
adaptive to that particular region
and occurrence, and using this data as usable
biodiversity data, and to creating embeddings
around it which can be utilized.
So how this model works. So first, we
use Alpha embeddings on our ground truths to create a classifier
model. Then we do the NDVI, which is a vegetation
index check
to understand the vegetation of that particular region.
And then we check for the slope, because while we're doing the study
that Prosopis juliflora
behave differently with the elevation.
So we are considering that as one of the factors that
when elevation changes, the plant adapts differently.
So the current accuracy of our model is 91%, and
it's already been included. We are working with Google DeepMind
team to include it in the Google Earth, so anyone can
just use it to understand the invasive species.
And we are also using this model to test it out
in different invasive species like Lantana camara, and also
for the mangrove classifications in sub-Saharan region.
Yeah. So one of the problems which we faced was,
the Prosopis is very similar to the native species, like
Prosopis cineraria, acacia, and also the woody
canopy is quite similar. So even if the ground
teams goes there and if they're not that
technical or understand the species properly, they can confuse it with
the native species. So what we are just doing that, we are using
hyperspectral imagery to do the spectroscopy
of these plants at three-meter resolution.
So the ground team already has which species is native and which
is Prosopis juliflora.
You can see the reflectance versus wavelength of the
Prosopis juliflora.
It's very significant and different
from other species. So it's easy for us
to create data sets of Prosopis juliflora with high accuracy so that
they can used by our ground teams and also by NGOs and
biodiversity groups,
which can
identify Prosopis and do the study on it.
How it works. So,
just consider it as a tile of 10 by 10 meter.
So
at 10 by 10 meter, let's say there are 10 plants.
Five of them are Prosopis, five of them are some other species.
So,
at three-meter resolution, we know exactly at what pixel
Prosopis is present or any other species is there, and we do the
thresholding accordingly to understand at three-meter
resolution. After this, we have three different zones.
The ground team do the drop zone, then they-
curating zone, and there's a refined zone to create the data sets
which can be used further in any other applications.
And the
georeferencing and ground truthing is done by our ground team, and we have a
proper record. So most of the things which was done earlier
in very conventional way, and there was a very high chance of data loss.
The ground team already have a base layer to understand where the plant is.
They just need to go and validate it, and they just need to focus on
dense areas and areas which is important for the study.
So the goal is not simply to map Prosopis juliflora more
accurately. It's to ensure that every prediction we make
today becomes transparent, attributable, and reusable evidence for
the biodiversity models of tomorrow.
So our next step is
to move to other species like Lantana,
which we are doing in the northern part of India, and also
we are moving to Sub-Saharan regions where
mangroves are there. So we are using same model with different spectral
signatures for mapping the species to understand how adaptive the
species are, and how
study can be performed on it. So, leveraging satellite data
and a geofoundation model is one of the
things of the future which can be used by the biodiversity
communities to understand the species.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. That was very interesting, Pras.
Yeah.
And promising.
Thank you.
Yeah. Dave, you want to make-- I wanted to say thank you to everybody.
Thank you to all our speakers and to...
You guys stand up so I can see you. So we co-organized this.
It's definitely a threesome, so
And we're-- Hmm? There's no online questions. Okay. At the moment. Okay.
And we're running out of time. Yes. Questions here.
Yes, we will pick- Just reiterate about the discussions.
Yes, we'll pick this up at lunch. There'll be a table, and we have a
discussion session at the end of today from 4:00 to 5:00, and we have a second part
of this session coming up after lunch.
Dave, you want to say it to-
You might just want to tell the people where to go for this discussion.
Got it.
Yeah. All right, so two things. Poster sessions are
during the breaks on the first floor where you got your coffee and your free cup
this morning. Please don't forget to visit the posters today,
Thursday, and Friday. But if you're interested in actually eating lunch
today,
this is important. But if you're not interested in eating lunch, you can mill about
the circles wherever you want.
But the door to get to the lunchroom, literally right out that door,
there's a nice set of wooden stairs to get you up there.
So if you're not keen on the stairs, you go a little bit farther down the hallway
in this direction, on the left side, there's an elevator.
So,
yeah. So it is there, Anne, also. Okay.
that door is your best bet to just go right up the stairs, but there are some other
places you can go as well. We love
catering to everyone. And Jen is going to the same lunch
room right
now.
Okay, thank you. And more open digital curation after lunch.
Thank you.
Hey, you two. Siobhan.
Thank you. Sabine. Thank you
To our sponsors, make sure to stop by and see them and say thank you, and reach
out and continue to expand the sponsors we have.
Please and thank you.
Lots of things on this slide. The main thing is keep everything
collegial, please. If you should run into any issues, let organizers
know or the moderators.
We do have people online, so if we have time for questions, you'll be asked
to share via microphone so they can hear you, so we're being
equitable.
And if you would like to continue the conversation with us, keep in mind this
is part two of this meeting, but we meet again
from 4:00 to 5:00 in the room called Baldur, and
that's an open discussion session about everything we've talked about so
far.
And we have an unconference on Friday afternoon,
and topics have popped into your head as a result of this that you'd like to find
other people who want to explore that topic with you,
we encourage you to come to the unconference.
And I think with that,
we're ready to get started.
So,
la, la, la. Aha.
So our first speaker
is
virtual. Welcome, David Shorthouse.
As a quick aside, Rod Page, Andrea Thomer, and I are
guest editing a topical collection in-
Sorry. Say again.
We can't see the video.
Hmm.
Might need technical help, y'all.
What button do I need to change to share it?
Mm-mm.
Who knows what the magic button is? I don't.
Safina, do you know?
Because it's not Zoom, so I'm not sure how to do...
I have to get rid of this.
Why is it?
That's the video.
Where's that slide here? Is that the...
That's PowerPoint. Sure. You can close that.
No, but that doesn't--
I don't know.
Technical help is needed here if you know how to get the video to play
up on the screen.
It might
have to show up there, yeah.
So that doesn't...
Because I'm just trying the microphones.
So you're trying-
Anybody know, y'all? Who's got the secret sauce?
When you play the video right now, you only hear the sound.
Oh, so you want to play the video.
We want it to appear up here.
Yeah.
On the screen.
Oh, do you have to slide it over?
Yeah, I think so. You have to do...
It's part-
Oh, yeah, that's right.
Doh. Oh, it's in my brain somewhere.
Yo.
Now I have to figure out how to press the play button, though, right?
Space bar.
Oh, space bar?
Nope.
As a quick aside, Rod Page, Andrea Thomer, and I are
guest editing a topical collection in the "Biodiversity Data Journal" entitled
"Beyond Digitization: Open Digital Curation of
Collections-Based Biodiversity Data." Annotations and
round-tripping of data enhancements feature prominently in the theme,
so please reach out to any of us if you'd like to learn more.
To set the stage, I draw your attention to a methods paper in "Plants,
People, Planet," published last December.
The authors here downloaded herbarium sheet images from GBIF and
managed to train an AI model to identify plants to species that
was 90% accurate.
They made a recommendation that the role of the specialist
taxonomist should now also include training
deep learning models to accelerate species identifications, because
who else could do that with any degree of authoritativeness?
But how is this meaningfully useful for a specialist taxonomist?
How does training a deep learning model result in direct
downstream credit for that taxonomist on all subsequent
determinations?
This sounds an awful lot like an uncharitable request to
work oneself out of a career.
So I wish to raise here an abundance of caution by attempting to
address one of the themes of this symposium session,
what is responsible AI? Particularly in relation to
honoring those who came before us and those who have developed all that
expertise.
We all share explicit norms of behavior and a responsibility to
foster positive relations. None of us wish to unknowingly
abuse anyone's motivations.
The suggestion here is just as breathless and
demotivating as is having volunteers transcribe
specimen labels on online platforms as a form of
Mechanical Turk, and then not openly publishing that data from
our organizations in a timely manner.
The presumed need here for ever faster solutions to digitize
specimens is not a trump card if in that
process, you shatter the trust it took decades to build
So forgive me for sounding a bit hyperbolic here, but it's also worth pointing out
that trust can be degraded through neglect or
omission.
A quick query on GBIF reveals that a full 60% of all
preserved specimens published by museums and herbaria do not have
any content at all in "identified by," one of the few
record-level terms we have in occurrence data that announces to the
world,
as stewards of these data, this is how we display the trusted people who
applied names to specimens.
The enormity of this omission has significant
implications for the success of the newly funded and launched
TETRIX project in the EU that aims to showcase the
impact of taxonomic expertise.
I echo Jan Mrník of Bonari that plant identification expertise
absolutely must be reclaimed, and I further broaden this to
all biota or any preserved material with affixed
determination labels.
Bionomia is now in its sixth year of operation and continues to
play a part in lowering the barrier of entry to enthusiasts and
taxonomists alike who wish to reclaim a more humanist,
less arcane expression of expertise.
Anyone with an ORCID is welcome to log in, explore how it works, and
to actively participate in the linking of natural history specimens to the
world's collectors and determiners, including your own specimens if they've
appeared in GBIF.
Like any project, it has its growing pains and its fair
share of limitations, but it has nonetheless enjoyed steady growth,
thanks to an interface translated into seven languages.
Once a month, roughly 320 million occurrence
records and growing
are redownloaded from GBIF. I'll walk you through how I
see where round-tripping of links generated in Bionomia by
volunteers has worked these past number of years, where it's fallen short,
some responsible AI-like activities that show some promise,
and I'll share some challenges that might be solved with the newly
ratified Darwin Core data package.
If you operate a collection management system that has a relational model,
chances are you are prepared to support some or all
of the more granular ways of expressing agents, the
relationships among and between them, and to the material they
acted upon in the emergent Darwin Core data package view of the world of
biodiversity data. This will be dramatically different from the
somewhat flat one-to-many relationships in our traditional
star-shaped Darwin Core archives.
There will be new opportunities in a data package to tease apart
what I call over-prescribed terms, like "recorded by" or
"identified by," into more semantic representations of
attribution as subjects, objects, and predicates
or verb-based actions.
As the new Darwin Core data package begins to take shape, there will be a period of
adjustment in how we share information about people.
Most notably, I predict that "recordedByID"
and "identifiedByID" will be rendered irrelevant
and eventually deprecated. Some of us, myself included on
earlier occasions, believed that these terms were a mistake to have
been created and ratified in the first place.
It's refreshing to see that agent name is a single field, so
that all cultural representations of people names can be accomplished.
But I question the need for a preferred prefix as part of
the name of the term itself.
Preferred to whom, and for what purpose?
And finally, we can now turn actions into a controlled
vocabulary as represented in agent role IRI.
But what we need now is a task group in the TADWIG attribution
interest group to ratify the items in that list that we
want to use, perhaps modeled after the contributor role ontology
from the OBO Foundry. Terms might include collected,
observed, determined, curated, illustrated,
preserved, transcribed, geo-referenced, et cetera.
Thankfully, we've made a great start on such a list, and it just needs to be taken
over the finish line.
Given that collectors are social creatures who participate in
various permutations of co-collector networks throughout their
careers, we can also be clever and employ
rudimentary continuous learning algorithms to tap into the
grand collector social network as it is being constructed.
So for instance, Truman Younker and Ray Baker at the
bottom had previously been attributed as collectors on this
snippet of an occurrence record in Bionomia.
Truman and Ray have co-collectors from yet
other occurrence records not shown here, whose names are very
similar to the parsed agent strings, FR Fosberg
or H St. John, as shown here in the green boxes.
And so those candidate matches that you see to known people
are boosted well above other people who might have similar names in the
collector social network that are not linked to either
Truman or Ray.
This is a small example for an enterprising and motivated informatician
to use this ever-expanding social graph in Bionomia
to a machine learning algorithm in support of some form of a lightweight,
hopefully offline, cross-platform attribution utility that
could be nested within a collection management system to help prompt
students or staff as they enter in new specimen data.
If you're that informatician, please reach out so hopefully we can find
some responsible way to do this.
First and foremost, any project, utility, or infrastructure that might
depend on human-generated data or information must have
valuable services for its individual users.
That's what drives uptake and positive feedback loops.
One of these in Bionomia is an ultra-simple email subscription
service if you'd like to receive notice when your collected or
determined specimens were downloaded from GBIF and used
in new published research.
It's functionally equivalent to the longstanding tradition in taxonomy
where authors of new taxa send their reprints, or now
PDFs, to the collectors as thanks for their early
efforts in the field.
And another service in Bionomia is for users to auto-archive versioned
snapshots of their claimed specimen records into Zenodo,
receive a DOI and formatted citation, and then include this in their
curriculum vitae alongside their formatted references to their published
papers.
Second, Bionomia has value-added services for organizations to help
engender round trips of enhancements.
When designing these, it was clear to me that there was no one-size-fits-all
solution. The solution, rather, was a menu of
CSV files in a frictionless data package.
Technical staff at an organization can write scripts against these,
and non-technical staff likewise can browse through them and
open them up in a spreadsheet editor.
A unique list of users, records that might be missing attributions
altogether, some whose collecting dates are in logical
conflict with collector birth or death dates, and other similar kinds of
files are all itemized in a descriptor, and then everything is
pushed into Zenodo so that you can retrieve at any time you wish.
A Bionomia HTML badge can also be pasted into an
organization's own webpage to help engender a bit more visibility in this process.
After many years of helping organizations integrate some of these
CSV files into their workflows while also reprocessing
new data from GBIF into Bionomia on a monthly basis, I've tried to
document numerous persistent challenges.
Round-tripping is nowhere near as easy as we might have assumed.
A view no doubt shared by the Filtered Push project that aspired to
do similar kinds of things with annotations in the early 2000s.
The single greatest problem has been, and continues to be,
unstable identifiers for occurrences.
The source of this issue is a complex blend of what I call
administrivia, technical snafus, data
migration from one system to another with ill-planned or disregarded digital
continuity, among other kinds of problems.
Whole datasets are frequently deleted from the GBIF index and replaced
as nested records in other datasets.
Yet other datasets are sometimes split into thematic subsets and then
republished, or datasets are deleted outright under the
assumption that the same but slightly variant records from other
sources are already being published.
Hilariously to me, the more stable term I often
use to stitch disconnected attributions back to a known
record
is catalog number.
Other challenges with no immediate solution in Bionomia is how to accept
attributions on rows in Darwin Core extension files, such
as identification history, as well as no home in
Bionomia for volunteers to record the evidence for their
asserted link between a person and an occurrence record.
In any case,
no organization has ever shown full readiness to
absorb the entire provenance of any attributed link
created by a volunteer in Bionomia.
None can record what third party made a link,
because these systems were never designed to do so.
User accounts are usually local, not
distributed in collection management systems.
In other words, some might be able to incorporate new
identifiers into their agent records in their collection management systems, but
none can record the date and time at which an unknown
person, such as a volunteer in Bionomia, asserted
that a particular person, as represented with an ORCID or a
Wikidata Qnumber, collected a particular specimen record.
The Darwin Core data package is not designed for this particular use
case, although we might get fairly close to it by making
judicious use of its provenance table.
So it remains to be seen whether or not the links created in Bionomia can be
fully shared across a distributed network.
Finally, some messages to revisit and to contemplate.
Round-tripping is much more difficult to do than we expected because the wheel can
be spun more than once. Conflicts in data begin to
creep in with every turn of the wheel.
The assumption that walled garden institutional collections management
systems are authoritative is clearly now a quaint
notion at best.
Source data from very large organizations are frequently unstable
and incorrect, whereas third-party enhancements made on their
data, once they're shared out, may be more stable,
transparent, and trustworthy.
As responsible stewards of natural history collections data, we must fully
populate identifiedBy or its equivalent in the emergent
Darwin Core data package. It is sloppy to do
otherwise and should be called out.
The role of the specialist taxonomist should be to do good
taxonomy.
The role of the data manager is to not omit metadata that is
essential for taxonomists and others to illustrate their expertise.
Thank you very much.
As a quick aside, Rod Page, Andrea Thomer, and I are
guest editing a topical collection in the Biodiversity Data Journal entitled
I have to figure out. Come on up.
You can help me figure this out.
Where's the X? Lord, y'all.
I have no idea.
Oh, it's there. I'm going. Getting warmer.
You're going to-- Yay.
Now for one up.
Okay.
All right, y'all. I'm going to have to find the mouse.
There it is. It's back again.
Oh, thank goodness. All right. Cool.
Well, that was fun.
And next up, can you introduce yourself?
Yeah. I am.
Yep.
Close it up.
Did I?
Yep.
Okay. Hi, I'm Siobhan Leachman. I'm a Wikimedian from New Zealand, and
I have been collaborating with... Ah, what happened?
It's come back. Cool. I've been collaborating with colleagues from Auckland Museum
Tūpapa, the National Museum of New Zealand, and the Bioeconomy Science
Institute.
I don't know why it's- It looks like there's a plug. Oh, the plug?
Is it because I'm stepping on it?
Okay. Hopefully, that's better. And I'll move away.
No.
Help.
Y'all.
Sorry, everybody. Technical difficulties.
Is
it the cord?
I tried pushing it in. Didn't seem to
make any difference.
Is it, I assume, is it this?
I don't know.
I can sort of turn it off, and I can do it on the machine, if it
helps.
Maybe.
Okay. Cool. I'll push it forward on this.
Which-
Yeah.
Use that one. Okay. Hopefully, I'll push the right button.
Sorry. Where was I?
No.
We don't either. Anybody have an idea what's shorting out?
Pull out the HDMI cable and put it back in.
There we go.
Or you can connect it to there. Yeah.
Another cable?
HDMI cable.
They said HDMI cable.
This one?
Yeah, pull it out and push it in.
It's not loose.
What's in there? How many cables does it take?
Lots.
Before it's folded.
Is that better?
Okay.
Find out in a minute.
Yep. HDMI seems to be-
As soon as you turn your back.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah.
Sorry about that, everybody.
No.
Nope.
Still not working. Can you give your talk without them, Siobhan?
Just-
Well, the... Okay, there's links to the slides in there.
They're in Zenodo. If you can quickly see the Zenodo link.
There's a Bitly link. I have yet to put them in Wiki Commons, but they will be in
Wiki Commons. They're practically as many places as I can put them, but just
not on the screen.
Murray, get the Bitly link. There you go.
Do I have to hold it?
Try and get the-
I'll hold it and see if that helps.
Yeah.
Sorry about that, everybody. Anyway, okay, I'm giving up.
I'm going to give my presentation. Hopefully, you can find the slides.
I'll also put it in the notes.
The Bioeconomy Science Institute, as well as members of the Wikidata community,
to create a proposed data model for type specimens items in
Wikidata.
Is it going to go forward? Yeah. Okay, so we were motivated to undertake
this work as editors have and continue to create
Wikidata items for type specimens.
But the modeling used for these Wikidata items is
currently inconsistent, so we're wanting to rectify this.
We're also aiming to assist museum and research institutions to
translate their Darwin Core compatible data
into Wikidata compliance statements, and in doing so, we're hoping to encourage the
interoperability of this type of data.
We're also keen to support the digital extended specimen work being
undertaken by the wider biodiversity community because we believe that Wikidata
can actually play a pivotal role in interlinking the data and sources for
type specimens.
Another motivator for this work is the potential for natural history institutions
to add to, add or at least link to these Wikidata items in their
collection management systems, and also in other natural history
databases. And this reuse would make it easier for anyone to trace
where these important physical specimens are held and would also improve the
findability of data about those specimens, including the publications
that discuss them and the taxa that they relate to.
Also, the data held in Wikidata is being reused by a multitude of
AI applications, and this reuse provides yet another avenue
of access, reuse, and visualization of type specimen data.
Now, Wikidata can aid the creation of responsible AI
applications. Wikidata tracks the data origins via the
references provided for each specimen.
Sorry, each statement, and Wikidata's also transparent as it
tracks all the edits being done to an item via either the
Wikidata account making those edits or if there is
no account, there's via the IP address being used by
those editors. So by providing type specimen data and
ensuring that it is modeled consistently and referenced
appropriately, Wikidata can actually help AI applications be
transparent about the provenance and source of the information those
applications are providing to users of their services.
Now, I just want to emphasize that the data added to Wikidata in
line with the proposed type specimen data model is not
intended to be canonical. What we are aiming to do is use
Wikidata as a finding aid to facilitate access to
the relevant data about type specimens and their related
identifiers. We aim for Wikidata to act as a bridge
between the different sources of information about the type specimen
and also provide links to the canonical data at source.
That
is to the data being provided by the holding institution.
So how do we go about creating this proposed data model?
Well, the process included comparing existing items on Wikidata
and considering the properties being used by editors.
We also had a look at the data standards created by this informatics
community, including Darwin Core.
We took a pragmatic approach.
As I know you'll be aware, many institutions upload this type of data to
aggregators like GBIF. We wanted to make it easy for
individuals associated with these types of institutions to
also share the data related to type specimens with Wikidata.
Another major consideration was how data might be extracted
from Wikidata. We thought about the types of queries the biodiversity
community might ask or want visualized and modeled the
data to ensure that these queries could be easily created.
We proposed several new Wikidata properties.
This included new properties for the collector, the specimen classifier,
the collection date, and the location collected.
And we were attempting to rectify the use of some Wikidata properties
as workarounds and wanted to ensure that pivotal data could be added
to the Wikidata type specimen item.
Finally, we created a batch of Wikidata items for holotype
specimens held at a New Zealand nationally significant collection,
the New Zealand Arthropod Collection.
The trial batch upload was based on a holotype specimen data
extracted from GBIF, placed in the data curation tool OpenRefine,
cleaned, and then reconciled with and uploaded into Wikidata,
and this batch helped us test and refine the model.
Now, as well as existing type specimen items and the likely queries of Wikidata,
the model was also informed by attempting to crosswalk properties used
in it to the concepts used in Darwin Core.
And this crosswalking really helped us learn about how institutions
aligned type specimen data with Darwin Core and then share this
data with GBIF, and it helped us think about the appropriate Wikidata
properties that were needed. It also encouraged us to
consider how the proposed model might be extended.
So where do you find the model and its associated documentation?
Well, we created a Wikidata Wiki Project page to aid collaboration with
the wider Wiki community. The Wiki project contains not just
the data model, it also contains supporting documentation and the
crosswalking mappings between the model and Darwin Core.
We also uploaded our documentation into Wikimedia Commons, so you can easily
download it there.
To make the documentation accessible to a wider audience, we added it
to the research repository Zenodo, and importantly, we formed a
Zenodo community.
We created this for this project, and it includes an Excel spreadsheet
generated from the OpenRefine upload that I discussed earlier.
All of this was aimed at helping guide institutions and editors
when creating or enriching type specimen items in Wikidata.
We've curated exemplar holotype Wikidata items, and these
items illustrate the data model and show just some of the sources of data
and identifiers that can be linked via Wikidata.
So for example, there is an exemplar Wikidata item for a
holotype that was first observed in iNaturalist, as well as an item
that links to the Disco generated DOI for the digital record of that
specimen.
And here's a list of the Wikidata properties currently being used in the model.
Now, these properties obviously help enrich the type specimen item with
semantically linked data statements.
And importantly, identifiers have also been added to items
if Wikidata properties exist for those identifiers.
So in this slide, you can see an example of where an iNaturalist observation ID
for that type specimen has been added to the item.
And if a Wikidata property for an identifier does not actually currently exist,
the data can still be linked via the describedat URL property.
Now, we recognize this data model is a work in progress, and
improvements can be made. For example, we've proposed
the creation of a Wikidata property for the GBIF occurrence
ID. This is under discussion with the Wikidata community at the moment.
Currently, the basis of record data is modeled as an instance
of statement.
Ideally, a new Wikidata property should be proposed to describe the
nature of the record, improving alignment with Darwin Core.
Another area of future work is the incorporation of the preservation method of
the specimen. Again, to include this, a Wikidata property
proposal for the preservation method would also be required.
And last, but certainly not least, we also considered proposing a
Wikidata property for bicultural notices to support the inclusion
of local context notices in this model.
GBIF is pilot testing the traditional knowledge and bicultural
labels on occurrence records at the moment.
We very much support this work, but we decided to
delay any Wikidata property proposal until the infrastructure
and associated guidance exists in GBIF and in Darwin Core.
Now, I'm coming to the end of my presentation, but before I finish, I just want to
emphasize that one of the main benefits of Wikidata is that it
empowers anyone to create and enrich these types of items.
While creating holotype specimen items in line with our proposed model, I and
other Wiki editors like me have been able to digitally connect
collectors, determiners, localities, publications, collection dates,
significant events such as research expeditions,
and importantly, also ensure that the relevant identifiers are all
semantically linked to these in Wikidata.
Wikidata helps democratize this type of data curation
and empowers the wider biodiversity community to enrich and link data
related to these important specimens and ensuring everyone can
contribute to improving the visibility of these
specimens and the interoperability of their related
data.
So thank you for listening, and hopefully I'll get some questions from you later.
Thank you.
Hi, everybody. So it's been explained to me that there was some sort of power
outage in the system, and they need to come and reset it, which they are not
currently here to do. So we're having a little tête-à-tête about do she
progress and deal with what we're dealing with, and then take a break after the
next speaker? I think maybe that will work. Can you manage?
We can try, if it works.
Improv, here we go.
Yeah.
All right. So thank you everybody for your understanding.
Right?
Okay. No.
We have to move it.
Oh, yeah.
Do you know how to-
Well,
no you're okay. It should have just done it.
It's a PDF. It's not a PowerPoint.
Oh. Okay. That's all right.
You have to move it.
Yes, I have to move it, but it means I'll have to find the mouse again.
Yeah.
Okay. Is it right or left?
Go to the left.
It's left. Thank you.
Very satisfying. Thank you.
All right. But now, wait, can I move it?
No.
Oh, gosh.
Yeah, no, it's...
All right.
Oh, well.
Okay.
Good.
Oh, no.
The pointer doesn't work.
Okay. That works.
Okay.
Good afternoon. My name is Sabine von Mehring.
I'm a botanist and data scientist based at the Museum für
Naturkunde, where I head the research group Data for Nature.
And today I'm here to speak on behalf of the task group
Modeling Research Expeditions.
As you can see here, several of my co-authors are members of that task group,
but we are a larger group.
As you all know, research expeditions
are a major source of specimens and natural history collections,
connecting distributed cultural heritage across institutions and
countries.
Historically, these expeditions were often transdisciplinary.
Biological and earth science specimens were collected
alongside ethnographical and anthropological objects.
As a result, specimens and other materials gathered
during the same expedition, together with their associated
data and metadata, are often distributed across
multiple institutions.
Consequently,
expedition data remain fragmented, inconsistently
modeled, and often lack persistent identifiers.
This hampers discoverability, interoperability, and provenance
tracking.
It also makes it more difficult to contextualize collecting
events and practices within the broader historical context,
including colonial contexts.
Research expeditions continue to contribute to natural history
collections today. There's therefore a need to establish
clear links between historical, contemporary expeditions, and the
entities connected to these events, such as specimens,
publications, people, and institutions.
This requires unambiguous identification and
persistent identifiers for the expeditions themselves.
So what actually constitutes an expedition, and how do we
represent it in our data?
Terminology is
an important topic, and especially here in the context of a standard
organization. We have already heard from David and
others about the Darwin Core terms and the Darwin Core data
packages and the agent term and the event,
and also the parent event ID is relevant in
our context here.
The terms research expeditions and scientific expeditions
are themselves not unproblematic.
We recognize that such expeditions often took place within
complex historical contexts and could be closely
intertwined with colonial agendas and economic
and/or military interests.
We have created a working definition for research
expeditions, which you can see here.
A research expedition is a specific organized field activity
involving one or more people at one or more locations,
undertaken in affiliation with or in support of an
institution for the purpose of conducting, supporting, or
advancing research within a defined start and
end date.
An expedition is a distinct time-bounded activity
that can be distinguished from ongoing or routine collecting
activities.
It has a defined research aim,
although research
is not always the sole purpose. And yes,
obviously there are and there will always be edge cases where it is hard
to differentiate, and this is a draft definition on which we are still working.
So in GBIF, an expedition can already be
represented as an event,
and the parent event ID can be used to link collecting events to a
broader expedition event. In some data sets, Wikidata
QIDs are already used as identifiers for
these parent events.
Our task group is currently exploring and promoting the use
of Wikidata QIDs as globally unique resolvable
identifiers for expedition events
where appropriate. And in the longer term, we are considering whether
more explicit support for research expeditions in Darwin Core would be useful.
But this is also something we have to compare and discuss
also with the
Darwin Core data package.
The key idea is, however, to treat the expedition itself as a
first-class entity that can be identified and linked to
other entities.
So this work is part of the research expedition task group, which
is part of the collection description interest group,
and the group focuses on developing a model for structured,
linked open data describing research expeditions.
The aim is to develop a model that can work across institutions,
collections, and data systems.
Our goals include identifying stable identifiers and creating them
for research expeditions, developing guidelines
for describing expeditions in Wikidata, and
linking expeditions
to related entities.
We use Wikidata as an open, collaborative, and multilingual
knowledge base for describing expedition metadata,
and it provides a way to link research expeditions
to and from collection management systems, data portals,
and aggregators.
By proposing a Wikidata schema, providing practical
examples, and recommending best practices, the task group aims to
improve the accessibility, discoverability, and
contextualization of expedition-related data.
And in addition, we have also created a Wikidata Wiki project
on research expedition to document our activities
also
within the WikiWas for the Wikidata community, and to
provide information specifically for Wikidata editors.
So this is an example of a Wikidata item for the Harriman
Alaska Expedition, and it demonstrates how an expedition can be described
as a distinct entity and linked to related people,
organizations, publications, collections, and other
entities.
So
a Wikidata item can be created with a minimum set of
recommended properties, including instance of,
like it is an expedition or research expedition, start and end
time, country or country of origin, participants,
collection items at, where the material is housed, and archives at.
The model is designed to be lightweight but extensible,
and additional properties can be added as needed, depending
on the available information and desired level of
detail.
These may include the funder of the expedition, the field of work,
the goal, start point, and so on. A complete
itinerary is also possible and can be visualized afterwards.
So this allows institutions to start with a basic,
consistent description while providing the flexibility to
enrich expedition records over time.
And this is a quick look at the broader Wikidata schema, which
includes
a number of additional properties
to describe the
expeditions and their relationships to other entities.
It is intended as a flexible starting point rather than a fixed and
exhaustive list of properties.
To increase transparency and to improve discoverability of
collection objects, Wikidata links are also added to the
collections holding specimens gathered during expeditions
using the property collection items at.
Where available, persistent identifiers for the individual specimens
can also be added there as a reference for this statement.
And we also include statements indicating whether relevant
archival material,
such as logbooks, field books, correspondence, or the personal
papers and estates of expedition participants are held.
If available, direct links to the finding aids, if
possible, with a DOI or a proper link to access,
can be added there as well.
All this linked open data can then be used to visualize the
relationships between people, publications, expeditions, and
collections in a knowledge graph.
This example here was created using Scholia and is based
on data from Wikidata. It shows the Harriman expedition,
which I mentioned earlier, and its
connections to expedition participants,
publications
resulting from the expedition, and collections holding the
specimens gathered during this event.
The GitHub repository of the task groups provides
documentation of the ongoing work, and it also
provides
open issues and the discussion about these.
And you can use the QR code to check these in
the repo and maybe contribute to the discussion.
So what are the recommendations emerging from the task group's work
so far?
The task group proposes an expedition data model that
connects historical and contemporary collecting events with
specimens and other collection objects, participants,
institutions, localities, itineraries,
publications, and archival records.
In other words, identify the expedition, describe it once, and
then link to the distributed evidence and objects,
link them back to it.
Particular emphasis is placed on interoperability with Darwin Core
and the use of persistent Wikidata identifiers, and also the
collaborative community curation of expedition
metadata, which is done within Wikidata.
And as a complement to, or an alternative to maintaining
all the expedition metadata exclusively within the collection management
system,
they can be placed in Wikidata and then the identifiers integrated in the
collection management systems. So our recommendations
or some first recommendations are to create new or enrich
existing Wikidata items for research expeditions,
particularly focus on those where you have the institutional
knowledge and the archival material,
and then use the minimum recommended properties as a starting
point and extend these descriptions where
appropriate.
And yeah, record these Wikidata identifiers, the
QIDs in your collection management system.
Several systems have these options already to integrate those.
And these QIDs can then be connected to
specimens and other collection objects.
So these recommendations aim to improve data
quality, facilitate cross-institutional linking, annotation, and
validation workflows, and increase transparency about the
historical context of collecting activities.
And by enabling
machine-readable and multilingual representations of expeditions,
the proposed model can contribute to making collection data more
fair and support broader reuse, for example,
in knowledge graphs, visualization tools, and digital
humanities research.
So we are now finalizing the recommendations,
discussing open issues, and then plan to publish
these recommendations for the community and
share.
And the aim is to create a resource also that
can support research questions, provide historical context,
and offer insights into the provenance, collecting
context, and historical trajectories of collecting objects.
So this is a large task, however, and it can be achieved not by
one group on its own. So we therefore really encourage you all
in your institutions, in collections to
contribute to this effort and open up the information you
have about research expeditions,
create and curate this data in Wikidata, and link
to your collection management systems, integrate them.
So together, this can help make expedition
histories more discoverable,
also more inclusive if we can add the hidden contributors to knowledge
creation, which are often not visible in the specimen
itself and the labels, but often in the archival material.
And,
yeah, make this information
accessible for all.
Thank you very much to my co-authors and the whole TADWIG task group and
the wider TADWIG and biodiversity and Wiki community.
And with that, I'm coming back to the title, "Here,
There, and Everywhere," The Beatles.
And thank you very much for your attention.
Come on.
Yes.
I can't.
We're good. I'll help you.
You do that.
He's going to fix it.
Thank you.
So it turns out that the folks online didn't have that issue we were having in
here. It was only in here. So yeah.
He's got to reset this.
He's got the magic button.
I hope.
So thank you very much,
Siobhan. Thank you for dealing with the improv moment, and
Sabina as well.
Yeah.
We have to go get hers from the other side. Yeah.
You're ahead of me, Esteban. Good job. Yeah.
Okay.
Did he leave already?
Is the reset done or not yet?
I think he's your key, right?
The gentleman there in the very back?
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
That's looking promising. Ish.
Aha.
Can you hear me?
Not yet. Can you turn on Esteban's mic?
I do. Yeah.
Okay, thank you very much.
I'm here to present this about how
digital curation is going to a circular process.
I want to start with a
quick overview of how data curation can go around.
So
researchers and publishers are part of an institution.
They go and prepare their data. Before publishing data,
they go through, it can be a GBIF node, or sometimes it can be in
their own institutions, to a data manager, and they give them feedback.
And they tell him, "Okay, you have missing data," or, "You have these things." So
it's a little loop before that.
After that, they go to an aggregator, in this
case, GBIF, and GBIF also give them feedback
that say, "Okay,
you have missing identifiers, you have conflicting
dates."
And at the end, they publish, and there can come a user,
and the user can give this feedback to several parts.
It can be to GBIF directly, to the nodes, or you can write an
email to the original publisher like, "Hey, I found this problem in your
data."
I want to start with a caveat. I'm going to do this example from SIB
Colombia, because I used to work there.
But I know that all of our nodes in GBIF
have different approach to data quality.
So I know people in Thai GBIF has a process,
people in other nodes have different ways
to improve their data. This is just a particular case because
I'm the most used to.
So SIB Colombia is the national GBIF node.
It's a network of organizations with the main objective of
contributing data to research, education, and
policy-making.
And at SIB Colombia, we have this little thing that is called acompañamiento,
that is wrongly translated, but guidance in Polish.
So before every dataset is published in
GBIF,
it goes through our hands in the SIB Colombia helpdesks.
So a human being sitting beside
gets the data from a publisher. And we do a quick, well,
it's not that quick, but we do a
review, semiautomatic process, using OpenRefine,
using the GBIF API, using QGIS, and
we review metadata and some
40, 30-something different Darwin Core elements that
we think add more value to this. And we
review that they are complete, that they are consistent.
And along this process,
you can go to our webpage and check how is the process.
And we are filling an Excel report.
An Excel report that says, okay,
if there is something that is really obvious and we can update,
like basis of record, because they
fill it in Spanish and not in English, we change that and put
it in the Excel. Or if they have a problem, we put that in the
Excel file and say, "Okay, you have missing identifiers.
You cannot publish with that. Please fix that."
Or your coordinates are saying that you are in the capital
of Colombia, but when I put them, they are in the ocean, so fix that.
We only publish data after they have fixed this.
So
there has been a feedback before publish.
Next, we go to the aggregator level in GBIF.
All records that go through GBIF
pass through a series of
steps. Oh.
Yes.
Okay.
I'm going to focus here in particular in the taxonomy, because we're going to see
it later.
So you can see people can put their taxonomical
names in different ways. Sometimes they have
SP,
sometimes they have a little
mistake in an
A, or it's not an A, it's an I, something like that.
And in GBIF, we interpret these names and say, "Okay, the first two names
are the same, Calopteryx aqualit." And we put the
full scientific name with the authorship.
And we do this for other elements, for
elevation, for dates, for controlled vocabularies,
with the goal to help
publishers, users to have these flags,
taxon match fuzzy, taxon match high rank, invalid date,
invalid coordinate, so they can
use that information to improve their data.
So if you're a publisher, you can use our tool, the Data
Validator.
It's an online tool that you can upload your Excel file or
your Darwin Core archive, and it's going to run through
all the same process that goes when you publish your data in GBIF,
and it's going to give you some issues and flags that you should
maybe want to look at. Sometimes they are not problems,
sometimes they are
maybe things you are missing, maybe when taxonomy
is not up to date.
But you can go there, check the information,
and improve your data before publishing.
You can also go check the Data Validator.
And we have the same for users. So after you have published your
data,
if you download the occurrence format annotated, you
can have the-- oh.
You can-
have this column with the specific issue and flag that
we found for every record. Or you can go at the data set level
and say, "Okay, this data set in particular has a
basis of record that is invalid." It can be because it's missing, because it's
not the full name.
And you can use that to either choose, if you are a
user,
not to use this data or go back to the publisher and say, "Okay, I really want
your data set, but I found that it has missing coordinates or
invalid coordinates, and I need them.
So can you please fix them?" Or if you are a publisher and you see your
data set and go to the issues and qualities and say, "Oh, there are
six flags. What is wrong? I would like to fix that."
And finally, we have the feedback to
GBIF. So we get a lot of feedback in GBIF in the help desk.
This is just a sample from three months, the first
three months of this year. We have probably 700
messages asking for help.
Most of the messages ask for general help.
How do I use GBIF? How do I cite this data?
I want to know more about GBIF.
I have a question about this specific
bid program, things like that.
After that, we have IPT questions, either from the IPT
test or how to install an IPT.
And
finally, we have
taxonomy-related issues. These taxonomy-related issues
can be either
this taxonomical name is wrong in the GBIF backbone, or
can be like this specific occurrence record is
mapped to the incorrect name.
So it's not that much that you used to think before.
And there is also a data content like, okay, your data
in GBIF is wrong, and you should fix that.
It's
from the 700 standards.
And the most interesting thing is how many of these
cases are fixed.
So for taxonomy, as of the last
two weeks that I made this,
45% of the
feedback for taxonomy problems was fixed.
That's thanks to Catalogue of Life, the extended release.
So someone put the feedback, and with the new extended release, well,
now it's fixed. This name was missing or was a synonym.
Now it's in the correct place. So we fixed, well, we as
a community, not we as the secretariat,
some of the 45%,
40-something percent. And for data content is some
37-something percent. So people fix their
data. So if you contact a publisher, they will try
to fix the data.
We all know that they have
problems with a limited amount of time or limited amount of
capacity, but
they try to do the best. And I think 30-something percent is a good
amount of things that are fixed. So if you found
something that has a problem, you can contact directly
the publisher or us, and we will send the feedback to the publisher,
and it will get fixed in
one third of the times.
And to finish,
how to use AI in this.
Currently, we're only using AI
to summarize some of the taxonomic feedback.
So my colleague John,
he developed this in
GitHub Actions. So we have a lot of feedback
for taxonomy-related things. Sometimes this feedback, if you are
not a taxonomic expert, can be a little bit hard to understand.
So we use an LLM, it's
OpenAI,
John programmed it to follow
several steps and to create this JSON file
summarizing with some categories like wrong name,
missing name, missing category, something like that.
So what the LLM does is summarize the comment.
That sometimes can be really specific with a DOI,
with the new publication. Sometimes can be like, your
name is wrong.
It just creates this JSON file. After that, we
review the JSON file. 70% of the time, we are
updating this JSON file. So we are not just clicking accept.
We update the JSON file just to check everything is correct.
And then we have another step that is used with
GitHub Actions, and this step is not
using AI, it's just using a script.
It's a deterministic step that goes to Catalogue of Life, the
last version of the extended release, and to check if this
JSON thing is still open or not.
So here it says that
Parmo trona is supposed to be
accepted. Currently, it's a synonym.
And in the last
Catalogue of Life extended release, it's still open.
So it's still appearing as a synonym.
That, according to this person, is wrong.
But this message, I reviewed that the help desk of
Catalogue of Life, so they can say, "Okay, this is incorrect." Or
maybe the people that published the checklist for bees
update it, and in one month, this will run
again and say, "Okay, now it's solved." And the issue is
closed, and we don't have to put more time to close this issue again.
And you can go to Backbone Feedback Repository
to check how this is done or to log your issues
about taxonomy.
Thank you very much.
Hi, everybody. We still have a minute or two in your time.
Do you have any questions, anyone, for Esteban
about their work
or their AI inclusion?
No.
Not yet?
Do you get any feedback, Esteban, from your community on the
use of AI in the process?
Not yet. This process is fairly new.
John implemented this this year,
and we are now just using it to summarize things.
So it's not like you are putting on AI or LLM to fix
things. So this is a nice little thing to
save time, basically.
Mm-hmm.
Instead of doing manually-
Mm-hmm
... you save time.
And
in SIP Colombia, we were starting to think about how we could
use AI
to
review,
to increase the speed that we do this process, but we
were just in early stage of how this can be done.
So it's just starting to see how things are doing, and also
models are getting really good really fast.
So what you try six months ago may be-
Yeah
... different right now, so.
Yeah, for sure. Okay. Is that time where we...
Thank you. Thank you, Esteban.
You're welcome.
So we... Yeah.
Pat,
good to get...
Yeah, exactly. Hand off.
Esteban.
So...
Yes.
There we go. Are you ready?
You want this?
Yes. Oh, okay.
Okay, hold on.
Voilà.
I can just use this.
You can. As you wish.
Okay.
Please introduce yourself.
Okay. Hello.
Hello, everyone, and good afternoon.
My name is Shih-Hsen Li. I'm from
Biodiversity Research Museum and Biodiversity
Research Center, Academia Sinica, Taiwan, and also
Taipei. Yeah, such a long name.
And my topic is Closing Gap in Specimen Metadata.
Yeah, and because
myself, I'm working on a
natural history collection management system for our
institution, and that is a platform
that any other different institution can
use the same platform. And then we find some problem,
I will explain later. And
that is the,
oh,
that's a GBIF data trend. You can find
that
graph in GBIF's data trend.
That is captured from GBIF data trend page, and
it has some explain about the data completeness.
Yeah. I think you maybe know the data completeness,
maybe including the
metadata that
didn't have the full date
of the specimen's collection date, and
they don't have the identification for the
species rank, or they don't have the valid
coordinate, or even the locality in the
Biden text. And that's
about the data completeness.
And we can see that that's
is also from GBIF data trend page.
It's a global scope. And the left
side is the
observation records, like data, most of
data from eBird or iNaturalist. And
the right one is the
specimen data. Yeah,
in GBIF, the
basis of record is a preserved specimen, or fossil
specimen, or living specimen. And we can see that the
specimen data, the
yellow color
means
that
the data from
observation data and specimen data also
increased this year
very much. But the specimen data lack
of completeness, and that gap is getting
larger and larger. So that's a problem, and we want
to try to fix that.
And because I'm from Taiwan, so I found the
data trend from Taiwan also, and that
it's like the same, so maybe it's
everybody has the
issues. And
why cause that? Because the
take image is very fast. You only need seconds
to take a image or even use a scanner, maybe
Maybe
one or two minutes can down. And everyone can do that, they just
press the button and no need
train
human to do that. And
it's easy to buy an equipment,
scanner or camera. And
the
image are stored in hard drives. But about the
transcription, it's very slow, take time,
and needs expert to read the old handwriting.
Also in Taiwan, we have some different era,
some
Western exploration era and Japanese era.
So different,
also have some handwriting or
different type of specimen label.
It's really hard to read if
the transcriber not well-trained.
And the transcriber,
we have to another fund for them to do
that.
But after transcribe, the data, have
metadata you can be searched for and useful in public data.
It's easy to find. But it's a
bottleneck.
But,
it started from maybe three
years ago, and
we have
nature history collection management system.
And
we also help other
institution in Taiwan. They
don't have enough money to set up a database or
do the digitization for their own.
So we just,
in our institution, we have some cooperation,
and we provide the system for them to
upload their data, and they
assign some people to do the digitization.
But no one to transcribe the data, so the data still
hidden in
the hard disk or even in the cloud because it has no
metadata. We just can see a lot of pictures, but
it's hard to find.
And so,
we
let
the institutions'
teacher, the college teacher, they
ask their student in the class to do the transcription.
And
that's
unpaid free labor.
So they can do this, and the teacher can give the grade and
assign every student a homework, like hundreds of
specimen data they have to transcribe.
But that's maybe two or three years.
And then we use AI to
quickly do this. And then we find that that's
only solve the problem of only one
institution, and the pace is still very slow.
So we try to, in Taiwan, we have another
organization called TBIA, Taiwan
Biodiversity Information Alliance.
And that's,
we
combine many institution or government
organization in Taiwan. They have biodiversity
data, and we collect the data together and make a
aggregated portal and
website. And that data also publish
in GBIF. So that's just
national well-aggregated data.
So I
try to make a system that this
use AI for help transcription can
apply to all the specimen in the TBIA system.
And that everybody can
help transcribe
via the system. And the transcription, the annotation will
keep in the system and help the data provider to...
They can quickly closing the gap of the
missing metadata. And the specimen in
TBIA,
the natural history
data is about 2 million data. And the
data says it's across
Taiwan institution and
worldwide museum. That's from GBIF data.
Yes. And
thanks for TBIA has made a good
aggregate of the data, so I can quickly find that.
That's
different flake of the data, like
30% of the data are missing identification.
But it's not real missing because,
when some data
provider, they publish to some
organization portal and then go to the TBIA, and
each
step maybe, the
mapping scientific name maybe a little change.
And so that
will cause the-
Scientific name matching problem.
And
all of the data will match
by the TAICo. It's
like catalog
of Taiwan, and it's a national
species checklist. And
TBIA already mapped the specimen
scientific name to the TAICo, so it's linked.
And then the missing coordinate data
has many, above
65%. But most of that,
it still have some locality information. Yeah.
So, we still can find the coordinate because
it's in verbatim locality. So, we
have some
clue to find that.
But the most problem is missing media data, because if
you don't have the picture, you cannot do
a transcription things. And now, this is the
system
looks like. And you can explore the
data in the TBIA. And
then you can see that some
terms are missing. So,
the right side is you can see the specimen and
try to help them
fill the missing terms. And you
can just use your eyes to do that, and
you can use AI. We have integrated the
AI API that can transcribe and...
Yeah. And transcribe, and you can choose, because the AI maybe
has wrong, especially the local name
in which in Chinese. Yeah. The
handwriting English, I think AI is
very good at it. But in Chinese,
or Japanese,
I think it's
hard for AI to do that. And so a human
needs to
do some
correction on that. And the system will save the
data that
the AI transcribed, or human correction.
And later, we can analyze that AI's doing
good or
not good. We can analyze later.
And then we have doing
some data
analysis, and we have
make the collectors
and identifier.
I've made some story about the...
You can find a collector and
his collection trip in a map and
by ear. And you can find that some data,
when the data list
on the table, and you can just quickly see that
maybe some data is missing locality or missing date,
and when this data is
put together, grouped by the
collector. Yes. And that's also,
I try to make some old
literature from Taiwanese
botanical survey history, and it can be linked to
some data existing in the TBIA now.
Yeah. And that's the other story.
And that's the future work I want,
data provider through this system, and they
get the acceptable data. And
that correction data will go back to the data provider.
They can decide,
and they can quickly update
their data and publish again. And
we wish to make the data more, the quality is more better.
And we also want to try to use that
system to
let other institution in Taiwan that had not
digitized their specimen, and
want to say that an untranscribed image is not a
failure, it's an invitation. Because
Taiwanese
organization, maybe they feel like if they
publish, that data is incomplete, they will
feel
they have failure or they are not...
But it will stop the...
Everybody cannot find that data. And
so, yes, the system wants to do that.
And
thanks for everybody.
So, Lee Tzu-chen.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Okay. That's not so easy. I want to reassure everyone, if
you're intrigued as I was by his challenges, to give us
exciting bits to think about how to facilitate language,
things like in Binomia-
Yeah.
... and being able to do what you envision there.
Yes.
And add that for your community.
That's really exciting.
Yes.
Yes, and-
I'm trying to do
Yeah, there you go.
Yeah.
When I doing this project, I was thinking, I want
to let the collector's name sync with
Binomia and Wikidata, and that's what make the data easier
to-
Let people know that we have some collection or specimen
here.
Yeah.
So thank you for that. And to all of you who find this intriguing,
online, the recording is fine, and the slides are there,
so you don't lose the story that Li Hu Xin, I have to say
it.
Yeah.
Xu Xin.
Yeah. Perfect.
Thank you.
Was telling us. So thank you for that.
Okay. Thank you.
All
right.
Do you guys want to do a tech thing now, or should we just do the last talk?
Pat, would you rather have them fix it first?
It's the same for me.
Well-
More for the people
... again,
it's sort of, can you just give your talk without the slides at some point?
Well, my digital twin voted, so I'm not sure.
So you don't see your slide on the computer?
On the computer. Yes.
It's fine on the computer. It's fine here.
No, but can I see my slide?
I see your... Yes.
No, but I can see them there.
You're fine here. Yes.
Oh, then it's okay.
Yes. It's the audience that has to understand that the
online audience is actually having a better experience at this point.
But even with the slides, they won't understand what I'm saying.
Ah. That's up to you.
All right. So for those of you who are interested in the technical solution, which
I didn't quite follow, but everybody noticed that the PDF worked fine,
if you ever have to solve this. And something about the hertz or something.
I'm not sure.
Yeah, I'm trying to find-
Yeah
... something.
So sharing a PDF worked fine, but not... Yeah.
I don't know.
But he said he could try in about a minute.
I'm sorry you had that.
Ah, it's okay.
I'm sorry. Oh, can you put your phone on? Thanks.
So Javier asked me too, for all the speakers when we are done, if we can
all join quickly on the stage to take a picture for this session before we
go to the next thing. That would be
thankful.
That's not me. No, that's the previous.
Okay.
That's not me.
Okay. Do you want me to start you?
No, but that's not mine.
Yep. This is not yours.
No.
Let's see here.
Display.
This is you.
That's...
Yes. Okay. Ready?
Yes.
All right.
Okay.
So sorry to keep you from your coffee
break. So I will try to be fast.
So as some of you may know, since April, I started to work on a
big new EU project called EU
AI Factories, and there I happen to have
work on the deliverables about the AI needs of different
scientific
communities, and also about their needs in
terms of trustworthy AI, where I
learned a lot of new things. And so I thought it would be
interesting to share a bit what I learned about this
topic here at TED Week. So it will be less
about
data or data quality, but some reflections on
AI needs and what trustworthy AI
actually means.
So back in the days, end of '90s, does anyone
remember the SETI program and SETI at Home,
which was searching
signs for extraterrestrial life with radio
frequencies? But at that time, the data was so
overwhelming and to search that, that in the US, I
think in California, Berkeley, they decided to use
the compute
power of all our personal devices,
and they wanted everyone to happily share their room
and their computers
to help using
the compute available everywhere,
to help them go through this data and see if we can find little
green aliens communicating with us.
So do you think this would still work now?
Probably not, because for once, the volume of data and
compute has become so high that it wouldn't be probably
feasible anymore. But people would also not, because of
fear of cyberattacks or stealing their data, being happy to
just serve their personal computer
power or space for third parties.
And also, we all want
more trustworthy environments, and we also seek for
more autonomy
on this side.
So this led that there is
massive investment in huge data centers,
but that somehow work on their continent.
I used here figures I found from the US, EU, and
China. So you can find in
billions of euro how much they invest,
and it's a sort of almost competition who is investing the
more billions in huge data centers to offer
GPUs and compute powers. But actually
finding surveys where they actually analyze what are the
actual needs of the community and why you want to give so much
AI compute power, that is sometimes more difficult to
find. It's really, "Oh,
I
put more billions of euro than Europe in the
US," and so on, and it's really becoming like a game
almost, and a competition.
And now you could think, if you go back to my first slide with SETI,
wow, how much
interesting international science collaboration could
this make if all these billions are invested and we can
all
together use this huge
compute power to do AI, to do better science, and more
global
research? But if you look at it in detail, for example,
in the EU, they have now made these certificates that are called
sovereignty levels from zero to four, and depending
on which data you use, especially sensitive data,
personal data, military data, whatever, they
require the C level four, where, for example,
nothing, not even the microchips, the components, the software,
should come from anywhere else than developed in the EU.
Now, this is totally utopic when you ask them,
even sovereign EU servers have always
components that come outside Europe
for the time being. So for the moment, this is really wishful thinking.
And of course, trustworthy AI can be seen as very
positively if you look at the requirements for ethics
being data legally applied, minimizing risk, and so on.
But we also identify that they go over the top,
and sometimes are really barriers to do science.
So they said they can have very fantastic datasets where they could have
nice results, but then they are blocked because of all the
trustworthy AI requirements, and it makes
doing research more and more difficult, and sometimes not
even knowing if you are allowed to use the data or not.
And I also participated to an
UNESCO meeting where they want on AI
infrastructure dependency or compute dependency,
where countries who don't have the means to have their own
data centers and compute facility become
completely dependent from the bigger countries who can
offer AI providers,
which can also be sometimes a bit unfair and
unequal.
There is also,
when I visited different AI centers, there is
again this competition, who can offer the most
GPUs per year? So I looked up a few
figures, let alone Amazon claims that they can
give 2.5 million GPUs in '25,
and if you look all the other US providers, it's really huge numbers.
In Europe, they hope to
arrive to 1.2 million GPUs by 2030.
And for China, the figures were not always available, but they
found in their studies that they want to reach
1.6 million GPUs by '29.
And
now looking at biodiversity data,
we reflect a bit when we assessed the needs in the
project I'm working for the biodiversity information community.
And indeed, if you look at the GBIF data that are there now,
3.8 billions.
Of course, if you ask global questions like the whole
world species distribution,
assessing biodiversity loss at continental or planetary
level, if you want to do large monitoring
analysis really at global level, and if you add all the
climate change, habitat loss, environmental parameter that
influence this distribution, yes, you can come at big
numbers. Also in projects like Disco and others
where we are not sure how many billions of specimens
are out there. They say 10% are digitized, but
imagine we could digitize everything, both
imaging and
also the data. So I ask ChatGPT as it is
AI, imagine we have 3 billions 2D image
specimen with all the data, how much compute would we
need to analyze this? So in storage, they
said up to 500 petabytes, and
depending, I put here the usual things we are doing in
AI and ChatGPT, based on the information they
could find, analyzed that we could need
almost one million to 50 million GPUs
hours to answer the questions if we had 3
billions images and all the associated
information complete.
But now coming back to reality, most of the time
when I discussed with researchers that are using AI, so for example, here
are the outputs from the Tetris project from the
cascading grant. So they made very nice AI
application using digital images of
snails from the Kerguelen Islands or AI
recognition by sound of grasshoppers.
You can find, if you go to the links, these nice examples.
And I also interviewed many researchers and they all said,
"Yeah, I do that in the evening or per night on my laptop, and
I never use these big compute centers.
I really don't need this." And I was also at a meeting where there was an
invited speaker from Spain, Gustavo
Candela, when I asked him this question, he said, "No, actually,
my goal is really to develop algorithm where every researcher
on his own laptop can do this training model and achieve
something. And I purposely try to have algorithm
and models where I don't need these big IE
data centers," because he estimate that it has also an
impact on the environment and so on, and that it's not good to use.
Now, I would nuance that because if some of you saw my presentation of
Green AI two years ago in Okinawa, other reports
showed that actually it's our laptops, personal
devices,
phones, and so on that have actually, for the moment, the
biggest environmental impact, and that is still much
higher than the impact of the big
computer centers. But if they continue to invest, like I show,
it can become equal and even sometimes more than our
personal devices in future.
So
what I also discussed with many of researchers is actually what takes the
most of time to them is the cleaning of the data and making the
data AI ready, finding the data, compiling them
so that they become good and meaningful for their AI
applications, and then transferring them to the server.
If it is a huge data set which will do the compute is what takes the most
of time. But the compute time as such, if the
algorithm is well-defined, doesn't take that much time.
And that's why also in this AI factory
project, they have the goal to have what they call thematic data
labs.
For the moment, there's climate change and environment, but they also discuss to
have other research domains. And I really fight here to have also
biodiversity data, which could be a good example because they look for
data that are not much influenced by legal aspects
and blocking. And biodiversity data is really one
that is the more open. So that could be used as a good
example. And the goal of these data labs, it's really to work on the
data so that they can be
used directly in AI readiness. And I think TDWG
could play a big role here because it asks a
lot of standardization. And
being able to retrieve the data and produce them directly by
AI in TDWG standards could be interesting
research approaches.
Oops.
And here just a word on
Green AI. Is it myth or reality? I looked
up some figures. So you can see currently,
25 figures. What is needed as
electricity, impact on CO2, water, and so on.
It's massive, and they estimate that it will still grow
threefolds.
And actually, I visited several AI center where
they really try to use, for example, agreements with logging
companies to do use pellets for the
heating system, and they have closed circuits with water that is
recycled so that they use as less as possible
water from the nature or reject it to reduce the
usage of water. But just when I was happy to
present that, a new study came out just this September
that actually this cooling
water system that circles, they use forever chemicals, the
PFAS, that are released in the atmosphere and the
soil.
And so on one hand, they protect the environment,
but unfortunately, they found out that they generate
chemicals that pollute our drinking water and that was recently
proven to be very bad for our health and can create
cancer. So what is a good solution?
It's really difficult to say.
So as a conclusion, I would like to thank all these different projects that
were an initiative, and of course, the colleagues working for them
that were very inspirational for me to learn a lot and to
prepare this presentation.
And as take home message, I would say think twice
before you use AI and ChatGPT and use
mitigation. If the results are to
protect nature and will make understand the
species better, to better understand them like we do for climate change,
maybe yes. But if it's to looking cats dancing somewhere,
maybe don't do it. And funny enough, I ask
sometimes researchers to ChatGPT, and he told
me, "No, this doesn't exist." And I type the word in
Google, and I find directly the resources.
And then I said to ChatGPT, "But how can you tell me this doesn't
exist? I just typed one word in Google, and I found it."
And funny enough, ChatGPT answered me, "But there are certain
searches where it's better you still use Google and a simple search than
me because they are still better than me.
So you have to choose wisely." And so I asked ChatGPT, "Tell me,
when should I use AI and when should I still old-fashioned use
Google?" And he also confirmed that using Google while
still also having an impact has less environmental
impact than using a robot or whatever.
So that's my conclusion. I don't have the solution
either, but I thought it was interesting to
reflect for this last talk about the impact of AI and what
responsible AI actually mean, and that we
can reflect all together how to
make the best out of it without, of course, dismissing that it's
a fantastic tool to have really nice results, as we saw in all
the previous presentations.
Thank you for that, Pat. Much appreciated.
I think now,
Siobhan, Sabina, we're in the interest of time, they've asked us to do a photo
for all the speakers. And then-
Discussion at 4:00
... discussion is, yeah, at 4:00 in here. So if you want to come back.
It's Balder.
Sorry, my mistake. Balder. B-A-L-D-E-R. Yes, in Balder.
If you want to pick up on this conversation and follow threads that were
interesting to you.
Thank you very much.
And thank you.
This
session called Bots, Bits and Biodiversity.
Firstly, I just want to introduce myself and my other moderators.
So my name's Jack Hollister, and we've got Steen down there, and we
have Haris here. We are all from the Natural History Museum in London.
And we wanted to make this session as a place
for people to make or to show off things
they're making, things they're doing with data, ways that they're
using large language models. Just nice little projects.
But this is a flash talk, so we have an hour and we need to get through
nine talks with a maximum of five minutes each.
So we're not going to do any questions, and we'll do questions at the end if we
manage to actually get through every one in time.
So to start with, I'm going to... Oh, God.
Oh, no.
So.
Sorry, guys.
Excellent. So first up on the talks is my talk, it's called
Agentic AI Systems for Specimen Interaction and Camera-based
Observations.
So again, this is just me. So I work for the Natural History Museum, but I'm also
part of Disco UK.
So throughout my science career, I've been obsessed with two things.
Firstly, this is how AI interprets biological specimens.
So, how does it view images and videos?
Can it pick out morphological features?
And I'm also quite obsessed with hosting AI locally.
So, that's running all your models on your own
computers.
And so for this project, I wanted to see whether I could get a vision language
model to be able to automatically pick out features, like morphological
features, with very little guidance.
And I wanted to see if
we could then
put this into a graph network and then have it in so you can interact with it.
So I wanted to ask whether we could get the vision language model
to
see if it could pick out things like wings.
If it can count the amount of wings, see if it can pick out legs, see if it can
count the amount of legs, to see if it can say what color something is,
to see if a specimen has any damage.
So to run this locally,
I've been working with Dell and they gave me access to some of their new
compute. So this little computer's called the GB10, goes for about
7,000 pounds, but you can fit very nice big local
language models on there. So you can fit up to 200 billion parameter models on one.
You can cluster two together to get 400 billion parameter models.
So they're very big models.
Vision language models are a bit beefier, so
for this particular project, the biggest one I could work with was a 32
billion parameter model.
But I didn't fine-tune it, I used
just straight
off the shelf, as it's called. So I just took it straight as is and worked with it.
I did have to create a prompt and a harness for it.
So this tells the model what it can do and also shows what it
can work with, so what images and stuff it can work with.
So to do this, I 3D printed this scanner.
So I didn't design this. I did make some edits.
You can make your own one following this link.
But what it does, it spins an image around 360 degrees and
rotates the camera about 150 degrees, and it takes photos constantly.
And these are some other parts I added.
So there's my GB10 cluster, and it also runs on a Raspberry
Pi to help run the motors to spin the specimen around.
I also created some software to work with this.
So these are typically all the images that could be taken on this one device.
You can take more images. I just set it to 40 because I thought it was a nice
number.
And then the magic happens. This is when you literally ask the vision language
model, "What can you see?" Obviously, there's a lot of predefined rules,
but it's as simple as, "Show me what you can see."
And this is what it does. It literally shows you how
many features it can see. So it can physically count and put bounding
boxes around the wings, around the antennae.
It can count all the legs. It can count a pin if that's what you're
after. And there's lots of more different features.
It
can just see, basically. It can interpret all these features
with very little
user input from us. And this one, I thought, was very important because it was able
to tell that this specimen was damaged.
If you're working with large natural history collections,
being able to quickly verify if a specimen is damaged or not is
very advantageous.
And
the other part of the software, I put all these features into a graph network,
and I can show you this on my laptop after the session.
But basically, you can
ask what features and if you can see them at any point of the country.
You can use these type of graph networks and add to them and
really visualize the data that you are creating.
I think that's very important for us.
And so yes, to conclude, I think vision language models are
very good at understanding morphology, and I think that's very important for the
field of taxonomy.
And
that's basically it. Thank you very much, guys.
Well done.
There you go.
I don't need that. All right.
We might have just kicked off one minute too early.
There's loads of people coming in as Jack was speaking.
We'll move on, and I would like to introduce...
Just going to get this right.
Phoebe Santos. Fantastic. So as we've said, no
questions in between. We'll just get through the talks.
Keep your questions in your mind,
and we will then take them as soon as we're done if we have time.
Now, the biggest problem is
where's the mouse?
Because I need to change- It's in the extended desktop.
Slide left. Slide left.
Everybody has this problem.
Other left.
Other left. That left. This is going to turn into the Macarena.
You need to-
There you go.
Yeah, that one.
Push on. That one. And where's the mouse?
Here.
It's coming.
It's coming. There you go. The other left, and then it's number two,
right?
And present.
There you go. Welcome. Have fun.
Thanks.
Hi. Hi, everyone. So my name is Phoebe Santos, and I'm going to be talking a bit
today about my master's thesis project, which I did with the Natural History Museum
of London, the Zoological Society of London, and UCL, and we looked
at using large language models for the transcription and information
extraction of ecological data from historical archives.
So to start off with, who can read this?
Or rather, who finds it easy to read?
I certainly find it difficult, and as a researcher trying to sort through hundreds
or thousands of documents like this to explore a single question or find
one piece of information can be extraordinarily time-consuming.
And digitizing and transcribing these records can make them far more searchable
and machine-readable and making them more accessible.
This is the basic premise of our research, looking at how large language models can
be used in an automated way to transcribe handwritten historical records.
So what we wanted to do was build on existing research showing that large language
models can be useful for transcription, but ask whether these approaches can
generalize beyond a single collection.
So a lot of the previous work focuses on developing an approach for a particular
dataset, meaning that the prompts and examples can be tailored to that collection.
We wanted to see whether a single approach could handle different types of
historical records, including differences in handwriting, format, and structure.
Structure became particularly important because we found early on that the models
often struggled to reproduce how information was formatted on the page, and
structure isn't just visual. We, as humans, use it to understand a document.
Paragraphs group ideas, marginal notes add context, and the flow of information on
a page shows how all of the information relates to one another.
So in my thesis, we had two main research questions, the first of which was how
well do our two chosen multimodal LLMs transcribe different types of
historical records?
And the second was whether
prompting strategy as well as
example specificity affect model performance.
And throughout that, looking at whether the models can
preserve the structure within the resulting transcription.
So we had two datasets. One was sourced from the British Library and contained
18th to 19th century handwritten English language records from the
British Colonial Office in India, and the other was from the Natural History Museum
in London and contained handwritten table records relating to their mammal
osteology records.
We used two multimodal LLMs. First was Claude Sonnet 5 with closed weights,
and the second was Qwen 2.5 Vision-Language 32B, which has open weights,
but neither model was altered in any way beyond setting temperature to 0.7.
Both models were given the same user prompt and schema setup, along with
the system prompt and the corresponding document images for transcription.
This is the final zero-shot prompt that we ended up with.
Along with its general transcription task, the model is also told as a
subtask to classify each page into one of three categories based on the
page's structure. We defined those categories and chose them prior.
Those were text, mixed, and table.
And then based off of that classification, the model was given additional
transcription instructions intended to encode the structure within the
resulting transcription.
We then tested zero, one, and few-shot prompting, as well as testing whether giving
the model examples that were dataset specific, so examples that were sourced and
resembled the structure of the dataset that they were transcribing, if that would
have an additional effect on transcription performance.
For our first aim of how well did the models actually transcribe, both models
performed very well overall for records classified as text.
Claude did perform significantly better, but that absolute gap in error difference
was rather small.
However, for the more structured records, such as those in the Natural History
Museum dataset, the difference between the two models was much more pronounced.
So Claude, again, performed significantly better with these more structured
records, while Qwen struggled with creating accurate transcriptions of these
very highly structured records.
For our second aim of how does prompting strategy and example specificity affect
performance, we found that for Claude, again, its performance was very
consistent across all prompting strategies as well as example specificity,
regardless of the dataset and regardless of the structure on the page.
For Qwen, its performance was similarly consistent across prompts for records
classified as text. But on the NHM dataset, where all records were much more
structured, we saw a more distinct effect.
So Qwen's performance improved as it received more examples, and its
performance got an additional boost when those examples were dataset specific.
Overall, this poses LLMs as a viable and accessible tool for transcribing
handwritten historical records, with both tested models performing very well on
unseen, structurally variable data without any prior fine-tuning.
The cost we recorded as well while using Claude, the closed weight model, also
showed LLM-based transcription as a potentially more affordable option for
institutions than existing commercial transcription services.
It's notable, though, that we only included English language records,
and we didn't test any other structures beyond the English convention of writing
from left to right.
Despite these limitations, LLM-based transcription could help bring large
collections of difficult-to-access historical records into use,
while retaining human judgment over what information and structure should be
preserved, and then how those resulting transcriptions should then be used.
I'm here for the whole conference. Please ask me any questions. Thank you.
Well done.
This is lightning talks, by the way. It's in the title.
I think we are missing Andrew.
Is Andrew in the room?
Okay. So we're going to jump to Christian.
And just find your talk.
Adujon, right?
Yeah.
Yes. I'm trying to find-
Yes.
Let's get you up there.
That's yours, right?
Yes.
Fantastic.
Hello.
I'm Christian from Estonia.
And I'm
talking about digitizing some
very old historical or very long-lasted
data collection about
gulls, common gulls.
Little introduction to where Estonia is and where
are the data gathered. It's
one small single
islet in western part of Estonia, and you saw
gulls there.
So
the project started already in '60s, and
almost 60 years the
breeding data has been collected there, along with
several other experiments. But all the history
of the gulls breeding there has been
stored and is on this kind of
small
catalog cards.
The methodology hasn't changed much
during this period, but that enables
to digitize the cards in a
similar manner.
The cards consist of
distinct parts, header part with the card code,
some ringing data, and each year when the
individual bird was observed, the
data of its nest
was recorded and later stored on these cards.
As you see, the cards also contain lots of handwritten
notes on
recoveries, if the bird was found elsewhere.
So
the cards have been scanned, and
then
I developed a prompt to read them.
That's a sample part of the prompt that describes the cards
that are quite similar.
And
then we program the system to submit
the card images simultaneously to
several publicly available
LLMs.
Then
after getting answers that were
in a testing phase,
the answers
were
presented in our application UI
as
if they were
similar by all
models. There was no differences.
They were presented One character or number,
but if there were differences, a human reviewer had
to
decide which
is correct. So in this way, we tested and
obtained a ground truth
database, and then benchmarked
much more models on this ground truth
to find out which models
of these publicly available models are best for
making the big batch run. So the
results were that actually Gemini
models by Google were the best.
And,
well, European Mistral was one of the
lowest, unfortunately.
We just spent
about $50
for 3,000 decodings
for benchmarkings.
The system also calculated
the effectiveness
of different models on different parts of the card.
And, well, next is we can
analyze the data,
see the
confusion points that is also reported by the application,
and then run it on all about 9,000 cards.
And then the data will be
stored in PlutoF database and
later published in GBIF.
Okay, thank you.
Fantastic. Thank you. You guys are all on time.
I love the fact that we mentioned so many models and what they're good at and what
they're bad at. Would love to see across the
whole conference what people have said
over these models.
Next up is Emma Granqvist, and I will quickly
see if I can make this work again.
You have your presenter.
Great. Thank you. Does this work?
Should work, yes.
Yeah.
So hi. Now for something slightly different.
I'm Emma. I'm the director of SBDI.
So that's the National Biodiversity Data Infrastructure in Sweden, and I'm
a researcher in a research program called
Finance to Revive Biodiversity. That's what I'll be talking about today,
and also mainly about future work, actually.
So hands up, how many have seen this image before?
Yeah, some. Okay. So these are the planetary
boundaries as a concept coming out of Stockholm Resilience Centre, showing
the safe operating space for the planet.
And as you can see, seven out of these nine limits are already
orange or deep in the orange. So the current situation is not
sustainable.
This is, of course, not really news, but I like this way of
illustrating where we're at
and also
where we should be going. Right? So in recent years, more and more focus has
also moved towards the finance sector.
What does the financial system have for us in terms of unsustainable
practices that cause much more finance and investments
to flow into
activities that harm biodiversity rather than the opposite?
So FinBio connects the economic financial system and
biodiversity. It's an interdisciplinary program and wants to help shift this
balance, of course.
But to do that, you do need solid methods to measure
biodiversity.
So how is biodiversity measured today?
I say measured because it's really usually not in the
financial world. So currently what is done when they do want
to assess state is what we call this top-down
approach. They work with global predictive models or with
proxies to somehow assess what their impact is or what the state
at their site is.
And we've been arguing that we do need, and that is fully
possible to have more a bottom-up approach with more locally connected
data, such as eDNA data.
So not to replace one with the other, but we do need way more of
this bottom-up approach.
So then we wanted to look specifically a little bit more at the risks
of what is being done currently. What's the risk of assessing
without any local data?
So what we've done recently is to combine
a very high-quality biodiversity data set.
That's arthropod eDNA survey data from both Sweden and
Madagascar
over a whole year. It's bulk insect samples.
And then we combine those with environmental
covariates and train the machine learning model on that and predict
five essential biodiversity variables or summary measures you could say,
to sites either than evaluating either within site
or at new sites. So evaluating how well this machine learning
model has learned to learn the patterns and
predict the state. And the key conclusions, which I will
have to be very brief here, but please have a look at the paper if you're
interested, is obviously that, as one would expect,
predictive performance drops heavily at sites where you have
absolutely no local data.
And- The consequence of this, which we also show, is that if you do
try to go into decision-making based on such a model,
even though this model has really great biodiversity data
underlying it, which is really not the case usually in these settings,
you will have a lot of mistakes in your decisions.
And we exemplified that with site rankings, which is used either in
conservation or indeed it's in project development, which site should be
protected, which should be exploited.
And you just get it wrong to a large extent.
So then what? We have
institutions mainly using these global models, but we've shown that
there are high errors in this. So what we propose then is a
biodiversity data hierarchy with quality scores,
and that's modeled on carbon accounting standards, so you link this to the
reporting framework, which we think is really key.
So the idea is that the data and the models underlying
the assessments would really be placed into these tiers, and this
is just a sketch. This is what we'll be refining in the upcoming
years. So phase two of this program starts in January.
But basically right here at TadWig, we're usually in the top already, right?
We're talking about observations, and that the sessions here when we talk about
data quality is usually about correcting observations, right?
But I'm really talking about mainly data quality as in
how informative is it for a given decision.
So yeah, that's
all from me. And if you're interested, do come and talk to me or ask questions.
Thank you.
Fantastic.
Thank you so much.
You guys all writing questions down?
I hope.
Su-Len?
Fantastic.
Let's see.
I've got to get my mouse. Where's my mouse? There.
The other left, right? Jesus Christ.
This one? Yes.
Away you go.
Okay. Yeah. Hello, everyone. My name is Su-Len.
I am a software developer at Naturalist Biodiversity Center, and I'm really
excited to talk to you about a project I work on called Disco, the
Distributed System of Scientific Collections.
Disco is a lot of things, but I only have five minutes.
So,
for the point of this talk, Disco is an in-development research
infrastructure for natural history collections data.
The idea is to bring together natural history collections
data from across institutions to have a single platform for
community curation.
So digitizing the collections, it's important.
Again, five minutes, so I'm going to assume everyone's on the same page here.
And we have been making very good progress as a community
digitizing the collections. However, it is getting difficult to scale
up. Sometimes the lower hanging fruit has been immediately
targeted, and now we're stuck with stuff that is a little harder to
digitize.
Institutions are working independently from one another.
There's less opportunity for collaboration, and there's a lot
of manual tasks that are just begging to be automated.
So what we get
is a system where different institutions are developing
more or less the same thing. And sometimes that's a question of people not
being aware of what the other institutions are doing, and sometimes it's a question
of everyone's data is so radically different from one another
that to bring one system, one digital
service to another institution would require so much time
to rework.
And so that's sort of where Disco comes in.
So Disco, this research infrastructure,
we've brought a bunch of data from different institutions
under the same structure. And so
digital services that aid and augment the data, if they are
adapted to Disco, can all of a sudden be brought into any
institution that is a partner of Disco.
We call these services machine annotation services.
And these are a few of our pilot machine annotation
services that we have available on our sandbox environment.
So we have... Oh, that is so big.
So,
we have a plant organ detection service using Leaf Machine.
We can link to other infrastructures, GBIF, ENA,
Geocase. We use GeoPic, which is developed by GBIF,
to georeference specimens. And most excitingly, we have a
label transcription tool, so we use Votervision to read labels
and then transcribe that into Darwin Core.
And what you'll notice, all of these things in bold, we don't develop them.
We've just adapted them to the infrastructure.
And now, we've talked a little bit about these services in Disco
for a couple of TadWigs now. But what's exciting is that we
finally have a service that allows us to do this at scale.
So instead of scheduling one of these services on each specimen
one at a time, what we can support now is running these over an
entire dataset immediately.
And so that sort of leads to this digitizing
pipeline that we are working towards.
So the idea is a digitalization project happening at an institution
will result in
photographs of specimens being taken.
And then those photographs, just the photographs, can be ingested into Disco, and
then all of these various services can be run over it immediately.
And at the same time,
remote experts, human experts, can annotate maybe the
taxonomy or do any sort of corrections
And then once those contributions have been verified, that
data can be sent back to the institution.
And that last part is still in development.
We have an export, but this is the goal that we're working towards.
And if you want to know how annotations are accepted, you can go see my
colleague Wouter's talk. That was this morning, so you can go back in time.
So, if this sounds interesting, I've heard a lot of interesting projects
already at this conference. If you have a service that you would be interested in
trying out connecting to Disco, we have a hackathon, a virtual hackathon
next month. You can sign up, and then we can work together and collaborate.
In terms of other steps, we are working on becoming a legal entity
called AERIC. Once we become a legal entity, we can make service level
agreements and bring these services to production.
But that's where we're at, and I hope we can connect. Thank you for your time.
Nice.
Come on.
Fantastic. Ariana's going to join us next.
Thank you.
Okay. Awesome. Can you guys hear me? Okay, excellent.
So I am here to talk about this project that we were
doing for about a year. Well, we were talking for about a year, and then we
met in person for two weeks, and we had one week to build something.
And now I have five minutes to talk about that. So here I am.
So this is a talk by myself and my colleagues, Henrik Omsenhaug Tveit and
Carl Thunes from NIBIO, who are over there.
So I'm pointing them out to embarrass them.
Okay,
I'll go fast. So introduction. So I am Ariana Salili James
from the Natural History Museum in the UK, and my colleagues are from NIBIO.
So that's the Norwegian Institute of Bioeconomy Research.
I still have to read it because I don't remember. Sorry about that.
And there we have a large collection of specimens, a
lot of insects. Over 200,000 pinned insects alone.
Yeah, 200,000 pinned insects in the entomology collection.
And the idea is, what can we do to help digitize these specimens?
And after we've done that, what else can AI help with?
For example, this could be for
doing classification on taxa. It can relate to agricultural
services in the future as well, whether it's pest management and things like that,
or for outreach related reasons as well. So who are we?
Again, we're a cross-institutional team.
I should say one other core member was Flora Todd.
She should have been here, but her PhD thesis is due in one week.
So can everyone wish Flora good luck, please? She can do it. You can do it, Flora.
Okay, so this was the team that we've got, and this
started about a year ago, where we had a year to build something.
So what was the plan? The plan was to develop a prototype digitization
setup. Then the next week, we were going to deal with the photography of the
specimens. Not all specimens, obviously, as much as we can do in a week,
focusing on Coleoptera as well, which are bark beetles.
And then from there, how can we use AI to develop a species identification tool?
And also, can we use the photographs or videos that we took for 3D
reconstruction?
So this was what happened in the week. So we had one week.
So our first thing is, let's just go around all the rooms and see what we could
find. We're a team that loves recycling, so if you've got bits and pieces
lying around, we can build something for you guys.
So we went around, we saw a few things, one example being the BugDome
boxes. I don't know if anyone here is familiar with BugDome, but we had a few
BugDome boxes lying around, so we took one of those boxes.
We then did a lot of cutting of foam and plastics and zip-tying
everything together, buying some really cheap lights, and then borrowing two
cameras from a friendly colleague, and we also brought in a rotating
platform as well. So this was inspired, if you've heard of ALICE
from the Natural History Museum, this was inspired by the ALICE setup, so shout out
to Stine for that.
But of course, we didn't have six cameras lying around, so we only had two cameras
to borrow. So that's why we decided on getting a rotating platform as well.
So we put all of this together in about one week, so
very, very rough. We then did some tests on some specimens,
doing some size tests, tests on different camera setups, camera
settings, and then we did some photography.
So we took photographs from different angles, so with the
rotating platform moving, and we then took a 360 video.
What we found was when we were doing the photographs, we can get a very clear view
of the specimen. But when we were doing the video, the views of the labels were
amazing. And because our collection was small enough, we were
fine with collecting that video data, and the idea being that this will, in the
future, lead to some automatic label extraction reading.
So the video will not be kept throughout the entire time,
collecting all that storage space.
So the video will be a more temporary thing here.
So that's kind of-- I will talk about that more. Okay.
So where did that lead us to? So next step was doing some species
classification. So this was led by Flora mainly working on
this. So we had two ideas, really. One was, can
we develop a tool, so based on other AI tools out there,
to focus on Coleoptera? Can we find out the genus and species
of different Coleoptera from images of digitized specimens?
So kind of creating a
robotic copy of Henrik here in case Henrik wasn't with us one day and he
wanted to identify something. And the other idea was, can we do this in the wild
as well? Because we have a lot of specimen images from the wild looking at bark
beetles. I should have said Coleoptera bark beetles.
Looking at bark beetles and also looking at the damage of the bark beetles, and
that's the key part. That's what we're trying to focus on and why it's important
for research happening at NIBIO.
So Flora worked on collecting data from GBIF.
She developed an AI-- Well, we developed an AI tool to first filter
that data because it wasn't all Coleoptera related.
Some of them were misclassified. And then using the photographs
taken from NIBIO, as well as photographs taken from the Natural History
Museum in the UK. So the photo on the right
Sorry, "you guys" is right. I'm getting confused.
But the one on the end, that's from the Natural History Museum in the UK.
So we took some photos of that, and then we trained a YOLOv511
model to do some classification with us.
So I'm not going to
have some time talking about the results, but the results were pretty good.
On the left, you'll see the genus-level classification, and then on top of that, we
then did a species-level classification.
We then used the videos to do a 3D classification tool as well.
So this was by Yung Sun, so using tools like ColMap
and other machine learning-related tools to create a 3D
mesh of the insect. The purpose for this being for outreach reasons.
So then I came back last week, and we developed a more
refined version of our box.
And we're now also working on creating the
software to capture all of these. So we now have three
cameras. We're developing an in-house software.
So you press one button, and it's all done, again, using the automated platform.
And then we're linking that to label extraction software on top of that.
So if you guys want to help us, please, we're trying to find a name.
So if you have name suggestions for our new box, that's the new one over there.
Please come to us, me, Henrik, or Carl, and we'll be very thankful for that.
Okay. I didn't go too over, sorry.
I will say for some foam and some cheap lights, good images.
Thank you.
All right. Andrew. Is Andrew here?
We missed Andrew earlier. Nope.
In that case,
we will be moving over to the last two virtual talks,
and then we can
have some discussions.
I think we might have to list up the titles of
the talks.
Let's see if I can get this.
Oh.
And...
One of our greatest challenges is imaging specimens and generating digital data
at a scale...
Can we get some sound?
No?
12 million are insects.
One of our greatest challenges is imaging specimens and generating digital data
at a scale that is both efficient and sustainable.
The Commonwealth Scientific agency, CSIRO, manages the natural research collections
of Australia. This includes around 50 million-
Mm
... specimens, and of these, we estimate 12 million are insects.
One of our greatest challenges is imaging specimens and generating digital data
at a scale that is both efficient and sustainable.
So today, I'll briefly show you how we are bringing-
And we're going to try here. Just give me a second
... together imaging, AI, and robotics, and its workflows-
To full volume now
... for
high-throughput
digitisation of our insect collection.
PAROS brings together imaging, AI, and robotics, robotics, and workflow automation-
Sure. Well, yeah, absolutely.
Our
new PAROS imaging system-
Oops. Again
... can position and angle
the specimens and their labels without-
Trying to find my mouse. There we go.
Let's stop that one
... manual intervention. And this is reducing imaging times from more than six
minutes to around 30 seconds per specimen.
Next, our images are automatically processed.
Hello. My name is Andrew Jones, and I'm a curator with the Tulane
University Biodiversity Research Institute at Tulane University
in New Orleans, Louisiana.
Is that better?
Thank you for coming to my presentation on-
... semantic governance and knowledge organization in AI-augmented
biodiversity infrastructures.
It's Andrew's.
Yeah, so-
Artificial intelligence is increasingly becoming part of the infrastructure we use-
We'll wait
... to organize and understand biodiversity data.
Traditionally, biodiversity collections have depended on structured systems,
taxonomic classifications, controlled vocabularies,
cataloging standards, and carefully documented metadata.
But now we're introducing systems that work probabilistically.
Large language models can generate annotations, classifications,
descriptions, and links between datasets, often at a scale that would be
difficult for humans to achieve manually.
And that creates an interesting problem for large datasets like ours.
The question is no longer simply, can AI help us organize
biodiversity information? It becomes, how do we
govern the meaning that AI is creating?
There is a tremendous opportunity here.
AI can help enrich existing biodiversity records by generating or
suggesting metadata, identifying relationship between records, and
making collections easier to search and discover.
For example,
the Tulane University Biodiversity Research Institute Natural History Collection
contains millions of specimen records.
Much of the specimen information already exists, but it can be difficult to
connect that information that was created at different times by different
institutions or using different terminology.
AI can help identify those connections.
It can recognize that different descriptions refer to similar concepts.
It can suggest taxonomic relationships, extract information from
legacy records, or help researchers discover specimens that may
not find otherwise. In other words, AI has the
potential to act as a layer between biodiversity collections and the people trying
to use them. But that layer introduces a fundamental distinction.
AI can generate an answer without necessarily generating an
agreed-upon meaning, and that's where the challenge begins.
The first challenge is semantic ambiguity.
An AI system might produce an annotation that sounds perfectly reasonable to a
human reader but does not correspond cleanly to an existing biodiversity
concept or controlled vocabulary.
The second challenge is consistency.
Two AI systems, or even the same system at different times,
may describe the same specimen differently.
Probabilistic systems don't necessarily reproduce the consistency that we
expect from traditional cataloging systems.
Then there's provenance. If an AI-generated annotation enters a
biodiversity repository, we need to know where that information came
from. Was it extracted from the original specimen record?
Was it inferred by a model? Was it reviewed by a
curator? Was it subsequently modified?
And finally, there's institutional trust.
A biodiversity repository isn't simply a database.
It is a record of scientific knowledge.
When AI becomes involved in creating or transforming that knowledge,
institutions need to be able to understand what the system did and
why.
So the problem isn't necessarily that AI is unreliable.
The problem is that AI-generated knowledge can be difficult to interpret, trace,
and govern.
This brings us to knowledge organization.
Biodiversity informatics already has an important advantage.
Decades of work have gone into developing shared standards and semantic
frameworks.
Standards like controlled vocabularies, taxonomic authorities, and
established cataloging practices give us a common language for describing
biodiversity.
These systems provide something that generative AI does not automatically
provide: shared semantic commitments.
So rather than treating AI as a replacement for these systems, we can think about
AI as operating within them. An AI system might suggest
a classification or generate metadata, but the output can then be
mapped to established vocabularies, checking its community standards,
and accompanied by information about its provenance.
This suggests a model of AI-assisted curation rather than
AI-directed curation. That distinction is important.
The goal isn't to prevent machines from generating knowledge.
It's to make sure that machine-generated knowledge remains understandable and
accountable within the communities that maintain biodiversity infrastructure.
That means governance has to become part of the technical architecture.
We need to know not only what an AI system produced, but also
which vocabulary it used, what source information it relied
upon, what transformations occurred, and whether a human
curator reviewed the result.
In that sense, semantic governance becomes a bridge between artificial intelligence
and existing knowledge organization practices.
So where do we go from here?
We see an opportunity for biodiversity informatics communities, and
particularly organizations like TADWIG, to establish shared
practices for AI-augmented infrastructure.
First, AI-generated information should be provenance-aware.
We should be able to distinguish original observations from machine-generated
annotations and subsequent human revisions.
Second, AI output should be semantically transparent.
Where possible, generated concepts should be connected to recognized
vocabularies, standards, and identifiers.
Third, these systems need to be interoperable.
AI shouldn't create another layer of isolated terminology that makes it harder
to connect collections. Instead, it should help strengthen connections
between existing systems.
And finally, governance needs to be community-driven.
The standards community that already understands biodiversity data should have a
role in defining how AI systems interact with those standards.
The larger point is that AI changes more than the way we
process biodiversity data. It changes who and what
is participating in the organization of knowledge.
If we can build systems where AI-generated knowledge is traceable,
semantically grounded, interoperable, and open to human oversight,
then AI can become a powerful extension of existing biodiversity
infrastructures rather than a competing knowledge system.
For TADWIG, that creates an opportunity to help define not simply
how biodiversity data are exchanged, but how
AI-generated biodiversity knowledge becomes trustworthy, understandable,
and shareable.
Please visit the Image Quality and AI Readiness Task Group page on the TADWIG
website to learn more about what our community is exploring. Thank you.
Hello, my name is Andrew Jones.
We found Andrew.
And I'm a curator with the Tulane University Biodiversity Research
Institute at Tulane.
Yeah.
All right. So we're going to try
Nicole again. Hopefully, we can get the sound up.
So let me just try that.
If Andrew is online and everybody else is virtual online, I do apologize for the
mix-up. I hope you're not shouting at us.
If you are, you can do it on the app and we will see it.
And of course, if you are asking questions to them, you'd have to do it through the
app if they're online.
Yeah.
No? Okay. We will keep trying.
No?
We're going to have to skip this talk, sorry.
Yeah, that's
fine.
Yeah.
Okay. Many apologies for that. We will-
Sorry
... skip that. Will it be available somewhere else?
We're going to have to ask her to re-record it because it's-
It's the speaker, and I could barely hear her.
So we're going to have to ask her to- Put microphone on the speaker.
But you can't really hear it even from the-
Yeah, but this microphone is better.
Okay. We
will jump to the last speaker,
who is
Jenna Kline,
and after that, we will have a brief-
Hello, everyone. My name is Jenna Kline, and I'm a post-doc at
MIT.
Today, I'll be giving a lightning talk on KaberTools, a tool
for automated
video-based animal behavioral monitoring.
KaberTools first started as the Kaber
datasets. Kaber stands for the Kenyan Animal
Behavior Recognition from drone videos.
This dataset was collected by myself and a wonderful team of
collaborators over about a month at Impala
Research Center in Laikipia, Kenya, in 2023.
We collected behavior videos of three species,
ended up with about 10 hours of footage, which was processed to
produce over 900 videos with annotated
behavior.
And as of this recording, has been downloaded about
200,000 times on Hugging Face.
Through the annotation process and subsequent data
analysis, we developed our KaberTools,
which is now a modular workflow for
video-based animal behavior monitoring.
Starting with video data collection from either drones or camera
traps, all the way through machine learning-based methods with manual
oversight to process the data through to
ecological analysis.
We provide tips and tricks for dealing with large video
datasets and three main stages of ML
processing,
which consists of three main tasks: detection,
tracking, and behavior annotation.
These computer vision tasks are all model-agnostic.
You can swap out custom behavior recognition models or custom
trackers and choose the degree of autonomy that
is most appropriate for your particular study
system.
And collaborators have used this tool for
camera trap-based and drone-based
studies of African wild dogs.
So a couple of the different ecological research questions KaberTools can
support. One is time budgets.
These tools are designed to extract ecological insight from videos at
scale.
We also provide scripts to automatically calculate behavior
transitions,
look at things like land use and differences in land use
across species,
and
even track individual identities and their characteristic
behavior patterns. In this case, this was used for the African wild
dog study.
And all of the scripts, data, and
preprint is available online. Please don't hesitate to reach out if you'd like to
use KaberTools. Thank you.
Hello, everyone. My name is Jenna Kline.
That was it. Those were the
talks.
Right on time, actually.
Some great little hardware,
large language models, OCR, deeper data.
I think it was great. Five minutes is a very short time. It's quite stressful.
As I promised, we should jump into some questions. I'm just going to stop this.
I do not actually have, and that is probably a lesson learned for next time if
we're doing this again, a list of all the talks with the titles.
If you can remember when you asked your question, maybe just mention which talk it
was from or context, and maybe the person who gave the talk can stand up and
answer.
Are there any questions or general questions for that matter?
You can ask questions to your own talk as well.
The team was very creative at building stuff-
It's Ariana here
... yes, out of
nothing, basically. So my question is,
how much does it cost, actually, to build one of
your sets?
Oh, we need another mic.
And one more question, so two questions.
And how fast it is to actually analyze
one specimen.
This sounds really close to me. Hello. Okay.
Thank you for the question. So we did actually calculate cost very recently, so
I'll do timing first, though. So with our previous iterations,
so not the one from last week, but the one from last year, it was about
20 seconds
for the digitization, and that was also because we were doing a manual
focus on the lateral view camera. So that's including putting it
down and photographing it. Was it 20? Am I right, guys?
Was it about 20 to 40 seconds?
But that's including the labels as well. We didn't take the labels off.
So that was taking the photographs of the specimen with the labels and also
doing the 360 video as well.
I think it might be closer to 20 to 40 seconds, potentially, actually.
Yeah, with everything included, including putting it in and out.
In terms of costings, the cameras were obviously the most
expensive part, but we had borrowed them.
When we bought a new one for it the other week, I think it cost
about
200,000 krona. Is that right?
Maybe a bit less. About 1,300, maybe about 1,000 pounds for
the camera, I would say. But the bits and pieces, they were very cheap.
So our LED lights were about maybe 15 pounds.
The rotating platform, again, was about 10 pounds.
We bought it very cheap. Some of it makes it more difficult in the future.
So for example, automating the rotating platform, if we spent
100 pounds, we could have bought a fancier version that could do that, but instead
we've had to use our time to
rotate that ourselves, for example. So we are doing it very cheaply.
To summarize,
so you don't have that great funding to actually
.
Yeah.
We were trying to do it as cheap as possible with recycled material.
Also, just to show institutions, if you have things lying around, and if you're
allowed to borrow someone's camera for two months,
this is what you can build, essentially.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
And Sue, we got a question for you.
Hi. Sorry, I forgot your name. I
have a quick question about the platform you are building.
Because from
theoretical perspective, it look great to
collect the data for different institution and build a
data integration platform.
Practically, how realistic is that those institution are
open to give you their data, and how do you handle data?
What is the,
how you say, the agreement? How do you
handle that on a practical visit? Are they really open?
First of all, thank you for the question.
We have a national node sort of structure.
So our
countries are members of DISCO, so they've already accepted, like, "Oh, we are
interested in this service. We have bought into DISCO."
The data that we ingest is all CC0 or CC
BY, so it's already open data.
And
sorry, there's another thing I wanted to add. Yeah.
It's open, and we have so far interest.
People are interested in having the data on the platform for additional
visibility, as well as this community curation that we're supporting.
Any other questions?
Oh, there's a couple. And then-
I'm just going to say, if there are questions for the Caber tools,
and all of that drone-based behavior monitoring, I'm happy to answer
those.
Okay.
So we've got a question over here.
Hello. I have a question to, I guess, most of the
presenters here.
When you used AI to digitize or to
recognize things,
and you do the quality review afterwards, have you noticed any
cases of hallucinations? And
if you didn't, is that a good sign because there weren't any, or is it a
bad sign because they were just undetected?
Probably Tanya actually want to answer the question.
Yeah. I can start answering this. So all the tools that we develop
are non-generative AI tools. This is machine learning, so there is no
hallucination, full stop. There are errors in
misclassification which are expected, and so we do review those,
and we very much evaluate
the accuracy
for different measures of accuracy for different contexts, typically trying
to
drive it all the
way sort of forward to the ecological task accuracy
rather than the unit machine learning accuracy.
And this is my very
strongly informed and strongly held opinion, that
accuracy on machine learning tasks is completely meaningful
because you get distribution shift and data changes and everything else the moment
you deploy it.
So you have to take it all the way to ecological task
accuracy.
Yeah. I was just going to say one on your paper,
Jacques, because I was... Yeah.
I think it's actually a really good question because a lot of the time when we
deploy these models, we get masses of information back,
enough or too much to actually validate. So where does that validation come in?
I think there's a couple of talks where you apply these
large language models, and the data that comes back is so humongous.
So how do you validate for those smaller degrees of hallucinations, and
can you find them? I think it's a really good question, but not one that I have
thought about addressing.
And an addition from Jenna, that she just texted me,
that
particularly for things like video-based
behavior or drone-based behavior,
what we find is that machine learning-based
classification data
analysis is much better than human.
One, because you have different perspective.
Two, because you can stop, rewind, review,
and verify much, much better. And so,
in fact, for behavior specifically, not just from drones,
but from all kinds of other data,
the behavioral traits, there is a whole project at Max Planck Animal Behavior
Institute where they're using full-on machine learning
to create latent spaces of
behavior. Because we don't even have names for a lot of units of
behavior.
It's a very under-named, not even under-labeled
area. But more generally, this is exactly the point
where, one, there is no hallucination because
no generative AI, and there is almost no way to
do this area purely from human observations.
Are you sure? We've still got five minutes.
We still have three minutes, and we don't actually have any questions
online.
Okay.
So any other questions or any acknowledgement?
Oh, there's one.
There's a question now. We've got time for one more.
It's not really a question. I just wanted to say I really enjoyed this session, and
I would like to see more of that. And one thing I was
struggling with is actually posing the questions reasonably.
I had questions to some of the presenters, but they wouldn't fit into the
one-minute thingy.
And then I had to find my way through the app, and I'm not even sure that they're
actually listening there to the app.
Maybe you can talk a little bit about that process.
So the process in general?
Yeah. How is feedback supposed to happen
if time is limited for Q&A?
Well, we've had lightning sessions before in other conferences
without the apps and stuff.
It's difficult because we could have seven minutes per person, but again, we need
the minutes to shift over. I think what we need is just some better aids at the end
so that people can trigger their memory as to what the talks were, who they were,
and just point. And I think it's absolutely doable.
We just need to support that final Q&A process a bit more,
which I don't think Jack and I...
I just think we didn't really think about that.
Great question. I think we're out of time.
If I can ask the presenters to come up for a photo,
and then do ask them afterwards,
and just ask them what their talk was about, if you can't remember.
If anyone-
Thank you so much. And please give an applause to all the presenters.
If you have any extra questions, I want to actually ask the
presenters. The Whova app actually do have a poll so
you can actually try to contact them or even for some sort of-
What are we doing this?
... collaborations. Yeah. And thanks to everyone.
My phone's out of battery. Get them up here.
Come up here.
We don't have a picture of them. It'll just be one slide.
We should. That was fun. But I don't think we have a combined slide of all of
them.
No. We need to do that next time. Yeah. Yeah, it is a little bit tricky.
Take this one. Yeah, sure.
We should workshop. Yeah. Because I don't know
what
you think.
So
Thursday and Friday?
Yeah. There will be no presentations.
There
will
be Fabien.